<RULE>
<PREAMB>
<AGENCY TYPE="N">DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE</AGENCY>
<SUBAGY>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives</SUBAGY>
<CFR>27 CFR Parts 447, 478, and 479</CFR>
<DEPDOC>[ATF No. 2024R-01F]</DEPDOC>
<RIN>RIN 1140-AA60</RIN>
<SUBJECT>Revising Machine Gun Definition in Response to Supreme Court Decision</SUBJECT>
<AGY>
<HD SOURCE="HED">AGENCY:</HD>
<P>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, Department of Justice.</P>
</AGY>
<ACT>
<HD SOURCE="HED">ACTION:</HD>
<P>Final rule.</P>
</ACT>
<SUM>
<HD SOURCE="HED">SUMMARY:</HD>
<P>
The Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (“ATF”) is amending Department of Justice (“Department”) regulations in response to the Supreme Court's decision in
<E T="03">Garland</E>
v.
<E T="03">Cargill.</E>
The Supreme Court held that ATF exceeded its statutory authority in its December 2018 final rule titled “Bump-Stock-Type Devices” by classifying a bump stock as a “machine gun” because a semi-automatic rifle equipped with a non-mechanical bump-stock-type device is not a “machine gun” under the National Firearms Act. Accordingly, ATF is removing from the three regulatory definitions of “machine gun” the two sentences that incorporated bump stocks into those definitions.
</P>
</SUM>
<EFFDATE>
<HD SOURCE="HED">DATES:</HD>
<P>This final rule is effective on May 6, 2026.</P>
</EFFDATE>
<FURINF>
<HD SOURCE="HED">FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:</HD>
<P>
Office of Regulatory Affairs, by email at
<E T="03">ORA@atf.gov,</E>
by mail at Office of Regulatory Affairs; Enforcement Programs and Services; Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives; 99 New York Ave NE; Washington, DC 20226, or by telephone at 202-648-7070 (this is not a toll-free number).
</P>
</FURINF>
</PREAMB>
<SUPLINF>
<HD SOURCE="HED">SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION:</HD>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">I. Background</HD>
<P>
The Attorney General is responsible for enforcing the Gun Control Act (“GCA”), as amended, and the National Firearms Act (“NFA”), as amended.
<SU>1</SU>
<FTREF/>
This includes the authority to promulgate regulations necessary to enforce the provisions of the GCA and NFA.
<E T="03">See</E>
18 U.S.C. 926(a); 26 U.S.C. 7805(a). Congress and the Attorney General have delegated the responsibility for administering and enforcing the GCA and NFA to the Director of ATF (“Director”), subject to the direction of the Attorney General and the Deputy Attorney General.
<E T="03">See</E>
28 U.S.C. 599A(b)(1), (c)(1); 28 CFR 0.130(a)(1)-(2); Treas. Order No. 221(2)(a), (d); 37 FR 11696-97 (June 10, 1972).
<SU>2</SU>
<FTREF/>
Accordingly, the Department and ATF have promulgated regulations implementing both the GCA and the NFA in 27 CFR parts 478, 479.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>1</SU>
 Some NFA and GCA provisions still refer to the “Secretary of the Treasury.” However, the Homeland Security Act of 2002, Public Law 107-296, 116 Stat. 2135, transferred the functions of ATF from the Department of the Treasury to the Department of Justice, under the general authority of the Attorney General. 26 U.S.C. 7801(a)(2); 28 U.S.C. 599A(c)(1). Thus, for ease of reference, this final rule refers to the Attorney General where relevant.
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>2</SU>
 In Attorney General Order Number 6353-2025, the Attorney General delegated authority to the Director to issue regulations pertaining to matters within ATF's jurisdiction, including under the NFA, GCA, and Title XI of the Organized Crime Control Act. ATF's jurisdiction also includes the Arms Export Control Act and the Contraband Cigarette Trafficking Act.
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>
Following a February 20, 2018, Presidential memorandum,
<SU>3</SU>
<FTREF/>
the Department amended ATF regulations by issuing a final rule titled “Bump-Stock-Type Devices” (“2018 final rule”), which determined that rifles with an attached bump-stock-type device constituted “machine guns” under Federal law.
<SU>4</SU>
<FTREF/>
On June 14, 2024, the Supreme Court held that “a semiautomatic rifle equipped with a [non-mechanical] bump stock is not a `machinegun' because it cannot fire more than one shot `by a single function of the trigger.' And, even if it could, it would not do so `automatically.'” 
<SU>5</SU>
<FTREF/>
The regulatory definition of “machine gun” does not distinguish between non-mechanical and mechanical bump stocks and simply states “bump-stock-type device.” ATF will rely on the statutory definition, as well as federal case law, such as
<E T="03">Cargill,</E>
that further defines terms within the “machine gun” definition such as “single function of the trigger” and “automatically.”
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>3</SU>
 On February 20, 2018, President Trump issued a memorandum instructing the Attorney General “to dedicate all available resources to . . . propose for notice and comment a rule banning all devices that turn legal weapons into machineguns.” Presidential Memorandum (Application of the Definition of Machinegun to “Bump Fire” Stocks and Other Similar Devices), 83 FR 7949 (Feb. 20, 2018); U.S. Dep't of Justice,
<E T="03">Attorney General Sessions Announces Regulation Effectively Banning Bump Stocks</E>
(Mar. 23, 2018),
<E T="03">https://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/attorney-general-sessions-announces-regulation-effectively-banning-bump-stocks</E>
[
<E T="03">https://perma.cc/S7DZ-76XD</E>
].
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>4</SU>
 83 FR 66514 (Dec. 26, 2018); 84 FR 9239 (Mar. 14, 2019) (ratifying final rule).
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>5</SU>
 
<E T="03">Garland</E>
v.
<E T="03">Cargill,</E>
602 U.S. 406, 415 (2024).
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>
ATF is now taking steps to conform its regulations with the Supreme Court's decision in
<E T="03">Cargill.</E>
This final rule removes from the Code of Federal Regulations (“CFR”) the revised portions of the regulatory definitions of “machine gun” that included bump stocks. Removing these portions of the previous final rule restores the regulatory text for those definitions to what it was prior to the December 2018 rule, with one minor exception.
<SU>6</SU>
<FTREF/>
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>6</SU>
 Consistent with the Supreme Court's decision, ATF is not reinserting the sentence segment “is a firearm originally designed to fire, or capable of being fired fully automatically by a single pull of the trigger” in the pre-rule definition of “machinegun” found in 27 CFR 447.11, nor is it removing the sentence that includes frames and receivers, conversion parts, and combinations of parts in the definition. See discussion below.
</P>
</FTNT>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">II. Final Rule</HD>
<P>
Under the NFA, as amended, and the GCA, as amended, the term “machinegun” means “any weapon which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger.” 26 U.S.C. 5845(b);
<E T="03">see</E>
18 U.S.C. 921(a)(24) (referencing the NFA definition). The term “machinegun” also includes “the frame or receiver of any such weapon” or any part or combination of parts designed and intended “for use in converting a weapon into a machinegun,” and “any combination of parts from which a machinegun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.” 26 U.S.C. 5845(b). This statutory definition uses the key terms “single function of the trigger” and “automatically,” but those terms are not defined in the statutory text. Before the 2018 final rule, the regulations contained definitions for the term “machine gun” in 27 CFR 478.11 and 479.11, that mirrored the NFA's statutory definition.
</P>
<P>
The definition of “machinegun” in 27 CFR 447.11, promulgated pursuant to the portion of section 38 of the Arms Export Control Act (“AECA”) (22 U.S.C. 2778) delegated to the Attorney General by section 1(n)(ii) of Executive Order 13637, 78 FR 16129 (Mar. 13, 2013), is similar, but not identical. Before the 2018 final rule, the definition of machine gun in 27 CFR 447.11 provided that a “`machinegun,' `machine pistol,' `submachinegun,' or `automatic rifle' is a firearm originally designed to fire, or capable of being fired fully
<PRTPAGE P="24349"/>
automatically by a single pull of the trigger.” However, it did not use the NFA's terminology — “is a firearm which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger” — nor did it contain the additional sentence that included machinegun frames and receivers, conversion parts, and combinations of parts, both of which were present in the NFA's statutory definition and the definitions in §§ 478.11 and 479.11.
</P>
<P>The 2018 final rule promulgated amendments to all these regulatory definitions to add bump-stock-type-devices. Specifically, the previous final rule amended these definitions by: (1) adding definitions to clarify the meaning of “automatically” and “single function of the trigger;” and (2) expressly including bump-stock-type-devices as machine guns. The 2018 final rule also harmonized the definition of “machinegun” in § 447.11 with the NFA's statutory definition and the “machine gun” definitions in §§ 478.11 and 479.11. This harmonization in § 447.11 included: (1) changing the sentence segment “is a firearm originally designed to fire, or capable of being fired fully automatically by a single pull of the trigger” to the NFA's segment “is a firearm which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger;” and (2) adding the sentence from the NFA that includes machine gun frames and receivers, conversion parts, and combinations of parts.</P>
<P>
On June 14, 2024, the Supreme Court issued its decision in
<E T="03">Cargill,</E>
in which it found that ATF exceeded its statutory authority in promulgating the rule classifying a bump stock as a machine gun. The Court effectively invalidated the rule's sentence defining “automatically” and “single function of the trigger,” and the sentence expressly including bump-stock-type devices as machine guns.
<SU>7</SU>
<FTREF/>
This rule updates ATF's corresponding regulatory provisions within parts 447, 478, and 479 to conform to the Court's decision by removing those two sentences in all three regulations. This rule also makes a minor technical amendment to move the commas in § 447.11's definition inside the quotation marks in conformity with standard American punctuation. These changes are shown in the table below:
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>7</SU>
 
<E T="03">Cargill,</E>
602 U.S. at 407-08.
</P>
</FTNT>
<GPOTABLE COLS="4" OPTS="L2,nj,tp0,p7,7/8,i1" CDEF="xs80,xl50,xl50,xl50">
<TTITLE> </TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">
Regulatory definition
<LI>(divided by sentence)</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Before 2018 final rule</CHED>
<CHED H="1">After 2018 final rule</CHED>
<CHED H="1">After this rule</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">§ 447.11</ENT>
<ENT>
<E T="03">Machinegun.</E>
A “machinegun”, “machine pistol”, “submachinegun”, or “automatic rifle” is a firearm originally designed to fire, or capable of being fired fully automatically by a single pull of the trigger.
</ENT>
<ENT>
<E T="03">Machinegun.</E>
A “machinegun”, “machine pistol”, “submachinegun”, or “automatic rifle” is a firearm which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger.
</ENT>
<ENT>
<E T="03">Machinegun.</E>
A “machinegun,” “machine pistol,” “submachinegun,” or “automatic rifle” is a firearm which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger.
</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT O="xl"> </ENT>
<ENT>The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machinegun, and any combination of parts from which a machinegun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.</ENT>
<ENT>The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machinegun, and any combination of parts from which a machinegun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT O="xl"> </ENT>
<ENT>For purposes of this definition, the term “automatically” as it modifies “shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot,” means functioning as the result of a self-acting or self-regulating mechanism that allows the firing of multiple rounds through a single function of the trigger; and “single function of the trigger” means a single pull of the trigger and analogous motions.</ENT>
<ENT/>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT O="xl"> </ENT>
<ENT>
The term “machinegun” includes a bump-stock-type device,
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
a device that allows a semi-automatic firearm to shoot more than one shot with a single pull of the trigger by harnessing the recoil energy of the semi-automatic firearm to which it is affixed so that the trigger resets and continues firing without additional physical manipulation of the trigger by the shooter.
</ENT>
<ENT/>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">§ 478.11 and 479.11</ENT>
<ENT>
<E T="03">Machine gun.</E>
Any weapon which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger.
</ENT>
<ENT>
<E T="03">Machine gun.</E>
Any weapon which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger.
</ENT>
<ENT>
<E T="03">Machine gun.</E>
Any weapon which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger.
</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<PRTPAGE P="24350"/>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT>The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machine gun, and any combination of parts from which a machine gun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.</ENT>
<ENT>The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machine gun, and any combination of parts from which a machine gun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.</ENT>
<ENT>The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machine gun, and any combination of parts from which a machine gun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT O="xl"> </ENT>
<ENT>For purposes of this definition, the term “automatically” as it modifies “shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot,” means functioning as the result of a self-acting or self-regulating mechanism that allows the firing of multiple rounds through a single function of the trigger; and “single function of the trigger” means a single pull of the trigger and analogous motions.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT O="xl"> </ENT>
<ENT>
The term “machine gun” includes a bump-stock-type device,
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
a device that allows a semi-automatic firearm to shoot more than one shot with a single pull of the trigger by harnessing the recoil energy of the semi-automatic firearm to which it is affixed so that the trigger resets and continues firing without additional physical manipulation of the trigger by the shooter.
</ENT>
<ENT/>
</ROW>
</GPOTABLE>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">III. Statutory and Executive Order Review</HD>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Administrative Procedure Act</HD>
<P>
Under the Administrative Procedure Act, 5 U.S.C. 553(b)(B), an agency may, for good cause, find that the usual requirements of prior notice and comment are impracticable, unnecessary, or contrary to the public interest. As described above, this rule simply removes the sentences added by the 2018 final rule in conformity with the Supreme Court's decision in
<E T="03">Cargill.</E>
These conforming updates to ATF regulations in parts 447, 478, and 479 are to ensure consistency with the
<E T="03">Cargill</E>
decision, thus avoiding any public confusion that may result from reliance on regulatory provisions that have been held to exceed statutory authority. Because this rule merely responds to the Supreme Court's decision, ATF finds it unnecessary to publish this rule for public notice and comment.
<E T="03">See McChesney</E>
v.
<E T="03">Petersen,</E>
275 F. Supp. 3d 1123, 1136 (D. Neb. 2016) (“No notice and commentary could have altered the Commission's obligation to implement the 2013 Congressional extension . . . Accordingly, . . . notice and comment [was] unnecessary under 553(b)(B).”);
<E T="03">In re Oil Spill by the Oil Rig “Deepwater Horizon” in the Gulf of Mexico on April 20, 2010,</E>
2015 WL 729701, at *4 (E.D. La. Feb. 19, 2015) (The “EPA had no discretion—it was required by Congress to adjust the penalty according to the formula. As a result, the usual notice and comment procedure was unnecessary in this instance.”). On the same basis, this rule is made effective upon publication because ATF finds good cause for an immediate effective date, as delaying the effective date of the conforming amendments would not serve the public interest (5 U.S.C. 553(d)(3)).
</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Executive Orders 12866 and 13563</HD>
<P>Executive Order 12866 (Regulatory Planning and Review) directs agencies to assess the costs and benefits of available regulatory alternatives and, if regulation is necessary, to select regulatory approaches that maximize net benefits.</P>
<P>Executive Order 13563 (Improving Regulation and Regulatory Review) emphasizes the importance of agencies quantifying both costs and benefits, reducing costs, harmonizing rules, and promoting public flexibility.</P>
<P>This rule removes previously added language to conform the ATF's regulations with the Supreme Court's decision without increasing costs. The Office of Management and Budget (“OMB”) has determined that this rule is a “significant regulatory action,” although not economically significant, under Executive Order 12866. It has therefore been reviewed by OMB pursuant to section 3(d)(3) of Executive Order 12866. ATF provides the following analysis to comply with Executive Orders 12866 and 13563.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">1. Benefits</HD>
<P>ATF estimates that this rule will result in quantifiable benefits to the public in the form of future production and sales, and some qualitative benefits due to recovered bump stocks and more options in firearms accessories in the future.</P>
<P>
In the 2018 final rule, ATF evaluated public comments received in response to its proposed rule and performed an analysis of the estimated “foregone future production and sales” for the 2018 final rule.
<SU>8</SU>
<FTREF/>
Since this final rule is rescinding provisions that were implemented by the 2018 final rule, ATF used—and updated—the foregone future production and sales from the 2018 final rule as a measure of overall quantitative benefits that will accrue from this final rule.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>8</SU>
 
<E T="03">See</E>
footnote 4,
<E T="03">supra.</E>
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>
In the 2018 final rule, ATF estimated that 62,084 bump stocks were produced per year. However, at that time, there had been no legal decision on whether bump stocks would be found to convert firearms into machine guns or not, so some persons who otherwise might have produced or purchased them might not have done so.
<SU>9</SU>
<FTREF/>
As a result, the future production estimate from 2018 is likely
<PRTPAGE P="24351"/>
lower than future bump stock production will be post-
<E T="03">Cargill.</E>
So, ATF notes that the production rate in this analysis is likely to result in an underestimate of the potential future revenue from bump stocks.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>9</SU>
 ATF notes that 62,084 bump stocks purchased over the next ten years may be an underestimate. Prior to the publication of the 2018 final rule, the Supreme Court had not decided whether bump stocks converted firearms into machine guns or would be considered GCA firearm accessories. Now, with that assurance, firearm purchasers may buy more bump stocks in the future.
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>
Based on historical prices, the retail price of bump stocks ranged from $99.99 
<SU>10</SU>
<FTREF/>
to $453.51.
<SU>11</SU>
<FTREF/>
ATF used these historical retail prices in this analysis as a proxy for future bump stock retail prices, but updated these prices to account for inflation.
<SU>12</SU>
<FTREF/>
Using the date the information was accessed for the 2018 final rule, and updating these retail prices to 2025 dollars, ATF estimates that the current retail value of these bump stocks ranges between $133.04 to $603.41. For the purposes of this analysis, ATF rounded and weighted the 2025 price range costs to calculate an average of $330 per bump stock at 2025 prices. At an estimated future production rate of 62,084 multiplied by $330 per bump stock, ATF estimates that the annualized benefit from this rule will be a minimum of $20,487,720, or $204,877,200 over the course of ten years.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>10</SU>
 Bumpfire Systems,
<E T="03">What Is a Bump Fire?</E>
(2017),
<E T="03">https://web.archive.org/web/20170214195732/http://bumpfiresystems.com/</E>
(last visited April 7, 2026).
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>11</SU>
 Slide Fire,
<E T="03">AR15 Bump Fire Stocks</E>
(2015),
<E T="03">https://web.archive.org/web/20170128085532/http://www.slidefire.com/products/ar-platform</E>
(last visited April 7, 2026).
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>12</SU>
 U.S. Bureau of Lab. Stats.,
<E T="03">CPI Inflation Calculator, https://www.bls.gov/data/inflation_calculator.htm</E>
(last visited Jan. 6, 2026) (inflation to December 2025).
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>In addition, after the 2018 final rule was published, approximately 965 bump stocks were turned into ATF for disposal. People who turned in bump stocks to ATF have been provided the opportunity to retrieve them from ATF, which would provide them with a qualitative benefit in recovering foregone property. Overall, this rule will also now allow firearm purchasers more options to accessorize and modify their existing firearms.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">2. Costs</HD>
<P>No costs were attributed to this rule because this rule is upholding the Supreme Court decision to assess bump stocks as firearms accessories, and it is also deregulatory in that it removes restrictions on bump stock sales and purchases. It does not impose additional requirements or cause persons to incur new costs.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Executive Order 14192</HD>
<P>
Executive Order 14192 (Unleashing Prosperity Through Deregulation) requires an agency, unless prohibited by law, to identify at least ten existing regulations to be repealed or revised when the agency publicly proposes for notice-and-comment or otherwise promulgates a new regulation that qualifies as an Executive Order 14192 regulatory action (defined in OMB Memorandum M-25-20 as a final significant regulatory action under section 3(f) of Executive Order 12866 that imposes total costs greater than zero). In furtherance of this requirement, section 3(c) of Executive Order 14192 requires that any new incremental costs associated with such new regulations must, to the extent permitted by law, also be offset by eliminating existing costs associated with at least ten prior regulations. Although this rule is a significant regulatory action as defined by Executive Order 12866, it does not impose total costs greater than zero. This rule removes regulatory language to adhere to the Supreme Court's decision in
<E T="03">Cargill</E>
and imposes no costs. Therefore, this rule is an Executive Order 14192 deregulatory action (defined OMB Memorandum M-25-20 as a final action that imposes total costs less than zero) and ATF does not need to identify at least ten existing regulations to repeal or revise to account for the promulgation of this rule.
</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">D. Executive Order 14294</HD>
<P>Executive Order 14294 (Fighting Overcriminalization in Federal Regulations) requires agencies promulgating regulations with criminal regulatory offenses potentially subject to criminal enforcement to explicitly describe the conduct subject to criminal enforcement, the authorizing statutes, and the mens rea standard applicable to each element of those offenses. This final rule does not create a criminal regulatory offense and is thus exempt from Executive Order 14294 requirements.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">E. Executive Order 13132</HD>
<P>This rule will not have substantial direct effects on the states, the relationship between the federal government and the states, or the distribution of power and responsibilities among the various levels of government. Therefore, in accordance with section 6 of Executive Order 13132 (Federalism), the Director has determined that this rule does not impose substantial direct compliance costs on state and local governments, preempt state law, or meaningfully implicate federalism. It thus does not warrant preparing a federalism summary impact statement.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">F. Executive Order 12988</HD>
<P>This rule meets the applicable standards set forth in sections 3(a) and 3(b)(2) of Executive Order 12988 (Civil Justice Reform).</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">G. Regulatory Flexibility Act</HD>
<P>Under the Regulatory Flexibility Act (“RFA”), 5 U.S.C. 601-612, agencies are required to conduct a regulatory flexibility analysis of any rule subject to notice-and comment-rulemaking requirements unless the agency head certifies, including a statement of the factual basis, that the rule will not have a significant economic impact on a substantial number of small entities or the rule is exempt from notice-and-comment rulemaking requirements under 5 U.S.C. 553(b) or other law. 5 U.S.C. 603(a), 604(a). Small entities include certain small businesses, small not-for-profit organizations that are independently owned and operated and are not dominant in their fields, and governmental jurisdictions with populations of less than 50,000.</P>
<P>In accordance with the RFA, 5 U.S.C. 603, 604, and 605(b), a Regulatory Flexibility Analysis is not required for this final rule because ATF was not required to publish a general NPRM for this matter. In addition, the Director certifies, after consideration, that this rule would not have a significant economic impact on a substantial number of small entities as it removes previously added requirements, thereby also removing any costs or burdens of complying with them.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">H. Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995</HD>
<P>This rule does not include a federal mandate that might result in the expenditure by state, local, and tribal governments, in the aggregate, or by the private sector, of $100 million or more in any one year, and it will not significantly or uniquely affect small governments. Therefore, ATF has determined that no actions are necessary under the provisions of the Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995 (“UMRA”). Regardless, like the RFA, the UMRA does not apply here because no NPRM was required to precede this final rule. 2 U.S.C. 1532(a).</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">I. Paperwork Reduction Act of 1995</HD>
<P>
Under the Paperwork Reduction Act of 1995 (“PRA”), 44 U.S.C. 3501-3521, agencies are required to submit to OMB, for review and approval, any information collection requirements a rule creates or any impacts it has on existing information collections. An information collection includes any reporting, record-keeping, monitoring,
<PRTPAGE P="24352"/>
posting, labeling, or other similar actions an agency requires of the public.
<E T="03">See</E>
5 CFR 1320.3(c). This rule does not create any new information collection requirements or impact any existing ones covered by the PRA.
</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">J. Congressional Review Act</HD>
<P>This rule is not a major rule as defined by the Congressional Review Act, 5 U.S.C. 804.</P>
<LSTSUB>
<HD SOURCE="HED">List of Subjects</HD>
<CFR>27 CFR Part 447</CFR>
<P>Administrative practice and procedure, Arms and munitions, Chemicals, Customs duties and inspection, Imports, Penalties, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Scientific equipment, Seizures and forfeitures.</P>
<CFR>27 CFR Part 478</CFR>
<P>Administrative practice and procedure, Arms and munitions, Exports, Freight, Imports, Intergovernmental relations, Law enforcement officers, Military personnel, Penalties, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Research, Seizures and forfeitures, Transportation.</P>
<CFR>27 CFR Part 479</CFR>
<P>Administrative practice and procedure, Arms and munitions, Exports, Imports, Military personnel, Penalties, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Seizures and forfeitures, Taxes, and Transportation.</P>
</LSTSUB>
<P>For the reasons discussed in the preamble, ATF is amending 27 CFR parts 447, 478, and 479 as follows:</P>
<PART>
<HD SOURCE="HED">PART 447—IMPORTATION OF ARMS, AMMUNITION AND IMPLEMENTS OF WAR</HD>
</PART>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="447">
<AMDPAR>1. The authority citation for 27 CFR part 447 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<AUTH>
<HD SOURCE="HED">Authority: </HD>
<P>22 U.S.C. 2778, E.O. 13637, 78 FR 16129 (Mar. 8, 2013).</P>
</AUTH>
</REGTEXT>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§ 447.11 </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
</SECTION>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="447">
<AMDPAR>2. Revise § 447.11 to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
    <SECTNO>§ 447.11</SECTNO>
    <SUBJECT>Meaning of terms.</SUBJECT>
    <P>When used in this part and in forms prescribed under this part, where not otherwise distinctly expressed or manifestly incompatible with the intent thereof, terms shall have the meanings ascribed in this section. Words in the plural form shall include the singular, and vice versa, and words imparting the masculine gender shall include the feminine. The terms “includes” and “including” do not exclude other things not enumerated which are in the same general class or are otherwise within the scope thereof.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Appropriate ATF officer.</E>
            An officer or employee of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF) specified by ATF Order 1130.34, Delegation of the Director's Authorities in 27 CFR Part 447, Importation of Arms, Ammunition and Implements of War.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Article.</E>
            Any of the defense articles enumerated in the U.S. Munitions Import List (USMIL).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Bureau.</E>
            Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, the Department of Justice.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Carbine.</E>
            A short-barrelled rifle whose barrel is generally not longer than 22 inches and is characterized by light weight.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">CFR.</E>
            The Code of Federal Regulations.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Chemical agent.</E>
            A substance useful in war which, by its ordinary and direct 
        <PRTPAGE P="7"/>
        chemical action, produces a powerful physiological effect.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Defense articles.</E>
            Any item designated in § 447.21 or § 447.22. This term includes models, mockups, and other such items which reveal technical data directly relating to § 447.21 or § 447.22.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Defense services.</E>
            (a) The furnishing of assistance, including training, to foreign persons in the design, engineering, development, production, processing, manufacture, use, operation, overhaul, repair, maintenance, modification, or reconstruction of defense articles, whether in the United States or abroad; or
    </P>
    <P>(b) The furnishing to foreign persons of any technical data, whether in the United States or abroad.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Director.</E>
            The Director, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, the Department of Justice, Washington, DC 20226.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Executed under the penalties of perjury.</E>
            Signed with the prescribed declaration under the penalties of perjury as provided on or with respect to the application, form, or other document or, where no form of declaration is prescribed, with the declaration: “I declare under the penalties of perjury that this ______ (insert type of document such as statement, certificate, application, or other document), including the documents submitted in support thereof, has been examined by me and, to best of my knowledge and belief, is true, correct, and complete.”
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Firearms.</E>
            A weapon, and all components and parts therefor, not over .50 caliber which will or is designed to or may be readily converted to expel a projectile by the action of an explosive, but shall not include BB and pellet guns, and muzzle loading (black powder) firearms (including any firearm with a matchlock, flintlock, percussion cap, or similar type of ignition system) or firearms covered by Category I(a) established to have been manufactured in or before 1898.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Frame or receiver.</E>
            The term “frame or receiver” shall have the same meaning as in § 478.12.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Import or importation.</E>
            Bringing into the United States from a foreign country any of the articles on the Import List, but shall not include intransit, temporary import or temporary export transactions subject to Department of State controls under Title 22, Code of Federal Regulations.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Import List.</E>
            The list of articles contained in § 447.21 and identified therein as “The U.S. Munitions Import List”.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Machinegun.</E>
            A “machinegun,” “machine pistol,” “submachinegun,” or “automatic rifle” is a firearm which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger. The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machinegun, and any combination of parts from which a machinegun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Permit.</E>
            The same as “license” for purposes of 22 U.S.C. 1934(c).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Person.</E>
            A partnership, company, association, or corporation, as well as a natural person.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Pistol.</E>
            A hand-operated firearm having a chamber integral with, or permanently aligned with, the bore.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Privately made firearm.</E>
            The term “privately made firearm” shall have the same meaning as in § 478.11.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Revolver.</E>
            A hand-operated firearm with a revolving cylinder containing chambers for individual cartridges.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Rifle.</E>
            A shoulder firearm discharging bullets through a rifled barrel at least 16 inches in length, including combination and drilling guns.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Sporting type sight including optical.</E>
            A telescopic sight suitable for daylight 
        <PRTPAGE P="8"/>
        use on a rifle, shotgun, pistol, or revolver for hunting or target shooting.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">This chapter.</E>
            Title 27, Code of Federal Regulations, Chapter II (27 CFR Chapter II).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">United States.</E>
            When used in the geographical sense, includes the several States, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, the insular possessions of the United States, the District of Columbia, and any territory over which the United States exercises any powers of administration, legislation, and jurisdiction.
    </P>
    <SECAUTH>(26 U.S.C. 7805 (68A Stat. 917), 27 U.S.C. 205 (49 Stat. 981 as amended), 18 U.S.C. 926 (82 Stat. 959), and sec. 38, Arms Export Control Act (22 U.S.C. 2778, 90 Stat. 744))</SECAUTH>
    <CITA>[T.D. ATF-48, 43 FR 13535, Mar. 31, 1978; 44 FR 55840, Sept. 28, 1979, as amended by T.D. ATF-202, 50 FR 14382, Apr. 12, 1985; T.D. ATF-215, 50 FR 42158, Oct. 18, 1985; T.D. ATF-484, 67 FR 64526, Oct. 21, 2002; ATF-9F, 72 FR 72938, Dec. 26, 2007; ATF-50F, 78 FR 23677, Apr. 22, 2013; ATF 2013R-9F, 79 FR 46692, Aug. 11, 2014; ATF 2018R-22F, 83 FR 66553, Dec. 26, 2018]</CITA>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<PART>
<HD SOURCE="HED">PART 478—COMMERCE IN FIREARMS AND AMMUNITION</HD>
</PART>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>3. The authority citation for 27 CFR part 478 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<AUTH>
<HD SOURCE="HED">Authority: </HD>
<P>5 U.S.C. 552(a); 18 U.S.C. 847, 921-931; 44 U.S.C. 3504(h).</P>
</AUTH>
</REGTEXT>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§ 478.11 </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
</SECTION>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>4. Revise § 478.11 to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
    <SECTNO>§ 478.11</SECTNO>
    <SUBJECT>Meaning of terms.</SUBJECT>
    <P>When used in this part and in forms prescribed under this part, where not otherwise distinctly expressed or manifestly incompatible with the intent thereof, terms shall have the meanings ascribed in this subpart. Words in the plural form shall include the singular, and vice versa, and words importing the masculine gender shall include the feminine. The terms “includes” and “including” do not exclude other things not enumerated which are in the same general class or are otherwise within the scope thereof.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Act.</E>
            18 U.S.C. Chapter 44.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Adjudicated as a mental defective.</E>
            (a) A determination by a court, board, commission, or other lawful authority that a person, as a result of marked subnormal intelligence, or mental illness, incompetency, condition, or disease:
    </P>
    <P>
        (1) Is a danger to himself or to others; or
        <PRTPAGE P="21"/>
    </P>
    <P>(2) Lacks the mental capacity to contract or manage his own affairs.</P>
    <P>(b) The term shall include—</P>
    <P>(1) A finding of insanity by a court in a criminal case; and</P>
    <P>(2) Those persons found incompetent to stand trial or found not guilty by reason of lack of mental responsibility pursuant to articles 50a and 72b of the Uniform Code of Military Justice, 10 U.S.C. 850a, 876b.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Admitted to the United States for lawful hunting or sporting purposes.</E>
            (a) Is entering the United States to participate in a competitive target shooting event sponsored by a national, State, or local organization, devoted to the competitive use or other sporting use of firearms; or
    </P>
    <P>(b) Is entering the United States to display firearms at a sports or hunting trade show sponsored by a national, State, or local firearms trade organization, devoted to the competitive use or other sporting use of firearms.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Alien.</E>
            Any person not a citizen or national of the United States.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Alien illegally or unlawfully in the United States.</E>
            Aliens who are unlawfully in the United States are not in valid immigrant, nonimmigrant or parole status. The term includes any alien—
    </P>
    <P>(a) Who unlawfully entered the United States without inspection and authorization by an immigration officer and who has not been paroled into the United States under section 212(d)(5) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (INA);</P>
    <P>(b) Who is a nonimmigrant and whose authorized period of stay has expired or who has violated the terms of the nonimmigrant category in which he or she was admitted;</P>
    <P>(c) Paroled under INA section 212(d)(5) whose authorized period of parole has expired or whose parole status has been terminated; or</P>
    <P>(d) Under an order of deportation, exclusion, or removal, or under an order to depart the United States voluntarily, whether or not he or she has left the United States.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Ammunition.</E>
            Ammunition or cartridge cases, primers, bullets, or propellent powder designed for use in any firearm other than an antique firearm. The term shall not include (a) any shotgun shot or pellet not designed for use as the single, complete projectile load for one shotgun hull or casing, nor (b) any unloaded, non-metallic shotgun hull or casing not having a primer.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Antique firearm.</E>
            1. Any firearm (including any firearm with a matchlock, flintlock, percussion cap, or similar type of ignition system) manufactured in or before 1898;
    </P>
    <P>2. Any replica of any firearm described in paragraph (a) of this definition if such replica:</P>
    <P>i. Is not designed or redesigned for using rimfire or conventional centerfire fixed ammunition; or</P>
    <P>
        ii. Uses rimfire or conventional centerfire fixed ammunition that is no longer manufactured in the United States and that is not readily available in the ordinary channels of commercial trade; or
        <PRTPAGE P="22"/>
    </P>
    <P>3. Any muzzle loading rifle, muzzle loading shotgun, or muzzle loading pistol that is designed to use black powder, or a black powder substitute, and that cannot use fixed ammunition. For purposes of this paragraph (3), the term “antique firearm” does not include any weapon that incorporates a firearm frame or receiver, any firearm that is converted into a muzzle loading weapon, or any muzzle loading weapon that can be readily converted to fire fixed ammunition by replacing the barrel, bolt, breechblock, or any combination thereof.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Armor piercing ammunition.</E>
            Projectiles or projectile cores which may be used in a handgun and which are constructed entirely (excluding the presence of traces of other substances) from one or a combination of tungsten alloys, steel, iron, brass, bronze, beryllium copper, or depleted uranium; or full jacketed projectiles larger than .22 caliber designed and intended for use in a handgun and whose jacket has a weight of more than 25 percent of the total weight of the projectile. The term does not include shotgun shot required by Federal or State environmental or game regulations for hunting purposes, frangible projectiles designed for target shooting, projectiles which the Director finds are primarily intended to be used for sporting purposes, or any other projectiles or projectile cores which the Director finds are intended to be used for industrial purposes, including charges used in oil and gas well perforating devices.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">ATF officer.</E>
            An officer or employee of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF) authorized to perform any function relating to the administration or enforcement of this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Business premises.</E>
            The property on which the manufacturing or importing of firearms or ammunition or the dealing in firearms is or will be conducted. A private dwelling, no part of which is open to the public, shall not be recognized as coming within the meaning of the term.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Chief, Federal Firearms Licensing Center (FFLC).</E>
            The ATF official responsible for the issuance and renewal of licenses under this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Collector.</E>
            Any person who acquires, holds, or disposes of firearms as curios or relics.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Collection premises.</E>
            The premises described on the license of a collector as the location at which he maintains his collection of curios and relics.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Commerce.</E>
            Travel, trade, traffic, commerce, transportation, or communication among the several States, or between the District of Columbia and any State, or between any foreign country or any territory or possession and any State or the District of Columbia, or between points in the same State but through any other State or the District of Columbia or a foreign country.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Committed to a mental institution.</E>
            A formal commitment of a person to a mental institution by a court, board, commission, or other lawful authority. The term includes a commitment to a mental institution involuntarily. The term includes commitment for mental defectiveness or mental illness. It also includes commitments for other reasons, such as for drug use. The term does not include a person in a mental institution for observation or a voluntary admission to a mental institution.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Complete muffler or silencer device.</E>
            A firearm muffler or firearm silencer that contains all component parts necessary to function, whether or not assembled or operable.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Complete weapon.</E>
            A firearm other than a firearm muffler or firearm silencer that contains all component parts necessary to function, whether or not assembled or operable.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Controlled substance.</E>
            A drug or other substance, or immediate precursor, as defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act, 21 U.S.C. 802. The term includes, but is not limited to, marijuana, depressants, stimulants, and narcotic drugs. The term does not include distilled spirits, wine, malt beverages, or tobacco, as those terms are defined or used in Subtitle E of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Crime punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year.</E>
            Any Federal, State or foreign offense for which the maximum penalty, whether or not imposed, is capital punishment or imprisonment in excess of 1 year. The term 
        <PRTPAGE P="23"/>
        shall not include (a) any Federal or State offenses pertaining to antitrust violations, unfair trade practices, restraints of trade, or other similar offenses relating to the regulation of business practices or (b) any State offense classified by the laws of the State as a misdemeanor and punishable by a term of imprisonment of 2 years or less. What constitutes a conviction of such a crime shall be determined in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held. Any conviction which has been expunged or set aside or for which a person has been pardoned or has had civil rights restored shall not be considered a conviction for the purposes of the Act or this part, unless such pardon, expunction, or restoration of civil rights expressly provides that the person may not ship, transport, possess, or receive firearms, or unless the person is prohibited by the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held from receiving or possessing any firearms.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Curios or relics.</E>
            Firearms which are of special interest to collectors by reason of some quality other than is associated with firearms intended for sporting use or as offensive or defensive weapons. To be recognized as curios or relics, firearms must fall within one of the following categories:
    </P>
    <P>(a) Firearms which were manufactured at least 50 years prior to the current date, but not including replicas thereof;</P>
    <P>(b) Firearms which are certified by the curator of a municipal, State, or Federal museum which exhibits firearms to be curios or relics of museum interest; and</P>
    <P>(c) Any other firearms which derive a substantial part of their monetary value from the fact that they are novel, rare, bizarre, or because of their association with some historical figure, period, or event. Proof of qualification of a particular firearm under this category may be established by evidence of present value and evidence that like firearms are not available except as collector's items, or that the value of like firearms available in ordinary commercial channels is substantially less.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Customs officer.</E>
            Any officer of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, any commissioned, warrant, or petty officer of the Coast Guard, or any agent or other person authorized by law to perform the duties of a customs officer.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Dating relationship.</E>
            A relationship between individuals who have or have recently had a continuing serious relationship of a romantic or intimate nature. A casual acquaintanceship or ordinary fraternization in a business or social context does not constitute a dating relationship. Whether a relationship constitutes a dating relationship shall be determined based on consideration of—
    </P>
    <P>1. The length of the relationship;</P>
    <P>2. The nature of the relationship; and</P>
    <P>3. The frequency and type of interaction between the individuals involved in the relationship.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Dealer.</E>
            Any person engaged in the business of selling firearms at wholesale or retail; any person engaged in the business of repairing firearms or of making or fitting special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms; or any person who is a pawnbroker. The term shall include any person who engages in such business or occupation on a part-time basis. The term shall include such activities wherever, or through whatever medium, they are conducted, such as at a gun show or event, flea market, auction house, or gun range or club; at one's home; by mail order; over the internet (
        <E T="03">e.g.,</E>
            online broker or auction); through the use of other electronic means (
        <E T="03">e.g.,</E>
            text messaging service, social media raffle, or website); or at any other domestic or international public or private marketplace or premises.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Destructive device.</E>
            (a) Any explosive, incendiary, or poison gas (1) bomb, (2) grenade, (3) rocket having a propellant charge of more than 4 ounces, (4) missile having an explosive or incendiary charge of more than one-quarter ounce, (5) mine, or (6) device similar to any of the devices described in the preceding paragraphs of this definition; (b) any type of weapon (other than a shotgun or a shotgun shell which the Director 
        <PRTPAGE P="24"/>
        finds is generally recognized as particularly suitable for sporting purposes) by whatever name known which will, or which may be readily converted to, expel a projectile by the action of an explosive or other propellant, and which has any barrel with a bore of more than one-half inch in diameter; and (c) any combination of parts either designed or intended for use in converting any device into any destructive device described in paragraph (a) or (b) of this section and from which a destructive device may be readily assembled. The term shall not include any device which is neither designed nor redesigned for use as a weapon; any device, although originally designed for use as a weapon, which is redesigned for use as a signalling, pyrotechnic, line throwing, safety, or similar device; surplus ordnance sold, loaned, or given by the Secretary of the Army pursuant to the provisions of section 4684(2), 4685, or 4686 of title 10, United States Code; or any other device which the Director finds is not likely to be used as a weapon, is an antique, or is a rifle which the owner intends to use solely for sporting, recreational, or cultural purposes.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Director.</E>
            The Director, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, the Department of Justice, Washington, DC.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Director of Industry Operations.</E>
            The principal ATF official in a Field Operations division responsible for administering regulations in this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Discharged under dishonorable conditions.</E>
            Separation from the U.S. Armed Forces resulting from a dishonorable discharge or dismissal adjudged by a general court-martial. The term does not include any separation from the Armed Forces resulting from any other discharge, e.g., a bad conduct discharge.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Division.</E>
            A Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives Division.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Drug trafficking crime.</E>
            1. Any felony punishable under the Controlled Substances Act (21 U.S.C. 801 
        <E T="03">et seq.</E>
        ), the Controlled Substances Import and Export Act (21 U.S.C. 951 
        <E T="03">et seq.</E>
        ), or 46 U.S.C. chapter 705; and
    </P>
    <P>2. Any felony punishable under the law of a State for which the conduct constituting the offense would constitute a felony punishable under the statutes cited in paragraph (1) of this definition.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Engaged in the business</E>
        1. Manufacturer of firearms.
            A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to manufacturing firearms as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the firearms manufactured;
    </P>
    <P>
        2. Manufacturer of ammunition.
            A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to manufacturing ammunition as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the ammunition manufactured;
    </P>
    <P>
        3. Dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or a pawnbroker. The term "engaged in the business as a dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or a pawnbroker" shall have the same meaning as in § 478.13.
    </P>
    <P>
        4. Gunsmith.
            A person who, as a service performed on existing firearms not for sale or distribution, devotes time, attention, and labor to repairing or customizing firearms, making or fitting special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms, or placing marks of identification on privately made firearms in accordance with this part, as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit, but such a term shall not include a person who occasionally repairs or customizes firearms (including identification), or occasionally makes or fits special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms. In the case of firearms for purposes of sale or distribution, such term shall include a person who performs repairs (e.g., by replacing worn or broken parts) on complete weapons, or places marks of identification on privately made firearms, but shall not include a person who manufactures firearms (i.e., frames or receivers or complete weapons) by completion, assembly, or applying coatings, or otherwise making them suitable for use, requiring a license as a manufacturer;
    </P>
    <P>
        5. Importer of firearms.
            A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to importing firearms as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit 
        <PRTPAGE P="24"/>
        through the sale or distribution of the firearms imported; and,
    </P>
    <P>
        6. Importer of ammunition.
            A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to importing ammunition as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the ammunition imported.
    </P>
    <P>
        7. Related definitions. For purposes of this definition—
    </P>
    <P>i. The term "purchase" (and derivative terms thereof) means the act of obtaining a firearm in an agreed exchange for something of value;</P>
    <P>ii. The term "sale" (and derivative terms thereof) means the act of disposing of a firearm in an agreed exchange for something of value, and the term "resale" means selling a firearm, including a stolen firearm, after it was previously sold by the original manufacturer or any other person; and</P>
    <P>iii. The term "something of value" includes money, credit, personal property (e.g., another firearm or ammunition), a service, a controlled substance, or any other medium of exchange or valuable consideration, legal or illegal.</P>
    <P><E T="03">Executed under penalties of perjury.</E>
    Signed with the prescribed declaration under the penalties of perjury as provided on or with respect to the return form, or other document or, where no form of declaration is prescribed, with the declaration:</P>
    <EXTRACT>
        <P>"I declare under the penalties of perjury that this—(insert type of document, such as, statement, application, request, certificate), including the documents submitted in support thereof, has been examined by me and, to the best of my knowledge and belief, is true, correct, and complete."</P>
    </EXTRACT>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Federal crime of terrorism.</E>
            Any offense as defined under 18 U.S.C. 2332b(g)(5).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Federal Firearms Act.</E>
            15 U.S.C. Chapter 18.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Felony.</E>
            Any offense under Federal or State law punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding one year.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Firearm.</E>
            Any weapon, including a starter gun, which will or is designed to or may readily be converted to expel a projectile by the action of an explosive; the frame or receiver of any such weapon; any firearm muffler or firearm silencer; or any destructive device; but the term shall not include an antique firearm. In the case of a licensed collector, the term shall mean only curios and relics. The term shall include a weapon parts kit that is designed to or may readily be completed, assembled, restored, or otherwise converted to expel a projectile by the action of an explosive. The term shall not include a weapon, including a weapon parts kit, in which the frame or receiver of such weapon is destroyed as described in the definition “frame or receiver”.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Firearm muffler or firearm silencer.</E>
            Any device for silencing, muffling, or diminishing the report of a portable firearm, including any combination of parts, designed or redesigned, and intended for use in assembling or fabricating a firearm silencer or firearm muffler, and any part intended only for use in such assembly or fabrication.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Former licensee inventory.</E>
            Firearms that were in the business inventory of a licensee at the time the license was terminated. Such firearms differ from a personal collection and other personal firearms in that they were purchased repetitively before the license was terminated as part of a licensee's business inventory with the predominant intent to earn a profit.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Frame or receiver.</E>
            The term “frame or receiver” shall have the same meaning as in § 478.12.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Friendly foreign government.</E>
            Any government with whom the United States has diplomatic relations and whom the United States has not identified as a State sponsor of terrorism.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Fugitive from justice.</E>
            Any person who has fled from any State to avoid prosecution for a felony or a misdemeanor; or any person who leaves the State to avoid giving testimony in any criminal proceeding. The term also includes any person who knows that misdemeanor or felony charges are pending against such person and who leaves the State of prosecution.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Handgun.</E>
            (a) Any firearm which has a short stock and is designed to be held and fired by the use of a single hand; and
    </P>
    <P>(b) Any combination of parts from which a firearm described in paragraph (a) can be assembled.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Hunting license or permit lawfully issued in the United States.</E>
            A license or 
        <PRTPAGE P="26"/>
        permit issued by a State for hunting which is valid and unexpired.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Identification document.</E>
            A document containing the name, residence address, date of birth, and photograph of the holder and which was made or issued by or under the authority of the United States Government, a State, political subdivision of a State, a foreign government, political subdivision of a foreign government, an international governmental or an international quasi- governmental organization which, when completed with information concerning a particular individual, is of a type intended or commonly accepted for the purpose of identification of individuals.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Importation.</E>
            The bringing of a firearm or ammunition into the United States; except that the bringing of a firearm or ammunition from outside the United States into a foreign-trade zone for storage pending shipment to a foreign country or subsequent importation into this country, pursuant to this part, shall not be deemed importation.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Importer.</E>
            Any person engaged in the business of importing or bringing firearms or ammunition into the United States. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Importer's or manufacturer's serial number.</E>
            The serial number placed by a licensee on a firearm, including any full or abbreviated license number, any such identification on a privately made firearm, or a serial number issued by the Director. For purposes of 18 U.S.C. 922(k) and § 478.34, the term shall include any associated licensee name, or licensee city or State placed on a frame or receiver.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Indictment.</E>
            Includes an indictment or information in any court, under which a crime punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year (as defined in this section) may be prosecuted, or in military cases to any offense punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year which has been referred to a general court-martial. An information is a formal accusation of a crime, differing from an indictment in that it is made by a prosecuting attorney and not a grand jury.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Interstate or foreign commerce.</E>
            Includes commerce between any place in a State and any place outside of that State, or within any possession of the United States (not including the Canal Zone) or the District of Columbia. The term shall not include commerce between places within the same State but through any place outside of that State.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Intimate partner.</E>
            With respect to a person, the spouse of the person, a former spouse of the person, an individual who is a parent of a child of the person, and an individual who cohabitates or has cohabitated with the person.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Large capacity ammunition feeding device.</E>
            A magazine, belt, drum, feed strip, or similar device for a firearm manufactured after September 13, 1994, that has a capacity of, or that can be readily restored or converted to accept, more than 10 rounds of ammunition. The term does not include an attached tubular device designed to accept, and capable of operating only with, .22 caliber rimfire ammunition, or a fixed device for a manually operated firearm, or a fixed device for a firearm listed in 18 U.S.C. 922, appendix A.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Licensed collector.</E>
            A collector of curios and relics only and licensed under the provisions of this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Licensed dealer.</E>
            A dealer licensed under the provisions of this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Licensed importer.</E>
            An importer licensed under the provisions of this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Licensed manufacturer.</E>
            A manufacturer licensed under the provisions of this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Local law enforcement authority.</E>
            A bureau, office, department, or other authority of a State or local government or Tribe that has jurisdiction to investigate a violation or potential violation of, or enforce, a State, local, or Tribal law.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Machine gun.</E>
            Any weapon which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger. The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machine gun, and any combination of parts from which a machine gun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Manufacturer.</E>
            Any person engaged in the business of manufacturing firearms or ammunition. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Mental institution.</E>
            Includes mental health facilities, mental hospitals, sanitariums, psychiatric facilities, and other facilities that provide diagnoses by licensed professionals of mental retardation or mental illness, including a psychiatric ward in a general hospital.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Misdemeanor crime of domestic violence.</E>
            1.
    </P>
    <P>
        i. Is a misdemeanor under Federal, State, Tribal, or local law or, in States which do not classify offenses as misdemeanors, is an offense punishable<PRTPAGE P="28631"/> by imprisonment for a term of one year or less, and includes offenses that are punishable only by a fine. (This is true whether or not the State statute specifically defines the offense as a “misdemeanor” or as a “misdemeanor crime of domestic violence.” The term includes all such misdemeanor convictions in Indian Courts established pursuant to 25 CFR part 11.);</P>
    <P>
        ii. Has, as an element, the use or attempted use of physical force (e.g., assault and battery), or the threatened use of a deadly weapon; and</P>
    <P>
        iii. Was committed by a current or former spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim, by a person with whom the victim shares a child in common, by a 
        <PRTPAGE P="26"/>
        person who is cohabiting with or has cohabited with the victim as a spouse, parent, or guardian, (e.g., the equivalent of a "common law" marriage even if such relationship is not recognized under the law), or a person similarly situated to a spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim (e.g., two persons who are residing at the same location in an intimate relationship with the intent to make that place their home would be similarly situated to a spouse).
    </P>
    <P>2. A person shall not be considered to have been convicted of such an offense for purposes of this part unless:</P>
    <P>i The person is considered to have been convicted by the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held.</P>
    <P>ii. The person was represented by counsel in the case, or knowingly and intelligently waived the right to counsel in the case; and</P>
    <P>iii. In the case of a prosecution for which a person was entitled to a jury trial in the jurisdiction in which the case was tried, either</P>
    <P>A. The case was tried by a jury, or</P>
    <P>B. The person knowingly and intelligently waived the right to have the case tried by a jury, by guilty plea or otherwise.</P>
    <P>3. A person shall not be considered to have been convicted of such an offense for purposes of this part if the conviction has been expunged or set aside, or is an offense for which the person has been pardoned or has had civil rights restored (if the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held provides for the loss of civil rights upon conviction for such an offense) unless the pardon, expunction, or restoration of civil rights expressly provides that the person may not ship, transport, possess, or receive firearms, and the person is not otherwise prohibited by the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held from receiving or possessing any firearms.
    </P>
    <P>
        4.
    </P>
    <P>
        i. Subject to paragraphs (4)(ii) and (iii) of this definition, a person shall not be considered to have been convicted of a misdemeanor crime of domestic violence against an individual in a dating relationship if the conviction has been expunged or set aside, or is an offense for which the person has been pardoned or has had firearm rights restored, unless the expungement, pardon, or restoration of rights expressly provides that the person may not ship, transport, possess, or receive firearms.
    </P>
    <P>
        ii. In the case of a person who has not more than one conviction of a misdemeanor crime of domestic violence against an individual in a dating relationship, and is not otherwise prohibited under 18 U.S.C. chapter 44, the person shall not be disqualified from shipping, transport, possession, receipt, or purchase of a firearm under 18 U.S.C. chapter 44 if:
    </P>
    <P>
        A. Five years have elapsed from the later of the judgment of conviction or the completion of the person's custodial or supervisory sentence, if any; and
    </P>
    <P>
        B. The person has not subsequently been convicted of another such offense, or any misdemeanor under Federal, State, local, or Tribal law that has, as an element, the use or attempted use of physical force, or the threatened use of a deadly weapon, or any other offense that would disqualify the person under 18 U.S.C. 922(g).
    </P>
    <P>
        iii. Restoration under paragraph (4)(ii) of this definition only removes the disqualification from shipping, transport, possession, receipt, or purchase of a firearm under this part. Restoration under paragraph (4)(ii) is not available for a current or former spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim; a person with whom the victim shares a child in common; a person who is cohabiting with or has cohabited with the victim as a spouse, parent, or guardian; or a person similarly situated to a spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">National Firearms Act.</E>
            26 U.S.C. Chapter 53.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">NICS.</E>
            The National Instant Criminal Background Check System established by the Attorney General pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 922(t).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Nonimmigrant alien.</E>
            An alien in the United States in a nonimmigrant classification as defined by section 101(a)(15) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(15)).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Nonimmigrant visa.</E>
            A visa properly issued to an alien as an eligible nonimmigrant by a competent officer as provided in the Immigration and Nationality Act, 8 U.S.C. 1101 
        <E T="03">et seq.</E>
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Pawnbroker.</E>
            Any person whose business or occupation includes the taking or receiving, by way of pledge or pawn, of any firearm as security for the payment or repayment of money. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Permanently inoperable.</E>
            A firearm which is incapable of discharging a shot by means of an explosive and incapable of being readily restored to a firing condition. An acceptable method of rendering most firearms permanently inoperable is to fusion weld the chamber closed and fusion weld the barrel solidly to the frame. Certain unusual firearms require other methods to render the firearm permanently inoperable. Contact ATF for instructions.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Person.</E>
            Any individual, corporation, company, association, firm, partnership, society, or joint stock company.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Personal collection (or personal collection of firearms, or personal firearms collection)</E>
        1. 
        <E T="03">General definition.</E>
            Personal firearms that a person accumulates for study, comparison, exhibition (
        <E T="03">e.g.,</E>
            collecting curios or relics, or collecting unique firearms to exhibit at gun club events), or for a hobby (
        <E T="03">e.g.,</E>
            noncommercial, recreational activities for personal enjoyment, such as hunting, skeet, target, or competition shooting, historical re-enactment, or noncommercial firearms safety instruction). The term shall not include any firearm purchased for the purpose of resale with the predominant intent to earn a profit (
        <E T="03">e.g.,</E>
            primarily for a commercial purpose or financial gain, as distinguished from personal firearms a person accumulates for study, comparison, exhibition, or for a hobby, but which the person may also intend to increase in value). In addition, the term shall not include firearms accumulated primarily for personal protection: 
        <E T="03">Provided,</E>
            that nothing in this definition shall be construed as precluding 
        <PRTPAGE P="29"/>
        a person from lawfully acquiring firearms for self-protection or other lawful personal use.
    </P>
    <P>
        2. 
        <E T="03">Personal collection of licensee.</E>
            In the case of a firearm imported, manufactured, or otherwise acquired by a licensed manufacturer, licensed importer, or licensed dealer, the term shall include only a firearm described in paragraph (1) of this definition that was—
    </P>
    <P>i. Acquired or transferred without the intent to willfully evade the restrictions placed upon licensees under 18 U.S.C. chapter 44;</P>
    <P>ii. Recorded by the licensee as an acquisition in the licensee's acquisition and disposition record in accordance with § 478.122(a), § 478.123(a), or § 478.125(e) (unless acquired prior to licensure and not intended for sale);</P>
    <P>iii. Recorded as a disposition from the licensee's business inventory to the licensee's personal collection or otherwise as a personal firearm in accordance with § 478.122(a), § 478.123(a), or § 478.125(e) (unless acquired prior to licensure and not intended for sale);</P>
    <P>iv. Maintained in such personal collection or otherwise as a personal firearm (whether on or off the business premises) for at least one year from the date the firearm was so transferred, in accordance with 18 U.S.C. 923(c) and 27 CFR 478.125a; and</P>
    <P>
        v. Stored separately from, and not commingled with the business inventory. When stored or displayed on the business premises, the personal collection and other personal firearms shall be appropriately identified as “not for sale” (
        <E T="03">e.g.,</E>
            by attaching a tag).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Pistol.</E>
            A weapon originally designed, made, and intended to fire a projectile (bullet) from one or more barrels when held in one hand, and having (a) a chamber(s) as an integral part(s) of, or permanently aligned with, the bore(s); and (b) a short stock designed to be gripped by one hand and at an angle to and extending below the line of the bore(s).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Predominantly earn a profit.</E>
            The term “predominantly earn a profit” shall have the same meaning as in § 478.13.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Principal objective of livelihood and profit.</E>
            The intent underlying the sale or disposition of firearms is predominantly one of obtaining livelihood and pecuniary gain, as opposed to other intents such as improving or liquidating a personal firearms collection: 
        <E T="03">Provided,</E>
            That proof of profit shall not be required as to a person who engages in the regular and repetitive purchase and disposition of firearms for criminal purposes or terrorism. For purposes of this part, the term “terrorism” means activity, directed against United States persons, which—
    </P>
    <P>(a) Is committed by an individual who is not a national or permanent resident alien of the United States;</P>
    <P>(b) Involves violent acts or acts dangerous to human life which would be a criminal violation if committed within the jurisdiction of the United States; and</P>
    <P>(c) Is intended—</P>
    <P>(1) To intimidate or coerce a civilian population;</P>
    <P>(2) To influence the policy of a government by intimidation or coercion; or</P>
    <P>(3) To affect the conduct of a government by assassination or kidnapping.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Privately made firearm (PMF).</E>
            A firearm, including a frame or receiver, completed, assembled, or otherwise produced by a person other than a licensed manufacturer, and without a serial number placed by a licensed manufacturer at the time the firearm was produced. The term shall not include a firearm identified and registered in the National Firearms Registration and Transfer Record pursuant to chapter 53, title 26, United States Code, or any firearm manufactured or made before October 22, 1968 (unless remanufactured or remade after that date).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Published ordinance.</E>
            A published law of any political subdivision of a State which the Director determines to be relevant to the enforcement of this part and which is contained on a list compiled by the Director, which list is incorporated by reference in the 
        <E T="04">Federal Register,</E>
            revised annually, and furnished to licensees under this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Readily.</E>
            A process, action, or physical state that is fairly or reasonably efficient, quick, and easy, but not necessarily the most efficient, speediest, or easiest process, action, or physical state. With respect to the classification of firearms, factors relevant in making this determination include the following:
    </P>
    <P>
        1. Time, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            how long it takes to finish the process;
    </P>
    <P>
        2. Ease, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            how difficult it is to do so;
    </P>
    <P>
        3. Expertise, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            what knowledge and skills are required;
    </P>
    <P>
        4. Equipment, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            what tools are required;
    </P>
    <P>
        5. Parts availability, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            whether additional parts are required, and how easily they can be obtained;
    </P>
    <P>
        6. Expense, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            how much it costs;
    </P>
    <P>
        7. Scope, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            the extent to which the subject of the process must be changed to finish it; and
    </P>
    <P>
        8. Feasibility, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            whether the process would damage or destroy the subject of the process, or cause it to malfunction.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Renounced U.S. citizenship.</E>
            (a) A person has renounced his U.S. citizenship if the person, having been a citizen of the United States, has renounced citizenship either—
    </P>
    <P>(1) Before a diplomatic or consular officer of the United States in a foreign state pursuant to 8 U.S.C. 1481(a)(5); or</P>
    <P>(2) Before an officer designated by the Attorney General when the United States is in a state of war pursuant to 8 U.S.C. 1481(a)(6).</P>
    <P>(b) The term shall not include any renunciation of citizenship that has been reversed as a result of administrative or judicial appeal.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Responsible person.</E>
            Any individual possessing, directly or indirectly, the power to direct or cause the direction of the management and policies of a sole proprietorship, corporation, company, partnership, or association, insofar as they pertain to firearms.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Revolver.</E>
            A projectile weapon, of the pistol type, having a breechloading chambered cylinder so arranged that the cocking of the hammer or movement of the trigger rotates it and brings the next cartridge in line with the barrel for firing.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Rifle.</E>
            (a) A weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder, and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of an explosive to fire only a single projectile through a rifled bore for each single pull of the trigger.
    </P>
    <P>
        (1) For purposes of this definition, the term “designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder” shall include a weapon that is equipped with an accessory, component, or other rearward attachment (
        <E T="03">e.g.,</E>
            a “stabilizing brace”) that provides surface area that allows the weapon to be fired from the shoulder, provided other factors, as described in paragraph (2), indicate that the weapon is designed, made, and intended to be fired from the shoulder.
    </P>
    <P>(2) When a weapon provides surface area that allows the weapon to be fired from the shoulder, the following factors shall also be considered in determining whether the weapon is designed, made, and intended to be fired from the shoulder:</P>
    <P>(i) Whether the weapon has a weight or length consistent with the weight or length of similarly designed rifles;</P>
    <P>(ii) Whether the weapon has a length of pull, measured from the center of the trigger to the center of the shoulder stock or other rearward accessory, component or attachment (including an adjustable or telescoping attachment with the ability to lock into various positions along a buffer tube, receiver extension, or other attachment method), that is consistent with similarly designed rifles;</P>
    <P>(iii) Whether the weapon is equipped with sights or a scope with eye relief that require the weapon to be fired from the shoulder in order to be used as designed;</P>
    <P>(iv) Whether the surface area that allows the weapon to be fired from the shoulder is created by a buffer tube, receiver extension, or any other accessory, component, or other rearward attachment that is necessary for the cycle of operations;</P>
    <P>(v) The manufacturer's direct and indirect marketing and promotional materials indicating the intended use of the weapon; and</P>
    <P>(vi) Information demonstrating the likely use of the weapon in the general community.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Secure gun storage or safety device.</E>
            1. A device that, when installed on a firearm, is designed to prevent the firearm from being operated without first deactivating the device;
    </P>
    <P>2. A device incorporated into the design of the firearm that is designed to prevent the operation of the firearm by anyone not having access to the device; or</P>
    <P>3. A safe, gun safe, gun case, lock box, or other device that is designed to be or can be used to store a firearm and that is designed to be unlocked only by means of a key, a combination, or other similar means.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Semiautomatic assault weapon.</E>
            (a) Any of the firearms, or copies or duplicates of the firearms in any caliber, known as:
    </P>
    <P>
        (1) Norinco, Mitchell, and Poly Technologies Avtomat Kalashnikovs (all models),
        <PRTPAGE P="31"/>
    </P>
    <P>(2) Action Arms Israeli Military Industries UZI and Galil,</P>
    <P>(3) Beretta Ar70 (SC-70),</P>
    <P>(4) Colt AR-15,</P>
    <P>(5) Fabrique National FN/FAL, FN/LAR, and FNC,</P>
    <P>(6) SWD M-10, M-11, M-11/9, and M-12,</P>
    <P>(7) Steyr AUG,</P>
    <P>(8) INTRATEC TEC-9, TEC-DC9 and TEC-22, and</P>
    <P>(9) Revolving cylinder shotguns, such as (or similar to) the Street Sweeper and Striker 12;</P>
    <P>(b) A semiautomatic rifle that has an ability to accept a detachable magazine and has at least 2 of—</P>
    <P>(1) A folding or telescoping stock,</P>
    <P>(2) A pistol grip that protrudes conspicuously beneath the action of the weapon,</P>
    <P>(3) A bayonet mount,</P>
    <P>(4) A flash suppressor or threaded barrel designed to accommodate a flash suppressor, and</P>
    <P>(5) A grenade launcher;</P>
    <P>(c) A semiautomatic pistol that has an ability to accept a detachable magazine and has at least 2 of—</P>
    <P>(1) An ammunition magazine that attaches to the pistol outside of the pistol grip,</P>
    <P>(2) A threaded barrel capable of accepting a barrel extender, flash suppressor, forward handgrip, or silencer,</P>
    <P>(3) A shroud that is attached to, or partially or completely encircles, the barrel and that permits the shooter to hold the firearm with the nontrigger hand without being burned,</P>
    <P>(4) A manufactured weight of 50 ounces or more when the pistol is unloaded, and</P>
    <P>(5) A semiautomatic version of an automatic firearm; and</P>
    <P>(d) A semiautomatic shotgun that has at least 2 of—</P>
    <P>(1) A folding or telescoping stock,</P>
    <P>(2) A pistol grip that protrudes conspicuously beneath the action of the weapon,</P>
    <P>(3) A fixed magazine capacity in excess of 5 rounds, and</P>
    <P>(4) An ability to accept a detachable magazine.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Semiautomatic pistol.</E>
            Any repeating pistol which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Semiautomatic rifle.</E>
            Any repeating rifle which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Semiautomatic shotgun.</E>
            Any repeating shotgun which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Short-barreled rifle.</E>
            A rifle having one or more barrels less than 16 inches in length, and any weapon made from a rifle, whether by alteration, modification, or otherwise, if such weapon, as modified, has an overall length of less than 26 inches.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Short-barreled shotgun.</E>
            A shotgun having one or more barrels less than 18 inches in length, and any weapon made from a shotgun, whether by alteration, modification, or otherwise, if such weapon as modified has an overall length of less than 26 inches.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Shotgun.</E>
            A weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder, and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of an explosive to fire through a smooth bore either a number of ball shot or a single projectile for each single pull of the trigger.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">State.</E>
            A State of the United States. The term shall include the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and the possessions of the United States (not including the Canal Zone).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">State of residence.</E>
            The State in which an individual resides. An individual resides in a State if he or she is present in a State with the intention of making a home in that State. If an individual is on active duty as a member of the Armed Forces, the individual's State of residence is the State in which his or her permanent duty station is located, as stated in 18 U.S.C. 921(b). The following are examples that illustrate this definition:
    </P>
    <EXAMPLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 1.</HD>
        <P>
            A maintains a home in State X. A travels to State Y on a hunting, fishing, 
            <PRTPAGE P="32"/>
            business, or other type of trip. A does not become a resident of State Y by reason of such trip.
        </P>
    </EXAMPLE>
    <EXAMPLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 2.</HD>
        <P>A maintains a home in State X and a home in State Y. A resides in State X except for weekends or the summer months of the year and in State Y for the weekends or the summer months of the year. During the time that A actually resides in State X, A is a resident of State X, and during the time that A actually resides in State Y, A is a resident of State Y.</P>
    </EXAMPLE>
    <EXAMPLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 3.</HD>
        <P>A, an alien, travels to the United States on a three-week vacation to State X. A does not have a state of residence in State X because A does not have the intention of making a home in State X while on vacation. This is true regardless of the length of the vacation.</P>
    </EXAMPLE>
    <EXAMPLE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 4.</HD>
        <P>A, an alien, travels to the United States to work for three years in State X. A rents a home in State X, moves his personal possessions into the home, and his family resides with him in the home. A intends to reside in State X during the 3-year period of his employment. A is a resident of State X.</P>
    </EXAMPLE>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Terrorism.</E>
            For purposes of the definitions “predominantly earn a profit” and “principal objective of livelihood and profit,” the term “terrorism” means activity, directed against United States persons, which—
    </P>
    <P>1. Is committed by an individual who is not a national or permanent resident alien of the United States;</P>
    <P>2. Involves violent acts or acts dangerous to human life which would be a criminal violation if committed within the jurisdiction of the United States; and</P>
    <P>3. Is intended—</P>
    <P>i. To intimidate or coerce a civilian population;</P>
    <P>ii. To influence the policy of a government by intimidation or coercion; or</P>
    <P>iii. To affect the conduct of a government by assassination or kidnapping.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Unlawful user of or addicted to any controlled substance.</E>
        1. A person who uses a controlled substance and demonstrates a pattern of compulsively using the controlled substance, characterized by impaired control over use, is addicted to a controlled substance.
        </P>
        <P>2. A person who regularly uses a controlled substance over an extended period of time continuing into the present, without a lawful prescription or in a manner substantially different from that prescribed by a licensed physician, is an unlawful user of a controlled substance.</P>
        <P>i. Such unlawful use is not limited to using a controlled substance on a particular day, or within a matter of days before shipping, transporting, possessing, or receiving a firearm. Rather, unlawful use requires evidence that the person has unlawfully used the substance with sufficient regularity and recency to indicate that the individual is actively engaged in such conduct. A person may be an unlawful current user of a controlled substance even though the substance is not being used at the precise time the person seeks to acquire, ship, transport, receive, or possess the firearm.</P>
        <P>ii. A person is not an unlawful user of a controlled substance if the person has ceased regularly unlawfully using the substance, or if the person's unlawful use is isolated or sporadic or does not otherwise demonstrate a pattern of ongoing use. A person is also not an unlawful user if the person, while using a lawfully prescribed controlled substance, deviates slightly or immaterially from the instructions of the prescribing physician.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Unserviceable firearm.</E>
            A firearm which is incapable of discharging a shot by means of an explosive and is incapable of being readily restored to a firing condition.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">U.S.C.</E>
            The United States Code.
    </P>
    <SECAUTH>(5 U.S.C. 552(a), 80 Stat. 383, as amended; 18 U.S.C. 847 (84 Stat. 959); 18 U.S.C. 926 (82 Stat. 1226))</SECAUTH>
    <CITA>[T.D. ATF-48, 43 FR 13536, Mar. 31, 1978; 44 FR 55842, Sept. 28, 1979]</CITA>
    <EDNOTE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Editorial Note:</HD>
        <P>
            For 
            <E T="04">Federal Register</E>
                citations affecting § 478.11, see the List of CFR Sections Affected, which appears in the Finding Aids section of the printed volume and at 
            <E T="03">www.govinfo.gov.</E>
        </P>
    </EDNOTE>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<PART>
<HD SOURCE="HED">PART 479—MACHINE GUNS, DESTRUCTIVE DEVICES, AND CERTAIN OTHER FIREARMS</HD>
</PART>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="479">
<AMDPAR>5. The authority citation for 27 CFR part 479 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<AUTH>
<HD SOURCE="HED">Authority: </HD>
<P>26 U.S.C. 5812; 28 U.S.C. 5822; 26 U.S.C. 7801; 26 U.S.C. 7805.</P>
</AUTH>
</REGTEXT>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§ 479.11 </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
</SECTION>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="479">
<AMDPAR>6.Revise § 479.11 to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
    <SECTNO>§ 479.11</SECTNO>
    <SUBJECT>Meaning of terms.</SUBJECT>
    <P>
        When used in this part and in forms prescribed under this part, where not otherwise distinctly expressed or manifestly incompatible with the intent thereof, terms shall have the meanings ascribed in this section. Words in the plural form shall include the singular, and vice versa, and words importing the masculine gender shall include the feminine. The terms “includes” and “including” do not exclude other 
        <PRTPAGE P="83"/>
        things not enumerated which are in the same general class or are otherwise within the scope thereof.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Antique firearm.</E>
            Any firearm not designed or redesigned for using rim fire or conventional center fire ignition with fixed ammunition and manufactured in or before 1898 (including any matchlock, flintlock, percussion cap, or similar type of ignition system or replica thereof, whether actually manufactured before or after the year 1898) and also any firearm using fixed ammunition manufactured in or before 1898, for which ammunition is no longer manufactured in the United States and is not readily available in the ordinary channels of commercial trade.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Any other weapon.</E>
            Any weapon or device capable of being concealed on the person from which a shot can be discharged through the energy of an explosive, a pistol or revolver having a barrel with a smooth bore designed or redesigned to fire a fixed shotgun shell, weapons with combination shotgun and rifle barrels 12 inches or more, less than 18 inches in length, from which only a single discharge can be made from either barrel without manual reloading, and shall include any such weapon which may be readily restored to fire. Such term shall not include a pistol or a revolver having a rifled bore, or rifled bores, or weapons designed, made, or intended to be fired from the shoulder and not capable of firing fixed ammunition.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">ATF officer.</E>
            An officer or employee of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF) authorized to perform any function relating to the administration or enforcement of this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Complete muffler or silencer device.</E>
            A muffler or silencer that contains all component parts necessary to function, whether or not assembled or operable.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Complete weapon.</E>
            A firearm other than a muffler or silencer that contains all component parts necessary to function, whether or not assembled or operable.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Customs officer.</E>
            Any officer of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, any commissioned, warrant, or petty officer of the Coast Guard, or any agent or other person authorized by law to perform the duties of a customs officer.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Dealer.</E>
            Any person, not a manufacturer or importer, engaged in the business of selling, renting, leasing, or loaning firearms and shall include pawnbrokers who accept firearms as collateral for loans.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Destructive device.</E>
            (a) Any explosive, incendiary, or poison gas (1) bomb, (2) grenade, (3) rocket having a propellent charge of more than 4 ounces, (4) missile having an explosive or incendiary charge of more than one-quarter ounce, (5) mine, or (6) similar device; (b) any type of weapon by whatever name known which will, or which may be readily converted to, expel a projectile by the action of an explosive or other propellant, the barrel or barrels of which have a bore of more than one-half inch in diameter, except a shotgun or shotgun shell which the Director finds is generally recognized as particularly suitable for sporting purposes; and (c) any combination of parts either designed or intended for use in converting any device into a destructive device as described in paragraphs (a) and (b) of this definition and from which a destructive device may be readily assembled. The term shall not include any device which is neither designed or redesigned for use as a weapon; any device, although originally designed for use as a weapon, which is redesigned for use as a signaling, pyrotechnic, line throwing, safety, or similar device; surplus ordnance sold, loaned, or given by the Secretary of the Army under 10 U.S.C. 4684(2), 4685, or 4686, or any device which the Director finds is not likely to be used as a weapon, or is an antique or is a rifle which the owner intends to use solely for sporting purposes.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Director.</E>
            The Director, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, the Department of Justice, Washington, DC.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Director, Industry Operations.</E>
            The principal regional official responsible for administering regulations in this part.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Director of the Service Center.</E>
            A director of an Internal Revenue Service Center in an internal revenue region.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">District director.</E>
            A district director of the Internal Revenue Service in an internal revenue district.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Executed under penalties of perjury.</E>
            Signed with the prescribed declaration under the penalties of perjury as provided on or with respect to the return, form, or other document or, where no form of declaration is prescribed, with the declaration:
    </P>
    <EXTRACT>
        <P>
            “I declare under the penalties of perjury that this—(insert type of document, such as, 
            <PRTPAGE P="84"/>
            statement, application, request, certificate), including the documents submitted in support thereof, has been examined by me and, to the best of my knowledge and belief, is true, correct, and complete.”
        </P>
    </EXTRACT>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Exportation.</E>
            The severance of goods from the mass of things belonging to this country with the intention of uniting them to the mass of things belonging to some foreign country.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Exporter.</E>
            Any person who exports firearms from the United States.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Firearm.</E>
            (a) A shotgun having a barrel or barrels of less than 18 inches in length; (b) a weapon made from a shotgun if such weapon as modified has an overall length of less than 26 inches or a barrel or barrels of less than 18 inches in length; (c) a rifle having a barrel or barrels of less than 16 inches in length; (d) a weapon made from a rifle if such weapon as modified has an overall length of less than 26 inches or a barrel or barrels of less than 16 inches in length; (e) any other weapon, as defined in this subpart; (f) a machine gun; (g) a muffler or a silencer for any firearm whether or not such firearm is included within this definition; and (h) a destructive device. The term shall not include an antique firearm or any device (other than a machine gun or destructive device) which, although designed as a weapon, the Director finds by reason of the date of its manufacture, value, design, and other characteristics is primarily a collector's item and is not likely to be used as a weapon. For purposes of this definition, the length of the barrel having an integral chamber(s) on a shotgun or rifle shall be determined by measuring the distance between the muzzle and the face of the bolt, breech, or breech block when closed and when the shotgun or rifle is cocked. The overall length of a weapon made from a shotgun or rifle is the distance between the extreme ends of the weapon measured along a line parallel to the center line of the bore.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Fixed ammunition.</E>
            That self-contained unit consisting of the case, primer, propellant charge, and projectile or projectiles.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Frame or receiver.</E>
            The term “frame or receiver” shall have the same meaning as in § 478.12 of this subchapter.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Importation.</E>
            The bringing of a firearm within the limits of the United States or any territory under its control or jurisdiction, from a place outside thereof (whether such place be a foreign country or territory subject to the jurisdiction of the United States), with intent to unlade. Except that, bringing a firearm from a foreign country or a territory subject to the jurisdiction of the United States into a foreign trade zone for storage pending shipment to a foreign country or subsequent importation into this country, under Title 26 of the United States Code, and this part, shall not be deemed importation.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Importer.</E>
            Any person who is engaged in the business of importing or bringing firearms into the United States.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Machine gun.</E>
            Any weapon which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger. The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machine gun, and any combination of parts from which a machine gun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Make.</E>
            This term and the various derivatives thereof shall include manufacturing (other than by one qualified to engage in such business under this part), putting together, altering, any combination of these, or otherwise producing a firearm.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Manual reloading.</E>
            The inserting of a cartridge or shell into the chamber of a firearm either with the hands or by means of a mechanical device controlled and energized by the hands.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Manufacturer.</E>
            Any person who is engaged in the business of manufacturing firearms.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Muffler or silencer.</E>
            Any device for silencing, muffling, or diminishing the report of a portable firearm, including any combination of parts, designed or redesigned, and intended for the use in assembling or fabricating a firearm silencer or firearm muffler, and any part intended only for use in such assembly or fabrication.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Person.</E>
            A partnership, company, association, trust, corporation, including each responsible person associated with such an entity; an estate; or an individual.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Pistol.</E>
            A weapon originally designed, made, and intended to fire a projectile (bullet) from one or more barrels when held in one hand, and having (a) a chamber(s) as an integral part(s) of, or permanently aligned with, the bore(s); and (b) a short stock designed to be gripped by one hand and at an angle to and extending below the line of the bore(s).
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Privately made firearm (PMF).</E>
        The term "privately made firearm (PMF)" shall have the same as meaning as in § 478.11 of this subchapter
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Readily.</E>
            A process, action, or physical state that is fairly or reasonably efficient, quick, and easy, but not necessarily the most efficient, speediest, or easiest process, action, or physical state. With respect to the classification of firearms, factors relevant in making this determination include the following:
    </P>
    <P>
        1. Time, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            how long it takes to finish the process;
    </P>
    <P>
        2. Ease, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            how difficult it is to do so;
    </P>
    <P>
        3. Expertise, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            what knowledge and skills are required;
    </P>
    <P>
        4. Equipment, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            what tools are required;
    </P>
    <P>
        5. Parts availability, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            whether additional parts are required, and how easily they can be obtained;
    </P>
    <P>
        6. Expense, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            how much it costs;
    </P>
    <P>
        7. Scope, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            the extent to which the subject of the process must be changed to finish it; and
    </P>
    <P>
        8. Feasibility, 
        <E T="03">i.e.,</E>
            whether the process would damage or destroy the subject of the process, or cause it to malfunction.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Responsible person.</E>
            In the case of an unlicensed entity, including any trust, partnership, association, company (including any Limited Liability Company (LLC)), or corporation, any individual who possesses, directly or indirectly, the power or authority to direct the management and policies of the trust or entity to receive, possess, ship, transport, deliver, transfer, or otherwise dispose of a firearm for, or on behalf of, the trust or legal entity. In the case of a trust, those persons with the power or authority to direct the management and policies of the trust include any person who has the capability to exercise such power and possesses, directly or indirectly, the power or authority under any trust instrument, or under State law, to receive, possess, ship, transport, deliver, transfer, or otherwise dispose of a firearm for, or on behalf of, the trust. Examples of who may be considered a responsible person include settlors/grantors, trustees, partners, members, officers, directors, board members, or owners. An example of who may be excluded from this definition of responsible person is the beneficiary of a trust, if the beneficiary does not have the capability to exercise the powers or authorities enumerated in this section.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Revolver.</E>
            A projectile weapon, of the pistol type, having a breechloading chambered cylinder so arranged that the cocking of the hammer or movement of the trigger rotates it and brings the next cartridge in line with the barrel for firing.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Rifle.</E>
    <P>
        (1) For purposes of this definition, the term “designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder” shall include a weapon that is equipped with an accessory, component, or other rearward attachment (e.g., a “stabilizing brace”) that provides surface area that allows the weapon to be fired from the shoulder, provided other factors, as described in paragraph (2), indicate that the weapon is designed, made, and intended to be fired from the shoulder.
    </P>
    <P>
        (2) When a weapon provides surface area that allows the weapon to be fired from the shoulder, the following factors shall also be considered in determining whether the weapon is designed, made, and intended to be fired from the shoulder:
    </P>
    <P>(i) Whether the weapon has a weight or length consistent with the weight or length of similarly designed rifles;</P>
    <P>(ii) Whether the weapon has a length of pull, measured from the center of the trigger to the center of the shoulder stock or other rearward accessory, component or attachment (including an adjustable or telescoping attachment with the ability to lock into various positions along a buffer tube, receiver extension, or other attachment method), that is consistent with similarly designed rifles;</P>
    <P>(iii) Whether the weapon is equipped with sights or a scope with eye relief that require the weapon to be fired from the shoulder in order to be used as designed;</P>
    <P>(iv) Whether the surface area that allows the weapon to be fired from the shoulder is created by a buffer tube, receiver extension, or any other accessory, component, or other rearward attachment that is necessary for the cycle of operations;</P>
    <P>(v) The manufacturer’s direct and indirect marketing and promotional materials indicating the intended use of the weapon; and</P>
    <P>(vi) Information demonstrating the likely use of the weapon in the general community.</P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Shotgun.</E>
            A weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of the explosive in a fixed shotgun shell to fire through a smooth bore either a number of projectiles (ball shot) or a single projectile for each pull of the trigger, and shall include any such weapon which may be readily restored to fire a fixed shotgun shell.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Transfer.</E>
            This term and the various derivatives thereof shall include selling, assigning, pledging, leasing, loaning, giving away, or otherwise disposing of. For purposes of this part, the term shall not include the temporary conveyance of a lawfully possessed firearm to a manufacturer or dealer qualified under this part for the sole purpose of repair, identification, evaluation, research, testing, or calibration and return to the same lawful possessor.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">United States.</E>
            The States and the District of Columbia.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">U.S.C.</E>
            The United States Code.
    </P>
    <P>
        <E T="03">Unserviceable firearm.</E>
            A firearm which is incapable of discharging a shot by means of an explosive and incapable of 
        <PRTPAGE P="86"/>
        being readily restored to a firing condition.
    </P>
    <SECAUTH>(26 U.S.C. 7805 (68A Stat. 917), 27 U.S.C. 205 (49 Stat. 981 as amended), 18 U.S.C. 926 (82 Stat. 959), and sec. 38, Arms Export Control Act (22 U.S.C. 2778, 90 Stat. 744))</SECAUTH>
    <CITA>[T.D. ATF-48, 43 FR 13538, Mar. 31, 1978; 44 FR 55842, Sept. 28, 1979; T.D. ATF-241, 51 FR 39630, Oct. 29, 1986; T.D. ATF-270, 53 FR 10492, Mar. 31, 1988; T.D. ATF-396, 63 FR 12647, Mar. 16, 1998; ATF 2013R-9F, 79 FR 46692, Aug. 11, 2014; ATF-41F, 81 FR 2721, Jan. 15, 2016; ATF 2018R-22F, 83 FR 66554, Dec. 26, 2018]</CITA>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<SIG>
<NAME>Robert Cekada,</NAME>
<TITLE>Director.</TITLE>
</SIG>
</SUPLINF>
<FRDOC>[FR Doc. 2026-08926 Filed 5-5-26; 8:45 am]</FRDOC>
<BILCOD>BILLING CODE 4410-FY-P</BILCOD>
</RULE>