
<RULE>
      <PREAMB>
        <AGENCY TYPE="N">DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE</AGENCY>
        <SUBAGY>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives</SUBAGY>
        <CFR>27 CFR Parts 478 and 479</CFR>
        <DEPDOC>[Docket No. ATF 2014R-42; AG Order No. 4419-2019]</DEPDOC>
        <SUBJECT>Removal of Expired Regulations Concerning Commerce in Firearms and Ammunition and Machine Guns, Destructive Devices, and Certain Other Firearms</SUBJECT>
        <AGY>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">AGENCY:</HD>
          <P>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, Department of Justice.</P>
        </AGY>
        <ACT>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">ACTION:</HD>
          <P>Final rule.</P>
        </ACT>
        <SUM>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">SUMMARY:</HD>
          <P>This final rule makes technical amendments to the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF) regulations in the Code of Federal Regulations (CFR). These technical changes are being made to remove expired, obsolete, or unnecessary regulations; correct specific headings; and to reflect changes to nomenclature resulting from the transfer of ATF to the Department of Justice from the Department of the Treasury pursuant to the Homeland Security Act of 2002. The changes are designed to update and provide clarity throughout these regulations.</P>
        </SUM>
        <EFFDATE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">DATES:</HD>
          <P>This rule is effective April 1, 2019.</P>
        </EFFDATE>
        <FURINF>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:</HD>
          <P>Shermaine Kenner, Office of Regulatory Affairs, Enforcement Programs and Services, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, U.S. Department of Justice, 99 New York Avenue NE, Washington, DC 20226; telephone: (202) 648-7070 (this is not a toll-free number).</P>
        </FURINF>
      </PREAMB>
      <SUPLINF>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION:</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">I. Background</HD>
        <P>ATF administers regulations published in 27 CFR part 478, concerning commerce in firearms and ammunition, and part 479, concerning machine guns, destructive devices, and certain other firearms. ATF identified several technical amendments that are needed to provide clarity and accuracy to these regulations.</P>
        <P>The technical changes made in this rule include the removal of expired regulations and regulations that are no longer applicable; the correction of section headings for accuracy; and a change in nomenclature resulting from the transfer of ATF to the Department of Justice from the Department of the Treasury pursuant to the Homeland Security Act of 2002.</P>
        <P>Several sections are being removed or amended because the statute that formed the basis of those regulations is no longer in effect. The Public Safety and Recreational Firearms Act (the Act), enacted as part of the Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994, Public Law 103-322, Title XI (1994), established a 10-year prohibition on the manufacture, transfer, or possession of “semiautomatic assault weapons,” as defined in the Act, as well as large capacity feeding devices. The Act expired on September 13, 2004, and ATF is removing or amending the following regulatory provisions that had, in whole or in part, implemented that Act and are therefore no longer effective:</P>
        <P>Sections 478.40, 478.40a, 478.119, 478.132, and 478.153 are being removed and reserved as they are no longer effective.</P>
        <P>Section 478.57 is being amended to remove paragraphs (b) and (c) as they are no longer effective.</P>
        <P>Section 478.92 is being amended to remove the section heading and replace it with a heading that does not contain “large capacity ammunition feeding devices”, and to remove paragraphs (a)(3) and (c), as they are no longer effective.</P>
        <P>Section 478.116 is being amended to remove all references to “ammunition feeding device” as those references are no longer effective.</P>
        <P>Section 478.171 is being amended to remove the last sentence referencing exportation of semiautomatic assault weapons as it is no longer effective.</P>
        <P>The final rule makes two additional technical changes. First, § 478.95 is being amended to reflect the correct section number as a result of the transfer of ATF to the Department of Justice from the Department of Treasury pursuant to the Homeland Security Act of 2002. Second, § 479.32 is being amended to remove paragraphs (a) and (c) referencing special occupational tax rates prior to January 1988, as the information is obsolete.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">II. Statutory Orders and Executive Review</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Executive Orders 12866, 13563, and 13771</HD>

        <P>This rule has been drafted and reviewed in accordance with Executive Orders 12866, “Regulatory Planning and Review,” section 1(b), The Principles of Regulation; Executive Order 13563, “Improving Regulation and Regulatory Review,” section 1(b), General Principles of Regulation; and Executive Order 13771, “Reducing Regulation and Controlling Regulatory Costs.”<PRTPAGE P="12094"/>
        </P>
        <P>This rule makes technical corrections to eliminate outdated and incorrect terminology and improve the clarity of the regulations, and makes no substantive changes. The Department has determined that this final rule is not a “significant regulatory action” as defined in Executive Order 12866, section 3(f). Accordingly, this final rule has not been reviewed by the Office of Management and Budget.</P>
        <P>Finally, because this rule is not a significant regulatory action, it is not subject to the requirements of Executive Order 13771. There are no costs associated with this regulation; however, it benefits the industry in that it removes outdated regulations and provides clarity for the regulated industry. Because there are no costs associated with this final rule, there are no monetized benefits. This rule is considered a deregulatory action under Executive Order 13771.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Executive Order 13132</HD>
        <P>This final rule will not have substantial direct effects on the States, on the relationship between the Federal Government and the States, or on the distribution of power and responsibilities among the various levels of government. Therefore, in accordance with section 6 of Executive Order 13132, “Federalism,” the Attorney General has determined that this regulation does not have sufficient federalism implications to warrant the preparation of a federalism summary impact statement.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Executive Order 12988</HD>
        <P>This regulation meets the applicable standards set forth in sections 3(a) and 3(b)(2) of Executive Order 12988, “Civil Justice Reform.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">D. Administrative Procedure Act</HD>
        <P>Under the Administrative Procedure Act (“APA”), 5 U.S.C. 553(b)(3)(B), an agency may, for good cause, find the usual requirements of prior notice and comment are impracticable, unnecessary, or contrary to the public interest. Currently, 27 CFR parts 478 and 479 contain references to expired regulations and have obsolete, outdated, and incorrect terminology that may be confusing to the public. The rule makes technical corrections to improve the clarity and accuracy of the regulations and makes no substantive changes. For these reasons, the agency has determined that publishing a notice of proposed rulemaking and providing opportunity for public comment is unnecessary.</P>

        <P>Further, the APA permits an agency to make this rule effective upon the date of publication because it is not a substantive rule. <E T="03">See</E> 5 U.S.C. 553(d). Furthermore, the Department finds that there is good cause for the final rule to take effect upon publication, since the revisions made by this rule are minor, non-substantive, and technical, and there is no reason to delay these changes. <E T="03">Id.</E>
        </P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">E. Regulatory Flexibility Act</HD>
        <P>In accordance with the Regulatory Flexibility Act, 5 U.S.C. 603, 604, and 605(b), a Regulatory Flexibility Analysis is not required for this final rule because the Department was not required to publish a general notice of proposed rulemaking for this matter.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">F. Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995</HD>
        <P>This rule will not result in the expenditure by State, local, and tribal governments, in the aggregate, or by the private sector, of $100 million or more in any one year, and it will not significantly or uniquely affect small governments. Therefore, no actions were deemed necessary under the provisions of the Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995, 2 U.S.C. 1531-1535.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">G. Paperwork Reduction Act of 1995</HD>
        <P>This final rule does not impose any new reporting or recordkeeping requirements under the Paperwork Reduction Act, 44 U.S.C. 3501-3521.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">H. Congressional Review Act</HD>
        <P>This rule is not a major rule as defined by the Congressional Review Act, 5 U.S.C. 804.</P>
        <LSTSUB>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">List of Subjects</HD>
          <CFR>27 CFR Part 478</CFR>
          <P>Administrative practice and procedure, Arms and munitions, Customs duties and inspection, Exports, Imports, Intergovernmental relations, Law enforcement officers, Military personnel, Penalties, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Research, Seizures and forfeitures, Transportation.</P>
          <CFR>27 CFR Part 479</CFR>
          <P>Administrative practice and procedure, Arms and munitions, Excise taxes, Exports, Imports, Military personnel, Penalties, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Seizures and forfeitures, Transportation.</P>
        </LSTSUB>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Authority and Issuance</HD>
        <P>Accordingly, for the reasons discussed in the preamble, 27 CFR parts 478 and 479 are amended as follows:</P>
        <PART>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 478—COMMERCE IN FIREARMS AND AMMUNITION</HD>
        </PART>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>1. The authority citation for 27 CFR part 478 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
          <AUTH>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority: </HD>
            <P>5 U.S.C. 552(a); 18 U.S.C. 921-931; 44 U.S.C. 3504(h).</P>
          </AUTH>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.40 </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT>[Removed and Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>2. Remove and reserve § 478.40.</AMDPAR>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.40a </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT>[Removed]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>3. Remove § 478.40a.</AMDPAR>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.57 </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>4. Amend § 478.57 by removing paragraphs (b) and (c) and redesignating paragraph (a) as an undesignated paragraph.</AMDPAR>
        </REGTEXT>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>5. Amend § 478.92 by revising the section heading, removing and reserving paragraph (a)(3), and removing paragraph (c) to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
          <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 478.92</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT> Identification of firearms and armor piercing ammunition by licensed manufacturers and licensed importers.</SUBJECT>
            <STARS/>
          </SECTION>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.95 </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>6. Amend § 478.95 by removing “178.94” and adding in its place “478.94” and removing “(a)” and “(b)”.</AMDPAR>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.116 </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>7. Section § 478.116 is revised to read</AMDPAR>
            <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 478.116</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Conditional importation.</SUBJECT>
            <P>The Director shall permit the conditional importation or bringing into the United States or any possession thereof of any firearm, firearm barrel, or ammunition for the purpose of examining and testing the firearm, firearm barrel, or ammunition in connection with making a determination as to whether the importation or bringing in of such firearm, firearm barrel, or ammunition will be authorized under this part. An application on ATF Form 6 for such conditional importation shall be filed, in duplicate, with the Director. The Director may impose conditions upon any importation under this section including a requirement that the firearm, firearm barrel, or ammunition be shipped directly from Customs custody to the Director and that the person importing or bringing in the firearm, firearm barrel, or ammunition must agree to either export the firearm, firearm barrel, or ammunition or destroy same if a determination is made that the firearm, firearm barrel, or ammunition may not be imported or brought in under this part. A firearm, firearm barrel, or ammunition imported or brought into the United States or any possession thereof under the provisions of this section shall be released from Customs custody upon the payment of customs duties, if applicable, and in the manner prescribed in the conditional authorization issued by the Director.</P>
            <CITA>[T.D. ATF-383, 61 FR 39321, July 29, 1996, as amended by ATF 2014R-42, 84 FR 12094, Apr. 1, 2019]</CITA>
          </SECTION>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.119, 478.132, and 478.153 </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT>[Removed and Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>8. Remove and reserve §§ 478.119, 478.132, and 478.153.</AMDPAR>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.171</SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT> [Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>9. Amend § 478.171 by removing “semiautomatic assault weapons” in the last sentence of the paragraph.</AMDPAR>
        </REGTEXT>
        <PART>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 479—MACHINE GUNS, DESTRUCTIVE DEVICES, AND CERTAIN OTHER FIREARMS</HD>
        </PART>
        <REGTEXT PART="479" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>10. The authority citation for 27 CFR part 479 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
          <AUTH>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority: </HD>
            <P>26 U.S.C. 5812; 26 U.S.C. 5822; 26 U.S.C. 7801; 26 U.S.C 7805.</P>
          </AUTH>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 479.32 </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="479" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>11. Amend § 479.32 by removing paragraphs (a) and (c) and redesignating paragraph (b) as an undesignated paragraph.</AMDPAR>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 479.32a </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="479" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>12. Section § 479.32a is revised to read</AMDPAR>
          <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 479.32a</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Reduced rate of tax for small importers and manufacturers.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) <E T="03">General.</E> Effective January 1, 1988, 26 U.S.C. 5801(b) provides for a reduced rate of special tax with respect to any importer or manufacturer whose gross receipts (for the most recent taxable year ending before the first day of the taxable period to which the special tax imposed by § 479.32 relates) are less than $500,000. The rate of tax for such an importer or manufacturer is $500 per year or fraction thereof. The “taxable year” to be used for determining gross receipts is the taxpayer's income tax year. All gross receipts of the taxpayer shall be included, not just the gross receipts of the business subject to special tax. Proprietors of new businesses that have not yet begun a taxable year, as well as proprietors of existing businesses that have not yet ended a taxable year, who commence a new activity subject to special tax, quality for the reduced special (occupational) tax rate, unless the business is a member of a “controlled group”; in that case, the rules of paragraph (b) of this section shall apply.</P>
            <P>(b) <E T="03">Controlled group.</E> All persons treated as one taxpayer under 26 U.S.C. 5061(e)(3) shall be treated as one taxpayer for the purpose of determining gross receipts under paragraph (a) of this section. “Controlled group” means a controlled group of corporations, as defined in 26 U.S.C. 1563 and implementing regulations in 26 CFR 1563-1 through 1563-4, except that the words <PRTPAGE P="89"/>“at least 80 percent” shall be replaced by the words “more than 50 percent” in each place they appear in subsection (a) of 26 U.S.C. 1563, as well as in the implementing regulations. Also, the rules for a “controlled group of corporations” apply in a similar fashion to groups which include partnerships and/or sole proprietorships. If one entity maintains more than 50% control over a group consisting of corporations and one, or more, partnerships and/or sole proprietorships, all of the members of the controlled group are one taxpayer for the purpose of this section.</P>
            <P>(c) <E T="03">Short taxable year.</E> Gross receipts for any taxable year of less than 12 months shall be annualized by multiplying the gross receipts for the short period by 12 and dividing the result by the number of months in the short period, as required by 26 U.S.C. 448(c)(3).</P>
            <P>(d) <E T="03">Returns and allowances.</E> Gross receipts for any taxable year shall be reduced by returns and allowances made during that year under 26 U.S.C. 448(c)(3).</P>
            <SECAUTH>(26 U.S.C. 448, 5061, 5801)</SECAUTH>
            <CITA>[T.D. ATF-271, 53 FR 17550, May 17, 1988]</CITA>
          </SECTION>
       </REGTEXT>
        <SIG>
          <PRTPAGE P="12095"/>
          <DATED>Dated: March 25, 2019.</DATED>
          <NAME>William P. Barr,</NAME>
          <TITLE>Attorney General.</TITLE>
        </SIG>
      </SUPLINF>
      <FRDOC>[FR Doc. 2019-06264 Filed 3-29-19; 8:45 am]</FRDOC>
      <BILCOD> BILLING CODE 4410-FY-P</BILCOD>
    </RULE>