
<RULE>
      <PREAMB>
        <AGENCY TYPE="S">DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE</AGENCY>
        <SUBAGY>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives</SUBAGY>
        <CFR>27 CFR Part 478</CFR>
        <DEPDOC>[Docket No. ATF 2019R-03; AG Order No. 4576-2019] </DEPDOC>
        <SUBJECT>Removal of Expired Regulations Concerning Commerce in Firearms and Ammunition; Correction</SUBJECT>
        <AGY>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">AGENCY:</HD>
          <P>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, Department of Justice.</P>
        </AGY>
        <ACT>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">ACTION:</HD>
          <P>Final rule.</P>
        </ACT>
        <SUM>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">SUMMARY:</HD>

          <P>On April 1, 2019, the Department of Justice published in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E> a final rule making technical changes to remove expired, obsolete, or unnecessary regulations; correct specific headings; and reflect changes to nomenclature in the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives regulations related to the commerce in firearms and ammunition. That document inadvertently included an incomplete revision to remove all words related to an expired regulation. This final rule corrects the April 2019 amendment by revising the section to complete the removal of the expired regulation.</P>
        </SUM>
        <EFFDATE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">DATES:</HD>
          <P>This rule is effective November 8, 2019.</P>
        </EFFDATE>
        <FURINF>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:</HD>
          <P>Shermaine Kenner, Office of Regulatory Affairs, Enforcement Programs and Services, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, U.S. Department of Justice, 99 New York Avenue NE, Washington, DC 20226; telephone: (202) 648-7070 (this is not a toll-free number).</P>
        </FURINF>
      </PREAMB>
      <SUPLINF>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION:</HD>
        <P/>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">I. Background</HD>

        <P>The Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF) administers regulations published in title 27, Code of Federal Regulations (CFR), part 478, concerning commerce in firearms and ammunition. On April 1, 2019, the Department of Justice (DOJ) published in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E> a final rule that made technical amendments in ATF regulations in the CFR (84 FR 12093). The technical changes made in this rule included the removal of expired regulations and regulations that are no longer applicable; the correction of section headings for accuracy; and a change in nomenclature resulting from the transfer of ATF to the Department of Justice from the Department of the Treasury pursuant to the Homeland Security Act of 2002.</P>
        <P>Several sections were removed or amended because the statute that formed the basis of those regulations is no longer in effect. The Public Safety and Recreational Firearms Act (the Act), enacted as part of the Violent Crime Control and Law Enforcement Act of 1994, Pub. L. 103-322, Title XI (1994), established a 10-year prohibition on the manufacture, transfer, or possession of “semiautomatic assault weapons,” as defined in the Act, as well as large capacity feeding devices. The Act expired on September 13, 2004, and the final rule was issued to remove or amend the regulatory provisions that had, in whole or in part, implemented that Act as they are no longer effective.</P>
        <P>The April 2019 technical amendments inadvertently failed to remove all words related to the expired regulation that were included in 27 CFR 478.171. This final rule corrects the changes in the CFR made by the 2019 technical amendments by amending § 478.171 to remove “and manufactured after September 13, 1994, ” and “or were” in the last sentence of the paragraph and to add “was” before “exported” in the last sentence of the paragraph.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">II. Statutory Orders and Executive Review</HD>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Executive Orders 12866, 13563, and 13771</HD>
        <P>This rule has been drafted and reviewed in accordance with Executive Orders 12866, ” Regulatory Planning and Review,” section 1(b), The Principle of Regulation; Executive Order 13563, “Improving Regulation and Regulatory Review,”section 1(b), General Principles of Regulation; and Executive Order 13771, ” Reducing Regulation and Controlling Regulatory Costs.”</P>
        <P>This rule makes technical corrections to eliminate outdated and incorrect terminology and improve the clarity of the regulations, and makes no substantive changes. The Department has determined that this final rule is not a “significant regulatory action” as defined in Executive Order 12866, section 3(f). Accordingly, this final rule has not been reviewed by the Office of Management and Budget.</P>
        <P>Finally, because this rule is not a significant regulatory action, it is not subject to the requirements of Executive Order 13771. There are no costs associated with this regulation; however, it benefits the industry in that it removes outdated regulations and provides clarity for the regulated industry. Because there are no costs associated with this final rule, there are no monetized benefits. This rule is considered a deregulatory action under Executive Order 13771.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Executive Order 13132</HD>
        <P>This final rule will not have substantial direct effects on the States, on the relationship between the Federal Government and the States, or on the distribution of power and responsibilities among the various levels of government. Therefore, in accordance with section 6 of Executive Order 13132, “Federalism,” the Attorney General has determined that this regulation does not have sufficient federalism implications to warrant the preparation of a federalism summary impact statement.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Executive Order 12988</HD>
        <P>This regulation meets the applicable standards set forth in sections 3(a) and 3(b)(2) of Executive Order 12988, “Civil Justice Reform.”</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">D. Administrative Procedure Act</HD>

        <P>Under the Administrative Procedure Act (“APA”), 5 U.S.C. 553(b)(3)(B), an agency may, for good cause, find the usual requirements of prior notice and comment are impracticable, unnecessary, or contrary to the public interest. Currently, 27 CFR part 478 contains references to expired regulations and has obsolete, outdated, and incorrect terminology that may be confusing to the public. The rule makes technical corrections to improve the clarity and accuracy of the regulations and makes no substantive changes. For <PRTPAGE P="60334"/>these reasons, the agency has determined that publishing a noticed of proposed rulemaking and providing opportunity for public comment is unnecessary.</P>

        <P>Further, the APA permits an agency to make this rule effective upon the date of publication because it is not a substantive rule. <E T="03">See</E> 5 U.S.C. 553(d). Furthermore, the Department finds that there is good cause for the final rule to take effect upon publication, since the revisions made by this rule are minor, non-substantive, and technical, and there is no reason to delay these changes. <E T="03">Id.</E>
        </P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">E. Regulatory Flexibility Act</HD>
        <P>In accordance with the Regulatory Flexibility Act, 5 U.S.C. 603, 604, and 605(b), a Regulatory Flexibility Analysis is not required for this final rule because the Department was not required to publish a general notice of proposed rulemaking for this matter.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">F. Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995</HD>
        <P>This rule will not result in the expenditure by State, local, and tribal governments, in the aggregate, or by the private sector, of $100 million or more in any one year, and it will not significantly or uniquely affect small governments. Therefore, no actions were deemed necessary under the provisions of the Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995, 2 U.S.C. 1531-1525.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">G. Paperwork Reduction Act of 1995</HD>
        <P>This final rule does not impose any new reporting or recordkeeping requirements under the Paperwork Reduction Act 44 U.S.C. 3501-3521.</P>
        <HD SOURCE="HD2">H. Congressional Review Act</HD>
        <P>Pursuant to the Congressonal Review Act, 5 U.S.C. 801 <E T="03">et seq.,</E> the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs designated this rule as not a major rule, as defined by 5 U.S.C. 804(2).</P>
        <LSTSUB>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">List of Subjects in 27 CFR Part 478</HD>
          <P>Administrative practice and procedure, Arms and munitions, Customs duties and inspection, Exports, Imports, Intergovernmental relations, Law enforcement officers, Military personnel, Penalties, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Research, Seizures and forfeitures, Transportation.</P>
        </LSTSUB>
        <HD SOURCE="HD1">Authority and Issuance</HD>
        <P>Accordingly, for the reasons discussed in the preamble, 27 CFR part 478 is amended as follows:</P>
        <PART>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 478—COMMERCE IN FIREARMS AND AMMUNITION</HD>
        </PART>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>1. The authority citation for 27 CFR part 478 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
          <AUTH>
            <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>
            <P> 5 U.S.C. 552(a); 18 U.S.C. 921-931; 44 U.S.C. 3504(h).</P>
          </AUTH>
        </REGTEXT>
         <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.171 </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT> [Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
          <AMDPAR>2. Section 478.171 is revised to read</AMDPAR>
          <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 478.171</SECTNO>
              <SUBJECT>Exportation.</SUBJECT>
              <P>Firearms and ammunition shall be exported in accordance with the applicable provisions of section 38 of the Arms Export Control Act (22 U.S.C. 2778) and regulations thereunder. However, licensed manufacturers, licensed importers, and licensed dealers exporting firearms shall maintain records showing the manufacture or acquisition of the firearms as required by this part and records showing the name and address of the foreign consignee of the firearms and the date the firearms were exported. Licensed manufacturers and licensed importers exporting armor piercing ammunition, shall maintain records showing the name and address of the foreign consignee and the date the armor piercing ammunition was exported.</P>
              <CITA>[T.D. ATF-270, 53 FR 10507, Mar. 31, 1988; T.D. ATF-363, 60 FR 17456, Apr. 6, 1995; ATF 2014R-42, 84 FR 12094, Apr. 1, 2019]</CITA>
          </SECTION>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
          <SECTNO>§ 478.11 </SECTNO>
          <SUBJECT> [Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
            <AMDPAR>3. Section 478.11 is revised to read</AMDPAR>
            <SECTION>
                <SECTNO>§ 478.11</SECTNO>
                <SUBJECT>Meaning of terms.</SUBJECT>
                <P>When used in this part and in forms prescribed under this part, where not otherwise distinctly expressed or manifestly incompatible with the intent thereof, terms shall have the meanings ascribed in this section. Words in the plural form shall include the singular, and vice versa, and words importing the masculine gender shall include the feminine. The terms “includes” and “including” do not exclude other things not enumerated which are in the same general class or are otherwise within the scope thereof.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Act.</E> 18 U.S.C. Chapter 44.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Adjudicated as a mental defective.</E> (a) A determination by a court, board, commission, or other lawful authority that a person, as a result of marked subnormal intelligence, or mental illness, incompetency, condition, or disease:</P>
                <P>(1) Is a danger to himself or to others; or</P>
                <P>(2) Lacks the mental capacity to contract or manage his own affairs.</P>
                <P>(b) The term shall include—</P>
                <P>(1) A finding of insanity by a court in a criminal case; and</P>

                <P>(2) Those persons found incompetent to stand trial or found not guilty by reason of lack of mental responsibility pursuant to articles 50a and 72b of the <PRTPAGE P="21"/>Uniform Code of Military Justice, 10 U.S.C. 850a, 876b.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Admitted to the United States for lawful hunting or sporting purposes.</E> (a) Is entering the United States to participate in a competitive target shooting event sponsored by a national, State, or local organization, devoted to the competitive use or other sporting use of firearms; or</P>
                <P>(b) Is entering the United States to display firearms at a sports or hunting trade show sponsored by a national, State, or local firearms trade organization, devoted to the competitive use or other sporting use of firearms.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Alien.</E> Any person not a citizen or national of the United States.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Alien illegally or unlawfully in the United States.</E> Aliens who are unlawfully in the United States are not in valid immigrant, nonimmigrant or parole status. The term includes any alien—</P>
                <P>(a) Who unlawfully entered the United States without inspection and authorization by an immigration officer and who has not been paroled into the United States under section 212(d)(5) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (INA);</P>
                <P>(b) Who is a nonimmigrant and whose authorized period of stay has expired or who has violated the terms of the nonimmigrant category in which he or she was admitted;</P>
                <P>(c) Paroled under INA section 212(d)(5) whose authorized period of parole has expired or whose parole status has been terminated; or</P>
                <P>(d) Under an order of deportation, exclusion, or removal, or under an order to depart the United States voluntarily, whether or not he or she has left the United States.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Ammunition.</E> Ammunition or cartridge cases, primers, bullets, or propellent powder designed for use in any firearm other than an antique firearm. The term shall not include (a) any shotgun shot or pellet not designed for use as the single, complete projectile load for one shotgun hull or casing, nor (b) any unloaded, non-metallic shotgun hull or casing not having a primer.</P>
                <P>
                    <E T="03">Antique firearm.</E>
                    (1) Any firearm (including any firearm with a matchlock, flintlock, percussion cap, or similar type of ignition system) manufactured in or before 1898;
                    </P>
                    <P>(2) Any replica of any firearm described in paragraph (a) of this definition if such replica:</P>
                    <P>(i) Is not designed or redesigned for using rimfire or conventional centerfire fixed ammunition; or</P>
                    <P>(ii) Uses rimfire or conventional centerfire fixed ammunition that is no longer manufactured in the United States and that is not readily available in the ordinary channels of commercial trade; or</P>
                    <P>(3) Any muzzle loading rifle, muzzle loading shotgun, or muzzle loading pistol that is designed to use black powder, or a black powder substitute, and that cannot use fixed ammunition. For purposes of this paragraph (3), the term “antique firearm” does not include any weapon that incorporates a firearm frame or receiver, any firearm that is converted into a muzzle loading weapon, or any muzzle loading weapon that can be readily converted to fire fixed ammunition by replacing the barrel, bolt, breechblock, or any combination thereof.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Armor piercing ammunition.</E> Projectiles or projectile cores which may be used in a handgun and which are constructed entirely (excluding the presence of traces of other substances) from one or a combination of tungsten alloys, steel, iron, brass, bronze, beryllium copper, or depleted uranium; or full jacketed projectiles larger than .22 caliber designed and intended for use in a handgun and whose jacket has a weight of more than 25 percent of the total weight of the projectile. The term does not include shotgun shot required by Federal or State environmental or game regulations for hunting purposes, frangible projectiles designed for target shooting, projectiles which the Director finds are primarily intended to be used for sporting purposes, or any other projectiles or projectile cores which the Director finds are intended to be used for industrial purposes, including charges used in oil and gas well perforating devices.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">ATF officer.</E> An officer or employee of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF) authorized to perform any function relating to the administration or enforcement of this part.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Business premises.</E> The property on which the manufacturing or importing of firearms or ammunition or the dealing in firearms is or will be conducted. A private dwelling, no part of which is open to the public, shall not be recognized as coming within the meaning of the term.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Chief, Federal Firearms Licensing Center (FFLC).</E> The ATF official responsible for the issuance and renewal of licenses under this part.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Collector.</E> Any person who acquires, holds, or disposes of firearms as curios or relics.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Collection premises.</E> The premises described on the license of a collector as <PRTPAGE P="22"/>the location at which he maintains his collection of curios and relics.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Commerce.</E> Travel, trade, traffic, commerce, transportation, or communication among the several States, or between the District of Columbia and any State, or between any foreign country or any territory or possession and any State or the District of Columbia, or between points in the same State but through any other State or the District of Columbia or a foreign country.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Committed to a mental institution.</E> A formal commitment of a person to a mental institution by a court, board, commission, or other lawful authority. The term includes a commitment to a mental institution involuntarily. The term includes commitment for mental defectiveness or mental illness. It also includes commitments for other reasons, such as for drug use. The term does not include a person in a mental institution for observation or a voluntary admission to a mental institution.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Controlled substance.</E> A drug or other substance, or immediate precursor, as defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act, 21 U.S.C. 802. The term includes, but is not limited to, marijuana, depressants, stimulants, and narcotic drugs. The term does not include distilled spirits, wine, malt beverages, or tobacco, as those terms are defined or used in Subtitle E of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Crime punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year.</E> Any Federal, State or foreign offense for which the maximum penalty, whether or not imposed, is capital punishment or imprisonment in excess of 1 year. The term shall not include (a) any Federal or State offenses pertaining to antitrust violations, unfair trade practices, restraints of trade, or other similar offenses relating to the regulation of business practices or (b) any State offense classified by the laws of the State as a misdemeanor and punishable by a term of imprisonment of 2 years or less. What constitutes a conviction of such a crime shall be determined in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held. Any conviction which has been expunged or set aside or for which a person has been pardoned or has had civil rights restored shall not be considered a conviction for the purposes of the Act or this part, unless such pardon, expunction, or restoration of civil rights expressly provides that the person may not ship, transport, possess, or receive firearms, or unless the person is prohibited by the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held from receiving or possessing any firearms.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Curios or relics.</E> Firearms which are of special interest to collectors by reason of some quality other than is associated with firearms intended for sporting use or as offensive or defensive weapons. To be recognized as curios or relics, firearms must fall within one of the following categories:</P>
                <P>(a) Firearms which were manufactured at least 50 years prior to the current date, but not including replicas thereof;</P>
                <P>(b) Firearms which are certified by the curator of a municipal, State, or Federal museum which exhibits firearms to be curios or relics of museum interest; and</P>
                <P>(c) Any other firearms which derive a substantial part of their monetary value from the fact that they are novel, rare, bizarre, or because of their association with some historical figure, period, or event. Proof of qualification of a particular firearm under this category may be established by evidence of present value and evidence that like firearms are not available except as collector's items, or that the value of like firearms available in ordinary commercial channels is substantially less.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Customs officer.</E> Any officer of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, any commissioned, warrant, or petty officer of the Coast Guard, or any agent or other person authorized by law to perform the duties of a customs officer.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Dealer.</E> Any person engaged in the business of selling firearms at wholesale or retail; any person engaged in the business of repairing firearms or of making or fitting special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms; or any person who is a pawnbroker. The term shall include any person who engages in such business or occupation on a part-time basis.<PRTPAGE P="23"/>
                </P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Destructive device.</E> (a) Any explosive, incendiary, or poison gas (1) bomb, (2) grenade, (3) rocket having a propellant charge of more than 4 ounces, (4) missile having an explosive or incendiary charge of more than one-quarter ounce, (5) mine, or (6) device similar to any of the devices described in the preceding paragraphs of this definition; (b) any type of weapon (other than a shotgun or a shotgun shell which the Director finds is generally recognized as particularly suitable for sporting purposes) by whatever name known which will, or which may be readily converted to, expel a projectile by the action of an explosive or other propellant, and which has any barrel with a bore of more than one-half inch in diameter; and (c) any combination of parts either designed or intended for use in converting any device into any destructive device described in paragraph (a) or (b) of this section and from which a destructive device may be readily assembled. The term shall not include any device which is neither designed nor redesigned for use as a weapon; any device, although originally designed for use as a weapon, which is redesigned for use as a signalling, pyrotechnic, line throwing, safety, or similar device; surplus ordnance sold, loaned, or given by the Secretary of the Army pursuant to the provisions of section 4684(2), 4685, or 4686 of title 10, United States Code; or any other device which the Director finds is not likely to be used as a weapon, is an antique, or is a rifle which the owner intends to use solely for sporting, recreational, or cultural purposes.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Director.</E> The Director, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, the Department of Justice, Washington, DC.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Director of Industry Operations.</E> The principal ATF official in a Field Operations division responsible for administering regulations in this part.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Discharged under dishonorable conditions.</E> Separation from the U.S. Armed Forces resulting from a dishonorable discharge or dismissal adjudged by a general court-martial. The term does not include any separation from the Armed Forces resulting from any other discharge, e.g., a bad conduct discharge.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Division.</E> A Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives Division.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Engaged in the business</E>—(a) <E T="03">Manufacturer of firearms.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to manufacturing firearms as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the firearms manufactured;</P>
                <P>(b) <E T="03">Manufacturer of ammunition.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to manufacturing ammunition as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the ammunition manufactured;</P>
                <P>(c) <E T="03">Dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or a pawnbroker.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to dealing in firearms as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the repetitive purchase and resale of firearms, but such a term shall not include a person who makes occasional sales, exchanges, or purchases of firearms for the enhancement of a personal collection or for a hobby, or who sells all or part of his personal collection of firearms;</P>
                <P>(d) <E T="03">Gunsmith.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to engaging in such activity as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit, but such a term shall not include a person who makes occasional repairs of firearms or who occasionally fits special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms;</P>
                <P>(e) <E T="03">Importer of firearms.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to importing firearms as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the firearms imported; and,</P>
                <P>(f) <E T="03">Importer of ammunition.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to importing ammunition as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the ammunition imported.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Executed under penalties of perjury.</E> Signed with the prescribed declaration <PRTPAGE P="24"/>under the penalties of perjury as provided on or with respect to the return form, or other document or, where no form of declaration is prescribed, with the declaration:
                </P>
                <EXTRACT>
                  <P>“I declare under the penalties of perjury that this—(insert type of document, such as, statement, application, request, certificate), including the documents submitted in support thereof, has been examined by me and, to the best of my knowledge and belief, is true, correct, and complete.”</P>
                </EXTRACT>
                
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Federal Firearms Act.</E> 15 U.S.C. Chapter 18.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Firearm.</E> Any weapon, including a starter gun, which will or is designed to or may readily be converted to expel a projectile by the action of an explosive; the frame or receiver of any such weapon; any firearm muffler or firearm silencer; or any destructive device; but the term shall not include an antique firearm. In the case of a licensed collector, the term shall mean only curios and relics.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Firearm frame or receiver.</E> That part of a firearm which provides housing for the hammer, bolt or breechblock, and firing mechanism, and which is usually threaded at its forward portion to receive the barrel.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Firearm muffler or firearm silencer.</E> Any device for silencing, muffling, or diminishing the report of a portable firearm, including any combination of parts, designed or redesigned, and intended for use in assembling or fabricating a firearm silencer or firearm muffler, and any part intended only for use in such assembly or fabrication.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Friendly foreign government.</E> Any government with whom the United States has diplomatic relations and whom the United States has not identified as a State sponsor of terrorism.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Fugitive from justice.</E> Any person who has fled from any State to avoid prosecution for a felony or a misdemeanor; or any person who leaves the State to avoid giving testimony in any criminal proceeding. The term also includes any person who knows that misdemeanor or felony charges are pending against such person and who leaves the State of prosecution.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Handgun.</E> (a) Any firearm which has a short stock and is designed to be held and fired by the use of a single hand; and</P>
                <P>(b) Any combination of parts from which a firearm described in paragraph (a) can be assembled.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Hunting license or permit lawfully issued in the United States.</E> A license or permit issued by a State for hunting which is valid and unexpired.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Identification document.</E> A document containing the name, residence address, date of birth, and photograph of the holder and which was made or issued by or under the authority of the United States Government, a State, political subdivision of a State, a foreign government, political subdivision of a foreign government, an international governmental or an international quasi- governmental organization which, when completed with information concerning a particular individual, is of a type intended or commonly accepted for the purpose of identification of individuals.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Importation.</E> The bringing of a firearm or ammunition into the United States; except that the bringing of a firearm or ammunition from outside the United States into a foreign-trade zone for storage pending shipment to a foreign country or subsequent importation into this country, pursuant to this part, shall not be deemed importation.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Importer.</E> Any person engaged in the business of importing or bringing firearms or ammunition into the United States. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Indictment.</E> Includes an indictment or information in any court, under which a crime punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year (as defined in this section) may be prosecuted, or in military cases to any offense punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year which has been referred to a general court-martial. An information is a formal accusation of a crime, differing from an indictment in that it is made by a prosecuting attorney and not a grand jury.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Interstate or foreign commerce.</E> Includes commerce between any place in a State and any place outside of that State, or within any possession of the United States (not including the Canal Zone) or the District of Columbia. The term shall not include commerce between places within the same State but <PRTPAGE P="25"/>through any place outside of that State.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Intimate partner.</E> With respect to a person, the spouse of the person, a former spouse of the person, an individual who is a parent of a child of the person, and an individual who cohabitates or has cohabitated with the person.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Large capacity ammunition feeding device.</E> A magazine, belt, drum, feed strip, or similar device for a firearm manufactured after September 13, 1994, that has a capacity of, or that can be readily restored or converted to accept, more than 10 rounds of ammunition. The term does not include an attached tubular device designed to accept, and capable of operating only with, .22 caliber rimfire ammunition, or a fixed device for a manually operated firearm, or a fixed device for a firearm listed in 18 U.S.C. 922, appendix A.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Licensed collector.</E> A collector of curios and relics only and licensed under the provisions of this part.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Licensed dealer.</E> A dealer licensed under the provisions of this part.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Licensed importer.</E> An importer licensed under the provisions of this part.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Licensed manufacturer.</E> A manufacturer licensed under the provisions of this part.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Machine gun.</E> Any weapon which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger. The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machine gun, and any combination of parts from which a machine gun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Manufacturer.</E> Any person engaged in the business of manufacturing firearms or ammunition. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Mental institution.</E> Includes mental health facilities, mental hospitals, sanitariums, psychiatric facilities, and other facilities that provide diagnoses by licensed professionals of mental retardation or mental illness, including a psychiatric ward in a general hospital.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Misdemeanor crime of domestic violence.</E> (a) Is a Federal, State or local offense that:</P>
                <P>(1) Is a misdemeanor under Federal or State law or, in States which do not classify offenses as misdemeanors, is an offense punishable by imprisonment for a term of one year or less, and includes offenses that are punishable only by a fine. (This is true whether or not the State statute specifically defines the offense as a “misdemeanor” or as a “misdemeanor crime of domestic violence.” The term includes all such misdemeanor convictions in Indian Courts established pursuant to 25 CFR part 11.);</P>
                <P>(2) Has, as an element, the use or attempted use of physical force (e.g., assault and battery), or the threatened use of a deadly weapon; and</P>
                <P>(3) Was committed by a current or former spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim, by a person with whom the victim shares a child in common, by a person who is cohabiting with or has cohabited with the victim as a spouse, parent, or guardian, (e.g., the equivalent of a “common law” marriage even if such relationship is not recognized under the law), or a person similarly situated to a spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim (e.g., two persons who are residing at the same location in an intimate relationship with the intent to make that place their home would be similarly situated to a spouse).</P>
                <P>(b) A person shall not be considered to have been convicted of such an offense for purposes of this part unless:</P>
                <P>(1) The person is considered to have been convicted by the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held.</P>
                <P>(2) The person was represented by counsel in the case, or knowingly and intelligently waived the right to counsel in the case; and</P>
                <P>(3) In the case of a prosecution for which a person was entitled to a jury trial in the jurisdiction in which the case was tried, either</P>
                <P>(i) The case was tried by a jury, or</P>

                <P>(ii) The person knowingly and intelligently waived the right to have the case tried by a jury, by guilty plea or otherwise.<PRTPAGE P="26"/>
                </P>
                <P>(c) A person shall not be considered to have been convicted of such an offense for purposes of this part if the conviction has been expunged or set aside, or is an offense for which the person has been pardoned or has had civil rights restored (if the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held provides for the loss of civil rights upon conviction for such an offense) unless the pardon, expunction, or restoration of civil rights expressly provides that the person may not ship, transport, possess, or receive firearms, and the person is not otherwise prohibited by the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held from receiving or possessing any firearms.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">National Firearms Act.</E> 26 U.S.C. Chapter 53.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">NICS.</E> The National Instant Criminal Background Check System established by the Attorney General pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 922(t).</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Nonimmigrant alien.</E> An alien in the United States in a nonimmigrant classification as defined by section 101(a)(15) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(15)).</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Nonimmigrant visa.</E> A visa properly issued to an alien as an eligible nonimmigrant by a competent officer as provided in the Immigration and Nationality Act, 8 U.S.C. 1101 <E T="03">et seq.</E>
                </P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Pawnbroker.</E> Any person whose business or occupation includes the taking or receiving, by way of pledge or pawn, of any firearm as security for the payment or repayment of money. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Permanently inoperable.</E> A firearm which is incapable of discharging a shot by means of an explosive and incapable of being readily restored to a firing condition. An acceptable method of rendering most firearms permanently inoperable is to fusion weld the chamber closed and fusion weld the barrel solidly to the frame. Certain unusual firearms require other methods to render the firearm permanently inoperable. Contact ATF for instructions.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Person.</E> Any individual, corporation, company, association, firm, partnership, society, or joint stock company.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Pistol.</E> A weapon originally designed, made, and intended to fire a projectile (bullet) from one or more barrels when held in one hand, and having (a) a chamber(s) as an integral part(s) of, or permanently aligned with, the bore(s); and (b) a short stock designed to be gripped by one hand and at an angle to and extending below the line of the bore(s).</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Principal objective of livelihood and profit.</E> The intent underlying the sale or disposition of firearms is predominantly one of obtaining livelihood and pecuniary gain, as opposed to other intents such as improving or liquidating a personal firearms collection: <E T="03">Provided,</E> That proof of profit shall not be required as to a person who engages in the regular and repetitive purchase and disposition of firearms for criminal purposes or terrorism. For purposes of this part, the term “terrorism” means activity, directed against United States persons, which—</P>
                <P>(a) Is committed by an individual who is not a national or permanent resident alien of the United States;</P>
                <P>(b) Involves violent acts or acts dangerous to human life which would be a criminal violation if committed within the jurisdiction of the United States; and</P>
                <P>(c) Is intended—</P>
                <P>(1) To intimidate or coerce a civilian population;</P>
                <P>(2) To influence the policy of a government by intimidation or coercion; or</P>
                <P>(3) To affect the conduct of a government by assassination or kidnapping.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Published ordinance.</E> A published law of any political subdivision of a State which the Director determines to be relevant to the enforcement of this part and which is contained on a list compiled by the Director, which list is incorporated by reference in the <E T="04">Federal Register,</E> revised annually, and furnished to licensees under this part.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Renounced U.S. citizenship.</E> (a) A person has renounced his U.S. citizenship if the person, having been a citizen of the United States, has renounced citizenship either—</P>
                <P>(1) Before a diplomatic or consular officer of the United States in a foreign state pursuant to 8 U.S.C. 1481(a)(5); or</P>

                <P>(2) Before an officer designated by the Attorney General when the United <PRTPAGE P="27"/>States is in a state of war pursuant to 8 U.S.C. 1481(a)(6).</P>
                <P>(b) The term shall not include any renunciation of citizenship that has been reversed as a result of administrative or judicial appeal.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Revolver.</E> A projectile weapon, of the pistol type, having a breechloading chambered cylinder so arranged that the cocking of the hammer or movement of the trigger rotates it and brings the next cartridge in line with the barrel for firing.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Rifle.</E> A weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder, and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of an explosive to fire only a single projectile through a rifled bore for each single pull of the trigger.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Secure gun storage or safety device.</E>
                  (1) A device that, when installed on a firearm, is designed to prevent the firearm from being operated without first deactivating the device;
                  </P>
                  <P>(2) A device incorporated into the design of the firearm that is designed to prevent the operation of the firearm by anyone not having access to the device; or</P>
                  <P>(3) A safe, gun safe, gun case, lock box, or other device that is designed to be or can be used to store a firearm and that is designed to be unlocked only by means of a key, a combination, or other similar means.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Semiautomatic assault weapon.</E> (a) Any of the firearms, or copies or duplicates of the firearms in any caliber, known as:</P>
                <P>(1) Norinco, Mitchell, and Poly Technologies Avtomat Kalashnikovs (all models),</P>
                <P>(2) Action Arms Israeli Military Industries UZI and Galil,</P>
                <P>(3) Beretta Ar70 (SC-70),</P>
                <P>(4) Colt AR-15,</P>
                <P>(5) Fabrique National FN/FAL, FN/LAR, and FNC,</P>
                <P>(6) SWD M-10, M-11, M-11/9, and M-12,</P>
                <P>(7) Steyr AUG,</P>
                <P>(8) INTRATEC TEC-9, TEC-DC9 and TEC-22, and</P>
                <P>(9) Revolving cylinder shotguns, such as (or similar to) the Street Sweeper and Striker 12;</P>
                <P>(b) A semiautomatic rifle that has an ability to accept a detachable magazine and has at least 2 of—</P>
                <P>(1) A folding or telescoping stock,</P>
                <P>(2) A pistol grip that protrudes conspicuously beneath the action of the weapon,</P>
                <P>(3) A bayonet mount,</P>
                <P>(4) A flash suppressor or threaded barrel designed to accommodate a flash suppressor, and</P>
                <P>(5) A grenade launcher;</P>
                <P>(c) A semiautomatic pistol that has an ability to accept a detachable magazine and has at least 2 of—</P>
                <P>(1) An ammunition magazine that attaches to the pistol outside of the pistol grip,</P>
                <P>(2) A threaded barrel capable of accepting a barrel extender, flash suppressor, forward handgrip, or silencer,</P>
                <P>(3) A shroud that is attached to, or partially or completely encircles, the barrel and that permits the shooter to hold the firearm with the nontrigger hand without being burned,</P>
                <P>(4) A manufactured weight of 50 ounces or more when the pistol is unloaded, and</P>
                <P>(5) A semiautomatic version of an automatic firearm; and</P>
                <P>(d) A semiautomatic shotgun that has at least 2 of—</P>
                <P>(1) A folding or telescoping stock,</P>
                <P>(2) A pistol grip that protrudes conspicuously beneath the action of the weapon,</P>
                <P>(3) A fixed magazine capacity in excess of 5 rounds, and</P>
                <P>(4) An ability to accept a detachable magazine.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Semiautomatic pistol.</E> Any repeating pistol which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Semiautomatic rifle.</E> Any repeating rifle which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Semiautomatic shotgun.</E> Any repeating shotgun which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Short-barreled rifle.</E> A rifle having one or more barrels less than 16 inches in length, and any weapon made from a rifle, whether by alteration, modification, or otherwise, if such weapon, as modified, has an overall length of less than 26 inches.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Short-barreled shotgun.</E> A shotgun having one or more barrels less than 18 inches in length, and any weapon made from a shotgun, whether by alteration, modification, or otherwise, if such weapon as modified has an overall length of less than 26 inches.<PRTPAGE P="28"/>
                </P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Shotgun.</E> A weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder, and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of the explosive in a fixed shotgun shell to fire through a smooth bore either a number of ball shot or a single projectile for each single pull of the trigger.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">State.</E> A State of the United States. The term shall include the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and the possessions of the United States (not including the Canal Zone).</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">State of residence.</E> The State in which an individual resides. An individual resides in a State if he or she is present in a State with the intention of making a home in that State. If an individual is on active duty as a member of the Armed Forces, the individual's State of residence is the State in which his or her permanent duty station is located, as stated in 18 U.S.C. 921(b). The following are examples that illustrate this definition:
                </P>
                <EXAMPLE>
                  <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 1.</HD>
                  <P>A maintains a home in State X. A travels to State Y on a hunting, fishing, business, or other type of trip. A does not become a resident of State Y by reason of such trip.</P>
                </EXAMPLE>
                <EXAMPLE>
                  <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 2.</HD>
                  <P>A maintains a home in State X and a home in State Y. A resides in State X except for weekends or the summer months of the year and in State Y for the weekends or the summer months of the year. During the time that A actually resides in State X, A is a resident of State X, and during the time that A actually resides in State Y, A is a resident of State Y.</P>
                </EXAMPLE>
                <EXAMPLE>
                  <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 3.</HD>
                  <P>A, an alien, travels to the United States on a three-week vacation to State X. A does not have a state of residence in State X because A does not have the intention of making a home in State X while on vacation. This is true regardless of the length of the vacation.</P>
                </EXAMPLE>
                <EXAMPLE>
                  <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 4.</HD>
                  <P>A, an alien, travels to the United States to work for three years in State X. A rents a home in State X, moves his personal possessions into the home, and his family resides with him in the home. A intends to reside in State X during the 3-year period of his employment. A is a resident of State X.</P>
                </EXAMPLE>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Unlawful user of or addicted to any controlled substance.</E> A person who uses a controlled substance and has lost the power of self-control with reference to the use of controlled substance; and any person who is a current user of a controlled substance in a manner other than as prescribed by a licensed physician. Such use is not limited to the use of drugs on a particular day, or within a matter of days or weeks before, but rather that the unlawful use has occurred recently enough to indicate that the individual is actively engaged in such conduct. A person may be an unlawful current user of a controlled substance even though the substance is not being used at the precise time the person seeks to acquire a firearm or receives or possesses a firearm. An inference of current use may be drawn from evidence of a recent use or possession of a controlled substance or a pattern of use or possession that reasonably covers the present time, e.g., a conviction for use or possession of a controlled substance within the past year; multiple arrests for such offenses within the past 5 years if the most recent arrest occurred within the past year; or persons found through a drug test to use a controlled substance unlawfully, provided that the test was administered within the past year. For a current or former member of the Armed Forces, an inference of current use may be drawn from recent disciplinary or other administrative action based on confirmed drug use, e.g., court-martial conviction, nonjudicial punishment, or an administrative discharge based on drug use or drug rehabilitation failure.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">Unserviceable firearm.</E> A firearm which is incapable of discharging a shot by means of an explosive and is incapable of being readily restored to a firing condition.</P>
                <P>
                  <E T="03">U.S.C.</E> The United States Code.</P>
                <SECAUTH>(5 U.S.C. 552(a), 80 Stat. 383, as amended; 18 U.S.C. 847 (84 Stat. 959); 18 U.S.C. 926 (82 Stat. 1226))</SECAUTH>
                <CITA>[T.D. ATF-48, 43 FR 13536, Mar. 31, 1978; 44 FR 55842, Sept. 28, 1979]</CITA>
                <EDNOTE>
                  <HD SOURCE="HED">Editorial Note:</HD>
                  <P>For <E T="04">Federal Register</E> citations affecting § 478.11, see the List of CFR Sections Affected, which appears in the Finding Aids section of the printed volume and at <E T="03">www.fdsys.gov.</E>
                  </P>
                </EDNOTE>
            </SECTION>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 478.73 </SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT> [Amended]</SUBJECT>
        </SECTION>
        <REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
        <AMDPAR>4. Section 478.73 is revised to read</AMDPAR>
        <SECTION>
            <SECTNO>§ 478.73</SECTNO>
            <SUBJECT>Notice of revocation, suspension, or imposition of civil fine.</SUBJECT>
            <P>(a) <E T="03">Basis for action.</E> Whenever the Director has reason to believe that a licensee has willfully violated any provision of the Act or this part, a notice of revocation of the license, ATF Form <PRTPAGE P="47"/>4500, may be issued. In addition, a notice of revocation of the license, on ATF Form 4500, may be issued whenever the Director has reason to believe that a licensee fails to have secure gun storage or safety devices available at any place in which firearms are sold under the license to persons who are not licensees (except in any case in which a secure gun storage or safety device is temporarily unavailable because of theft, casualty loss, consumer sales, backorders from a manufacturer, or any other similar reason beyond the control of the licensee). In addition, pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 922(t)(5) and 18 U.S.C. 924(p), a notice of revocation, suspension, or imposition of a civil fine may be issued on ATF Form 4500 whenever the Director has reason to believe that a licensee has knowingly transferred a firearm to an unlicensed person and knowingly failed to comply with the requirements of 18 U.S.C. 922(t)(1) with respect to the transfer and, at the time that the transferee most recently proposed the transfer, the national instant criminal background check system was operating and information was available to the system demonstrating that the transferee's receipt of a firearm would violate 18 U.S.C. 922(g) or 922(n) or State law; or that a licensee has violated 18 U.S.C. 922(z)(1) by selling, delivering, or transferring any handgun to any person other than a licensee, unless the transferee was provided with a secure gun storage or safety device for that handgun.</P>
            <P>(b) <E T="03">Issuance of notice.</E> The notice shall set forth the matters of fact constituting the violations specified, dates, places, and the sections of law and regulations violated. The Director shall afford the licensee 15 days from the date of receipt of the notice in which to request a hearing prior to suspension or revocation of the license, or imposition of a civil fine. If the licensee does not file a timely request for a hearing, the Director shall issue a final notice of suspension or revocation and/or imposition of a civil fine on ATF Form 5300.13, as provided in § 478.74.</P>
            <CITA>[T.D. ATF-415, 63 FR 58278, Oct. 29, 1998, as amended by T.D. ATF-27P, 74 FR 1878, Jan. 14, 2009; T.D. ATF 2013R-9F, 79 FR 46692, Aug. 11, 2014; ATF 2008R-15P; 81 FR 32235, May 23, 2016]</CITA>
        </SECTION>
        </REGTEXT>
        <SIG>
          <DATED>Dated: November 1, 2019.</DATED>
          <NAME>William P. Barr,</NAME>
          <TITLE>Attorney General.</TITLE>
        </SIG>
      </SUPLINF>
      <FRDOC>[FR Doc. 2019-24301 Filed 11-7-19; 8:45 am]</FRDOC>
      <BILCOD> BILLING CODE 4410-FY-P</BILCOD>
    </RULE>