<RULE>
<PREAMB>
<AGENCY TYPE="N">DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE</AGENCY>
<SUBAGY>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives</SUBAGY>
<CFR>27 CFR Part 478</CFR>
<DEPDOC>[Docket No. ATF 24P; AG Order No. 5304-2021]</DEPDOC>
<RIN>RIN 1140-AA10</RIN>
<SUBJECT>Secure Gun Storage and Definition of “Antique Firearm”</SUBJECT>
<AGY>
<HD SOURCE="HED">AGENCY:</HD>
<P>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, Department of Justice.</P>
</AGY>
<ACT>
<HD SOURCE="HED">ACTION:</HD>
<P>Final rule.</P>
</ACT>
<SUM>
<HD SOURCE="HED">SUMMARY:</HD>
<P>The Department of Justice is amending the regulations of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (“ATF”) to codify into regulation certain provisions of the Omnibus Consolidated and Emergency Supplemental Appropriations Act, 1999. This rule amends ATF's regulations to account for the existing statutory requirement that applicants for Federal firearms dealer licenses certify that secure gun storage or safety devices will be available at any place where firearms are sold under the license to nonlicensed individuals. This certification is already included in the Application for Federal Firearms License, ATF Form 7/7CR (“Form 7/7CR”). The regulation also requires applicants for manufacturer or importer licenses to complete the certification if the licensee will have premises where firearms are sold to nonlicensees. Moreover, the regulation requires that the secure gun storage or safety devices be compatible with the firearms offered for sale by the licensee. Finally, it conforms the regulatory definitions of certain terms to the statutory language, including the definition of “antique firearm,” which is amended to include certain modern muzzle loading firearms.</P>
</SUM>
<EFFDATE>
<HD SOURCE="HED">DATES:</HD>
<P>This rule is effective February 3, 2022.</P>
</EFFDATE>
<FURINF>
<PRTPAGE P="183"/>
<HD SOURCE="HED">FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:</HD>
<P>Vivian Chu, Office of Regulatory Affairs, Enforcement Programs and Services, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, U.S. Department of Justice, 99 New York Avenue NE, Washington, DC 20226; telephone: (202) 648-7070.</P>
</FURINF>
</PREAMB>
<SUPLINF>
<HD SOURCE="HED">SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION:</HD>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">I. Background</HD>
<P>
On October 21, 1998, Public Law 105-277 (112 Stat. 2681), the Omnibus Consolidated and Emergency Supplemental Appropriations Act, 1999 (“the Act”), was enacted. Among other things, the Act amended the Gun Control Act of 1968, Public Law 90-618 (82 Stat. 1213) (“GCA”) (codified as amended at 18 U.S.C. chapter 44). Some of the GCA amendments made by the Act are as follows: 
<SU>1</SU>
<FTREF/>
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>1</SU>
 The Child Safety Lock Act of 2005 (“CSLA”), enacted as part of the Protection of Lawful Commerce in Arms Act, Public Law 109-92 (119 Stat. 2095), amended the GCA by adding a new subsection, 18 U.S.C. 922(z). This subsection requires licensed importers, manufacturers, and dealers to provide secure gun storage or safety devices whenever they sell, deliver, or transfer any handgun to a nonlicensed person.
<E T="03">See</E>
18 U.S.C. 922(z)(1). The CSLA was implemented primarily in a final rule issued shortly before the NPRM was issued for this rule.
<E T="03">See</E>
Federal Firearms License Proceedings—Hearings, 81 FR 32,230 (May 23, 2016) (amending 27 CFR 478.73, which provides that a notice of suspension or revocation of a license, or the imposition of a civil penalty, may be issued whenever the ATF Director has reason to believe that any licensee has violated § 922(z)(1) by selling, delivering, or transferring any handgun to any person other than a licensee, unless the transferee was provided with a secure gun storage or safety device for that handgun). Although the requirements of the CSLA and the regulation at issue in this rulemaking are in some respects similar, the two requirements are distinct: The CSLA requires that licensed importers, manufacturers, and dealers actually provide a secure gun storage or safety device to any nonlicensee that receives a handgun, whereas the regulation at issue in this rulemaking applies more broadly to the sale of “firearms” (not just handguns) to nonlicensees, but requires only that secure gun storage or safety devices be made available (not actually provided).
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>
<E T="03">(1) Secure Gun Storage.</E>
The Act amended section 923(d)(1) of title 18, United States Code, to require that, with certain exceptions, applicants for Federal firearms dealer licenses certify the availability of secure gun storage or safety devices at any place where firearms are sold under the license to nonlicensees. 18 U.S.C. 923(d)(1)(G). The certification requirement does not apply where a secure gun storage or safety device is temporarily unavailable because of theft, casualty loss, consumer sales, backorders from a manufacturer, or any other similar reason beyond the control of the licensee.
<E T="03">Id.</E>
</P>
<P>In addition, the Act amended 18 U.S.C. 923(e) to provide that the Attorney General may revoke, after notice and opportunity for hearing, the license of any Federal firearms licensee that fails to have secure gun storage or safety devices available at any place where firearms are sold under the license to nonlicensees, subject to the same exceptions noted above.</P>
<P>The Act defined the term “secure gun storage or safety device” in 18 U.S.C. 921(a)(34) to mean: (1) A device that, when installed on a firearm, is designed to prevent the firearm from being operated without first deactivating the device; (2) a device incorporated into the design of the firearm that is designed to prevent the operation of the firearm by anyone not having access to the device; or (3) a safe, gun safe, gun case, lock box, or other device that is designed to be or can be used to store a firearm and that is designed to be unlocked only by means of a key, a combination, or other similar means.</P>
<P>The provisions of the Act relating to secure gun storage became effective April 19, 1999.</P>
<P>
<E T="03">(2) Definition of Antique Firearm.</E>
The Act amended the definition of “antique firearm” in the GCA to include certain modern muzzle loading firearms. Specifically, section 115 of the Act amended the definition of “antique firearm” in 18 U.S.C. 921(a)(16) to include a weapon that is a muzzle loading rifle, muzzle loading shotgun, or muzzle loading pistol; that is designed to use black powder or a black powder substitute; and that cannot use fixed ammunition. The term expressly does not include any weapon that incorporates a firearm frame or receiver; any firearm converted into a muzzle loading weapon; or any muzzle loading weapon that can be readily converted to fire fixed ammunition by replacing the barrel, bolt, breechblock, or any combination thereof. 18 U.S.C. 921(a)(16)(C).
</P>
<P>The provisions of the Act relating to antique firearms became effective upon the date of enactment, October 21, 1998.</P>
<P>
<E T="03">(3) Miscellaneous Amendments.</E>
Prior to amendment by the Act, the term “rifle” was defined in the GCA to mean “a weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of the explosive in a fixed metallic cartridge to fire only a single projectile through a rifled bore for each single pull of the trigger.” 18 U.S.C. 921(a)(7) (1994). The Act amended the definition of “rifle” by replacing the words “the explosive in a fixed metallic cartridge” with “an explosive.”
<E T="03">See</E>
18 U.S.C. 921(a)(7) (2018).
</P>
<P>
Additionally, prior to amendment by the Act, the term “shotgun” was defined in the GCA to mean “a weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of the explosive in a fixed shotgun shell to fire through a smooth bore either a number of ball shot or a single projectile for each single pull of the trigger.” 18 U.S.C. 921(a)(5) (1994). The Act amended the definition of “shotgun” by replacing the words “the explosive in a fixed shotgun shell” with “an explosive.”
<E T="03">See</E>
18 U.S.C. 921(a)(5) (2018).
</P>
<P>The provisions of the Act relating to the miscellaneous amendments also became effective upon the date of enactment, October 21, 1998.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">II. Proposed Rule</HD>
<P>
On May 26, 2016, the Department of Justice (“the Department”) published in the
<E T="04">Federal Register</E>
a notice of proposed rulemaking (“NPRM”) to codify into regulation certain provisions of the Act. Commerce in Firearms and Explosives; Secure Gun Storage, Amended Definition of Antique Firearm, and Miscellaneous Amendments, 81 FR 33448 (May 26, 2016). The rule proposed amending ATF's regulations to account for the existing statutory requirement that applicants for Federal firearms dealer licenses certify that secure gun storage or safety devices will be available at any place where firearms are sold under the license to nonlicensed individuals. This certification is already included in ATF Form 7/7CR. The NPRM also proposed requiring applicants for Federal firearms manufacturer or importer licenses to complete the certification if the licensee will have premises where firearms are sold to nonlicensees.
</P>
<P>Next, the Department proposed to amend 27 CFR 478.11 by adding a definition for the term “secure gun storage or safety device” that tracks the language in the statute, as well as a new section 27 CFR 478.104 that specifies the terms of the certification requirement. Moreover, the proposed regulation required that the secure gun storage or safety device be compatible with the firearms offered for sale by the licensee. 81 FR at 33449. Therefore, applicants under the proposed rule would be required to certify the availability of compatible secure gun storage or safety devices at any place where firearms were sold under the license to nonlicensees.</P>
<P>
The NPRM proposed applying the certification requirement to applicants for Federal firearms importer or manufacturer licenses if the licensee has
<PRTPAGE P="184"/>
premises where firearms are sold to nonlicensees. Federal regulations provide that a licensed importer or a licensed manufacturer may engage in business on the licensed premises as a dealer in the same type of firearms authorized by the license to be imported or manufactured. 27 CFR 478.41(b). Accordingly, under the proposed rule, an applicant for a Federal firearms importer or manufacturer license that engaged in business on the licensed premises as a dealer of firearms to nonlicensees was required to complete the certification.
</P>
<P>
One provision of the Act provides that, “[n]otwithstanding any other provision of law, evidence regarding compliance or noncompliance [with the secure gun storage or safety device requirement] shall not be admissible as evidence in any proceeding of any court, agency, board, or other entity.” Public Law 105-277, sec. 119, reprinted in 18 U.S.C. 923 note. In the proposed rule, ATF explained that this section applies to civil liability actions against dealers and other similar actions, and not to proceedings associated with license denials or revocations (or appeals in Federal court from decisions in such proceedings) involving noncompliance with the secure gun storage or safety device requirement of the GCA. 81 FR at 33449. The proposed rule amended 27 CFR 478.73 to clarify that a notice of revocation of a Federal firearms license may be issued whenever the ATF Director has reason to believe that a licensee fails to have secure gun storage or safety devices available at any place in which firearms are sold under the license to persons who are not licensees (except in any case in which a secure gun storage or safety device is temporarily unavailable because of theft, casualty loss, consumer sales, backorders from a manufacturer, or any other similar reason beyond the control of the licensee).
<E T="03">Id.</E>
at 33453.
</P>
<P>
Finally, the Department proposed to amend 27 CFR 478.11 to reflect the definitions of the terms “antique firearm,” “rifle,” and “shotgun” set forth in the Act.
<E T="03">Id.</E>
</P>
<P>Comments on the notice of proposed rulemaking were to be submitted to ATF on or before August 24, 2016.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">III. Comment Analysis and Department Response</HD>
<P>In response to the NPRM, with respect to an industry that includes approximately 59,909 federally licensed firearms dealers (including pawnbrokers), 12,673 licensed firearms manufacturers, and 1,054 licensed firearms importers, ATF received only four comments. This small number of responses indicates that a broad majority of the firearms industry accepts codification of behavior that has been statutorily required for more than 20 years.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Comments on Impact on Manufacturers and Importers</HD>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">1. Comments Received</HD>
<P>One commenter argued that the proposed rule imposes the certification requirement on all manufacturers and importers that sell firearms to the public, despite the fact that the statute requires only that dealers in firearms meet the certification requirement. Further, according to the commenter, forcing manufacturers and importers to have secure gun storage available and perhaps even to “use” such secure gun storage could create a burdensome and expensive requirement. Requiring firearms, many of which might not even be finished, to be stored under lock and key every night would, in the opinion of the commenter, be difficult, time consuming, and cost-prohibitive. Therefore, according to the commenter, the proposed rule violated Federal law by creating new requirements for licensees.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">2. Department Response</HD>
<P>
The Department disagrees with the comment that ATF does not have the statutory authority to require licensed manufacturers and importers to certify that secure gun storage or safety devices will be available at any place in which firearms are sold to nonlicensees. Under 18 U.S.C. 923(a), the license application must be in such form and contain the information necessary to determine eligibility for licensing as the Attorney General may prescribe by regulation. Similarly, under 18 U.S.C. 926(a), the Attorney General has the authority to promulgate any rules that are necessary to implement the provisions of the GCA. “Because § 926 authorizes the [Attorney General] to promulgate those regulations which are `necessary,' it almost inevitably confers some measure of discretion to determine what regulations are in fact `necessary.' ”
<E T="03">Nat'l Rifle Ass'n</E>
v.
<E T="03">Brady,</E>
914 F.2d 475, 479 (4th Cir. 1990).
</P>
<P>
Although the language of section 923(d)(1)(G) refers only to applications for license as a dealer, section 923(e), as amended by the Act, more broadly provides that the Attorney General may, after notice and an opportunity for a hearing, “revoke
<E T="03">any</E>
license issued under this section if
<E T="03">the holder of such license</E>
. . . fails to have secure gun storage or safety devices available at any place in which firearms are sold under the license to persons who are not licensees.” (Emphasis added.) Section 923(e) thus applies to all licensees that sell firearms to nonlicensees—not just dealer licensees. Hence, because licensed manufacturers and importers may sell their firearms directly to nonlicensees,
<E T="03">see</E>
27 CFR 478.41(b), ATF has the authority to revoke the licenses of manufacturers or importers if they fail to have secure gun storage or safety devices available for retail transactions. Requiring manufacturers and importers to certify that secure gun storage or safety devices will be available at any place in which firearms are sold to nonlicensees helps ensure that manufacturers and importers are aware of the implicit requirement in section 923(e) that these licensees must make such storage or devices available. This certification has been required of all license applicants except collectors on ATF Form 7/7CR (5300.12/5310.16) for years.
</P>
<P>Finally, neither the NPRM nor the final rule requires manufacturers or importers to use secure gun storage or safety devices on their inventory; rather, they need only make such storage or devices available.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Comments on Compatibility of Devices</HD>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">1. Comments Received</HD>
<P>One commenter noted that 18 U.S.C. 923 does not explicitly require that secure gun storage or safety devices maintained by Federal firearms dealers be compatible or even be used, only that they be available; therefore, according to the commenter, the proposed rule cannot require it. Further, the commenter noted that ATF has no authority to revoke the license of a dealer that does not lock up its firearms.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">2. Department Response</HD>
<P>The commenter misinterpreted the proposed rule's application. The proposed rule did not, as the commenter suggested, require federally licensed dealers to use compatible devices on their inventory, nor did the rule require them to lock up and store their firearms inventory. Rather, the NPRM proposed implementing 18 U.S.C. 923(d)(1)(G) by requiring applicants for dealer licenses, or those licensed manufacturers and importers that will also deal firearms to nonlicensed individuals as permitted in 27 CFR 478.41(b), to certify only that compatible secure gun storage or safety devices are available at any place where firearms are sold under the license to nonlicensed individuals.</P>
<P>
The Department believes the compatibility language in the rule is
<PRTPAGE P="185"/>
consistent with the text of the statute because it clarifies that the secure gun storage or safety devices made available must be compatible with the firearms offered for sale by the licensee.
</P>
<P>
Courts have explained that “the administration and enforcement of a statute call upon the agency charged with its execution to interpret it.”
<E T="03">Continental Airlines, Inc.</E>
v.
<E T="03">Dep't of Transportation,</E>
843 F.2d 1444, 1449 (D.C. Cir. 1988). When a court is called upon to review an agency's construction of a statute it administers, the court looks to the framework set forth in
<E T="03">Chevron U.S.A., Inc.</E>
v.
<E T="03">Natural Resources Defense Council, Inc.,</E>
467 U.S. 837 (1984). The first step of
<E T="03">Chevron</E>
review is to ask “whether Congress has directly spoken to the precise question at issue.”
<E T="03">Id.</E>
842. “If the intent of Congress is clear, that is the end of the matter; for the court, as well as the agency, must give effect to the unambiguously expressed intent of Congress. If, however, the court determines Congress has not directly addressed the precise question at issue . . . the question for the court is whether the agency's answer is based on a permissible construction of the statute.”
<E T="03">Id.</E>
at 842-43 (footnote omitted). Although the Act defines “secure gun storage or safety device,” that definition does not specify whether or with which sorts of firearms the secure gun storage and safety devices must be compatible. The Department believes that this rule comports with the best reading of the statute and permissibly clarifies that such storage and devices must be compatible with the firearms sold at the licensed premises. This specification in the regulation resolves any ambiguity in the statute and fulfills its purpose because customers purchasing firearms should be able to leave the premises with a secure gun storage or safety device that is compatible with the type of firearm they purchased. A contrary rule, under which licensees could comply with the statute by making available exclusively devices that are incompatible with the firearms they sell, would unreasonably thwart Congress's evident purpose in the Act.
<E T="03">See City of Chicago</E>
v.
<E T="03">U.S. Dep't of Treasury, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms,</E>
423 F.3d 777, 781 (7th Cir. 2005) (statutes should not be read in a way that “would thwart Congress' intention”).
</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Comments on Noncompliance Evidence in License Denial or Revocation Procedures</HD>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">1. Comments Received</HD>
<P>
In the NPRM, ATF referenced a provision in the Act that states that “evidence regarding compliance or noncompliance [with the secure gun storage or safety device requirement] shall not be admissible as evidence in any proceeding of any court, agency, board, or other entity.”
<E T="03">See</E>
Public Law 105-277, sec. 119. ATF explained that, based on basic tenets of statutory construction, it reads the evidentiary limitation as applying only “to civil liability actions against dealers and other similar actions, and not to proceedings associated with license denials or revocations (or appeals in Federal court from decisions in such proceedings) involving noncompliance with the secure gun storage or safety device requirement” of the Act. 81 FR at 33449.
</P>
<P>Three commenters asserted that this provision of the Act prohibits the use of a dealer's compliance or noncompliance with the secure gun storage or safety device requirement in any administrative proceedings to deny or revoke a Federal firearms license. Two commenters also argued that ATF's interpretation substitutes its judgment for that of Congress, and, by effectively amending legislation, violates the “Separation of Powers Doctrine.” These commenters stated that ATF does not have the power to change or ignore statutes. They argued that words have meaning, and that ATF cannot construe statutes to permit something the plain text prohibits or create an exception for ATF's administrative hearings where one does not exist in the law.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">2. Department Response</HD>
<P>
The Department respectfully disagrees. There are at least two canons of statutory interpretation that inform the Department's reading of the evidence provision the commenters relied on. The first relevant canon provides that, “[w]henever a power is given by statute, everything necessary to make it effectual or requisite to attain the end is implied.”
<E T="03">Luis</E>
v.
<E T="03">United States,</E>
136 S. Ct. 1093, 1097 (2016) (Thomas, J., concurring) (quoting 1 J. Kent, Commentaries on American Law 464 (13th ed. 1884)). The second relevant canon provides that a “court will not merely look to a particular clause in which general words may be used, but will take in connection with it the whole statute . . . and the objects and policy of the law.”
<E T="03">Stafford</E>
v.
<E T="03">Briggs,</E>
444 U.S. 527, 535 (1980) (quoting
<E T="03">Brown</E>
v.
<E T="03">Duchesne,</E>
19 How. 183, 194 (1857)). The evidence provision cannot be read in isolation. Rather, it must be read within the context of the rest of the statute, including the specific grant of authority for the Attorney General to revoke the license of a licensee that does not comply with the Act. Moreover, the Act specifically provides that none of its amendments “shall be construed . . . as creating a cause of action against any firearms dealer or any other person for any civil liability.” 18 U.S.C. 923 note. That prohibition on civil liability implies that Congress expected compliance with the secure gun storage or safety device requirement to be enforced not by private individuals in civil actions, but by the Attorney General in administrative proceedings, in accordance with the specific authority granted to the Attorney General to do so in 18 U.S.C. 923(e). The Attorney General could not fulfill this role if, as asserted by the commenters, evidence of noncompliance could not be used in administrative proceedings related to that noncompliance, thus indicating that the evidence provision in the Act does not apply to administrative proceedings regarding compliance with the secure gun storage or safety device requirement.
<E T="03">Cf. United States</E>
v.
<E T="03">Tohono O'Odham Nation,</E>
563 U.S. 307, 315 (2011) (“Courts should not render statutes nugatory through construction.”).
</P>
<P>
The Department's interpretation of the evidence provision is further supported by the legislative history. The secure gun storage provisions that were enacted were initially sponsored by Senator Larry Craig as part of S.10, the Violent and Repeat Juvenile Offender Act of 1997, for which a Senate report was produced by the Senate Committee on the Judiciary.
<SU>2</SU>
<FTREF/>
The Committee's report stated that “[t]he penalty for willful violation . . . is revocation of the dealer's license,
<E T="03">after notice and opportunity for hearing is given</E>
pursuant to current law.” 
<SU>3</SU>
<FTREF/>
Thus, the Committee evidently expected that noncompliance with the secure gun storage and safety device provisions would be enforced through administrative proceedings, including a hearing. It would accordingly be nonsensical to bar the Attorney General from using evidence of such noncompliance in the same proceedings. Congress, in other words, would not have written the specific amendments giving the Attorney General the ability to revoke or deny a license based on noncompliance if
<PRTPAGE P="186"/>
evidence of noncompliance could not be considered at the hearing ATF is required to conduct under the law. Accordingly—in light of the context in which the evidence provision appears, the legislative history underlying the secure gun storage or safety device requirement, and the authority granted in section 923(e)—the Department's position that the evidence provision does not apply to ATF's enforcement hearings or actions is the best interpretation of the law, and is certainly a permissible interpretation of the provision.
<E T="03">See Chevron,</E>
467 U.S. at 843.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>2</SU>
 S. Rep. No. 105-108, at 108 (1997).
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>3</SU>
 
<E T="03">Id.</E>
(emphasis added).
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>
Furthermore, Congress expressly authorized the Attorney General to deny or revoke a license if the licensee or applicant fails to have or certify that it has secure gun storage or safety devices available at any place in which firearms are sold under the license to persons who are not licensees (with the same exceptions noted above). 18 U.S.C. 923(d), (e). To exercise this authority, the Attorney General is required to provide notice to an applicant or licensee and, upon request of the aggrieved party, is authorized to conduct an administrative hearing to make a final determination. 18 U.S.C. 923(e), (f); 27 CFR 771.40-44. The agency's final decision is appealable to a Federal court. 18 U.S.C. 923(f)(3). ATF 
<SU>4</SU>
<FTREF/>
can also institute criminal proceedings against a licensee for violations of the GCA or the regulations. 18 U.S.C. 923(f)(4). The express statutory grant of authority in section 923 to deny or revoke a license based on evidence of noncompliance supersedes the general language the commenters relied on.
<E T="03">See RadLAX Gateway Hotel, LLC</E>
v.
<E T="03">Amalgamated Bank,</E>
566 U.S. 639, 645 (2012) (citing
<E T="03">HCSC-Laundry</E>
v.
<E T="03">United States,</E>
450 U.S. 1, 6 (1981) (per curiam), for the proposition that the specific governs the general, “particularly when the two [statutes] are interrelated and closely positioned, both in fact being parts of [the same statutory scheme]”);
<E T="03">Busic</E>
v.
<E T="03">United States,</E>
446 U.S. 398, 406 (1980).
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>4</SU>
 The Attorney General is responsible for enforcing the GCA, as amended. This responsibility includes the authority to promulgate regulations necessary to enforce the provisions of the GCA.
<E T="03">See</E>
18 U.S.C. 926(a). The Attorney General has delegated the responsibility for administering and enforcing the GCA to the ATF Director, subject to the direction of the Attorney General and Deputy Attorney General.
<E T="03">See</E>
28 CFR 0.130(a)(1)-(2).
</P>
</FTNT>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">D. Comments on Definitions of “Rifle” and “Shotgun”</HD>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">1. Comments Received</HD>
<P>Comments relating to the definitions of “rifle” and “shotgun” stated that, to prevent confusion between a modern rifle or shotgun and a muzzleloader or antique firearm, and to preclude future Federal “over reach” to classify muzzle loading arms as rifles, the definitions should specifically exclude muzzle loading arms using black powder or black powder substitutes. Additionally, one commenter stated that “explosive” is not the correct word for the propellant in a modern firearm and suggested amending the term “explosive” in the definitions of “rifle” and “shotgun” to reference smokeless solid propellants that deflagrate rather than detonate, thereby clarifying that metallic cartridge firearms using smokeless propellants do not fall under the definitions of “rifle” or “shotgun” due to their lack of use of an explosive that detonates.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">2. Department Response</HD>
<P>The Department respectfully declines to revise the definitions of “rifle” and “shotgun” to refer to smokeless solid propellants, rather than an “explosive,” because doing so would not be consistent with the statutory definitions set forth in the Act. The current statutory definition for “antique firearm” excludes certain muzzle loading firearms using black powder or black powder substitutes from the definition of “firearm,” thus making the inclusion of additional language to exclude them unnecessary. This final rule updates the existing regulations to reflect the current language of the statute.</P>
<P>Further, the Department does not agree with the suggested clarification of the term “explosive” in the definitions of “rifle” and “shotgun.” The use of the phrase “by action of an explosive” within the definitions of “rifle” and “shotgun” is appropriate, as it is descriptive of a process and not a classification of the propellant powder. The provisions of the Act relating to antique firearms and definitions of the terms “rifle” and “shotgun” became effective on the day of enactment, October 21, 1998. This final rule updates the existing regulations to reflect the current language of the statute.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">IV. Final Rule</HD>
<P>This final rule implements the amendments to the regulations in 27 CFR part 478 that were specified in the NPRM published on May 26, 2016 (81 FR 33448) without change.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">V. Statutory and Executive Order Review</HD>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">A. Executive Orders 12866 and 13563</HD>
<P>Executive Order 12866 (Regulatory Planning and Review) directs agencies to assess the costs and benefits of available regulatory alternatives and, if regulation is necessary, to select regulatory approaches that maximize net benefits (including potential economic, environmental, public health and safety effects, distributive impacts, and equity). Executive Order 13563 (Improving Regulation and Regulatory Review) emphasizes the importance of quantifying both costs and benefits, of reducing costs, of harmonizing rules, and of maintaining flexibility.</P>
<P>The Office of Management and Budget (“OMB”) has determined that, although this final rule is not economically significant, it is a “significant regulatory action” under section 3(f)(4) of Executive Order 12866 because this final rule raises novel legal or policy issues arising out of legal mandates. Accordingly, the rule has been reviewed by OMB.</P>
<P>
This rule requires that Federal firearms licensees (“FFLs”) make available secure gun storage or safety devices to non-FFLs that purchase firearms. Furthermore, this rule requires that all FFLs must certify that they have secure gun storage or safety devices available if they sell firearms to non-FFLs. This section describes the affected population, costs, and benefits for this rule. In determining the costs and benefits of this rule, ATF has followed OMB guidance for conducting regulatory analyses.
<E T="03">See</E>
OMB, Memorandum to the Heads of Executive Agencies and Establishments,
<E T="03">Re: Regulatory Analysis,</E>
Circular A-4 (Sept. 17, 2003) (“Circular A-4”). According to that guidance, regulations such as this one that largely restate self-enforcing statutory requirements should be analyzed against a baseline that pre-dates the enactment of the relevant statute. Thus, although ATF has implemented and enforced the Act in the years since its passage even in the absence of the regulation at issue in this rulemaking, the costs and benefits of doing so have been attributed to this regulation for the purpose of this analysis.
</P>
<P>
Table 1 provides the summary of the expected effects that this rule will have on the public. For more details regarding this analysis, please refer to the standalone regulatory analysis (“RA”) located on the docket.
<PRTPAGE P="187"/>
</P>
<GPOTABLE COLS="2" OPTS="L2,i1" CDEF="s100,r100">
<TTITLE>Table 1—Summary of Affected Population, Costs, and Benefits</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">Category</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Final rule</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Applicability</ENT>
<ENT>• All FFLs.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT>• Type 1 FFL—Dealer in firearms other than destructive devices.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT>• Type 2 FFL—Pawnbroker in firearms other than destructive devices.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Affected Population</ENT>
<ENT>• 130,525 FFLs.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT>• 52,795 Type 1 FFLs.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="22"> </ENT>
<ENT>• 7,114 Type 2 FFLs.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Total Costs to Industry, Public, and Government (7% Discount Rate)</ENT>
<ENT>$853,187 at 7% annualized.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Savings (7% Discount Rate)</ENT>
<ENT>N/A.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Benefits (7% Discount Rate)</ENT>
<ENT>N/A.</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Benefits non-monetized</ENT>
<ENT>
• Inhibits unauthorized access to privately owned firearms by individuals such as children, who might suffer accidental injuries.
<LI>• Inhibits access to privately owned firearms by criminals, who might use them for illicit activities.</LI>
</ENT>
</ROW>
</GPOTABLE>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">1. Need for Federal Regulation</HD>
<P>Agencies take regulatory action for various reasons. One reason is to carry out Congress's policy decisions, as expressed in statutes. Here, this rulemaking aims to comply with the Omnibus Consolidated and Emergency Supplemental Appropriations Act of 1999 relating to secure gun storage. Another reason underpinning regulatory action is the failure of the market to compensate for negative externalities caused by commercial activity. A negative externality can be the byproduct of a transaction between two parties that is not accounted for in the transaction. This final rule addresses a negative externality. The negative externality of the sale of firearms is that the firearms might not be stored properly and could be accessed by children who could cause accidents with the firearms or accessed by criminals who would use them for illicit activities. This rule provides nonlicensed firearm owners with the option to have devices that enable them to store their firearms so as to inhibit children or criminals from accessing their firearms.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">2. Affected Population</HD>
<P>This rulemaking affects two populations. The first population is the number of FFLs required to certify on Form 7/7CR that secure gun storage or safety devices will be available at any place in which firearms are sold under the license to persons who are not licensees. The second population is the number of FFLs that need to acquire secure gun storage or safety devices to make available at their place of business.</P>
<P>Entities directly affected by the requirement to certify the availability of secure gun storage or safety devices are all FFLs. Although this rule primarily affects FFLs that sell firearms to nonlicensed persons, this rule affects all FFLs in that all FFL applicants must indicate on the Form 7/7CR application whether the applicants have gun storage or safety devices available for nonlicensees or whether this requirement is not applicable because they are seeking a Type 3 license for collectors.</P>
<P>Because the Act was enacted shortly before 1999, and because ATF has required certification since 1999, ATF estimated the affected population to be all FFLs from 1999 to present. However, FFLs have to certify the availability of secure gun storage or safety devices only when they apply as new FFLs or every three years when they renew their Federal firearms license. Tables 2 and 3 show the numbers of new applications and renewals by FFL type and year. For more information on the methodology used to determine the numbers of new FFLs by Type, please refer to the standalone RA.</P>
<GPOTABLE COLS="6" OPTS="L2,i1" CDEF="s25,15,15,15,15,15">
<TTITLE>Table 2—New and Renewal Applications of Type 1, 2, 3, 6, and 7 Federal Firearms Licensees</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">Year</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
01—Dealer
<LI>in firearms</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
02—Pawnbroker
<LI>in firearms</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
03—Collector of
<LI>curios and relics</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
06—Manufacturer
<LI>of ammunition for firearms</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
07—Manufacturer
<LI>of firearms</LI>
</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">1999</ENT>
<ENT>24,977</ENT>
<ENT>3,516</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>787</ENT>
<ENT>574</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2000</ENT>
<ENT>24,829</ENT>
<ENT>3,583</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>777</ENT>
<ENT>652</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2001</ENT>
<ENT>24,788</ENT>
<ENT>3,572</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>757</ENT>
<ENT>715</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2002</ENT>
<ENT>24,660</ENT>
<ENT>3,615</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>727</ENT>
<ENT>800</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2003</ENT>
<ENT>24,553</ENT>
<ENT>3,639</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>723</ENT>
<ENT>874</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2004</ENT>
<ENT>24,547</ENT>
<ENT>3,579</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>711</ENT>
<ENT>938</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2005</ENT>
<ENT>24,494</ENT>
<ENT>3,553</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>683</ENT>
<ENT>1,034</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2006</ENT>
<ENT>24,406</ENT>
<ENT>3,503</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>679</ENT>
<ENT>1,143</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2007</ENT>
<ENT>24,266</ENT>
<ENT>3,434</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>690</ENT>
<ENT>1,315</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2008</ENT>
<ENT>24,148</ENT>
<ENT>3,345</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>708</ENT>
<ENT>1,482</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2009</ENT>
<ENT>23,763</ENT>
<ENT>3,337</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>759</ENT>
<ENT>1,782</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2010</ENT>
<ENT>23,284</ENT>
<ENT>3,368</ENT>
<ENT>19,919</ENT>
<ENT>859</ENT>
<ENT>2,097</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2011</ENT>
<ENT>20,956</ENT>
<ENT>3,046</ENT>
<ENT>22,338</ENT>
<ENT>816</ENT>
<ENT>2,343</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2012</ENT>
<ENT>21,259</ENT>
<ENT>3,105</ENT>
<ENT>21,622</ENT>
<ENT>855</ENT>
<ENT>3,104</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2013</ENT>
<ENT>22,274</ENT>
<ENT>3,221</ENT>
<ENT>13,134</ENT>
<ENT>966</ENT>
<ENT>3,748</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2014</ENT>
<ENT>22,049</ENT>
<ENT>3,235</ENT>
<ENT>6,767</ENT>
<ENT>1,033</ENT>
<ENT>3,966</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2015</ENT>
<ENT>20,876</ENT>
<ENT>3,029</ENT>
<ENT>18,671</ENT>
<ENT>967</ENT>
<ENT>3,901</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2016</ENT>
<ENT>22,104</ENT>
<ENT>3,146</ENT>
<ENT>19,322</ENT>
<ENT>957</ENT>
<ENT>4,317</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2017</ENT>
<ENT>21,896</ENT>
<ENT>3,043</ENT>
<ENT>18,876</ENT>
<ENT>873</ENT>
<ENT>4,622</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2018</ENT>
<ENT>20,479</ENT>
<ENT>2,799</ENT>
<ENT>17,643</ENT>
<ENT>776</ENT>
<ENT>4,603</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2019</ENT>
<ENT>20,034</ENT>
<ENT>2,726</ENT>
<ENT>17,478</ENT>
<ENT>709</ENT>
<ENT>4,848</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<PRTPAGE P="188"/>
<ENT I="01">2020</ENT>
<ENT>22,710</ENT>
<ENT>3,060</ENT>
<ENT>20,150</ENT>
<ENT>777</ENT>
<ENT>6,076</ENT>
</ROW>
<TNOTE>
* 
<E T="02">Note:</E>
Numbers may not add for Type 1 FFLs due to adjustments to ensure the numbers of applications in Tables 2 and 3 match total FFLs in this table.
</TNOTE>
</GPOTABLE>
<GPOTABLE COLS="6" OPTS="L2,i1" CDEF="s25,15,15,15,15,15">
<TTITLE>Table 3—New and Renewal Applications of Type 8, 9, 10, and 11 Federal Firearms Licensees</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">Year</CHED>
<CHED H="1">08—Importer of firearms</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
09—Dealer in
<LI>destructive</LI>
<LI>devices</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
10—Manufacturer
<LI>of destructive</LI>
<LI>devices</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
11—Importer of
<LI>destructive</LI>
<LI>devices</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
Total new
<LI>applications</LI>
<LI>and renewals</LI>
</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">1999</ENT>
<ENT>265</ENT>
<ENT>4</ENT>
<ENT>44</ENT>
<ENT>26</ENT>
<ENT>50,112</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2000</ENT>
<ENT>275</ENT>
<ENT>4</ENT>
<ENT>46</ENT>
<ENT>26</ENT>
<ENT>50,111</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2001</ENT>
<ENT>283</ENT>
<ENT>5</ENT>
<ENT>45</ENT>
<ENT>28</ENT>
<ENT>50,112</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2002</ENT>
<ENT>303</ENT>
<ENT>7</ENT>
<ENT>52</ENT>
<ENT>31</ENT>
<ENT>50,114</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2003</ENT>
<ENT>307</ENT>
<ENT>7</ENT>
<ENT>56</ENT>
<ENT>35</ENT>
<ENT>50,113</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2004</ENT>
<ENT>315</ENT>
<ENT>7</ENT>
<ENT>60</ENT>
<ENT>37</ENT>
<ENT>50,113</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2005</ENT>
<ENT>317</ENT>
<ENT>7</ENT>
<ENT>66</ENT>
<ENT>40</ENT>
<ENT>50,113</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2006</ENT>
<ENT>327</ENT>
<ENT>8</ENT>
<ENT>81</ENT>
<ENT>47</ENT>
<ENT>50,113</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2007</ENT>
<ENT>338</ENT>
<ENT>11</ENT>
<ENT>86</ENT>
<ENT>52</ENT>
<ENT>50,111</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2008</ENT>
<ENT>344</ENT>
<ENT>15</ENT>
<ENT>94</ENT>
<ENT>57</ENT>
<ENT>50,112</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2009</ENT>
<ENT>365</ENT>
<ENT>17</ENT>
<ENT>107</ENT>
<ENT>64</ENT>
<ENT>50,113</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2010</ENT>
<ENT>375</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>119</ENT>
<ENT>71</ENT>
<ENT>50,112</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2011</ENT>
<ENT>349</ENT>
<ENT>18</ENT>
<ENT>112</ENT>
<ENT>69</ENT>
<ENT>50,047</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2012</ENT>
<ENT>355</ENT>
<ENT>22</ENT>
<ENT>109</ENT>
<ENT>71</ENT>
<ENT>50,502</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2013</ENT>
<ENT>411</ENT>
<ENT>24</ENT>
<ENT>113</ENT>
<ENT>76</ENT>
<ENT>43,967</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2014</ENT>
<ENT>451</ENT>
<ENT>26</ENT>
<ENT>114</ENT>
<ENT>80</ENT>
<ENT>37,721</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2015</ENT>
<ENT>428</ENT>
<ENT>25</ENT>
<ENT>117</ENT>
<ENT>82</ENT>
<ENT>48,096</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2016</ENT>
<ENT>429</ENT>
<ENT>27</ENT>
<ENT>130</ENT>
<ENT>86</ENT>
<ENT>50,518</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2017</ENT>
<ENT>430</ENT>
<ENT>30</ENT>
<ENT>138</ENT>
<ENT>90</ENT>
<ENT>49,998</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2018</ENT>
<ENT>413</ENT>
<ENT>36</ENT>
<ENT>138</ENT>
<ENT>88</ENT>
<ENT>46,975</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2019</ENT>
<ENT>413</ENT>
<ENT>48</ENT>
<ENT>146</ENT>
<ENT>94</ENT>
<ENT>46,496</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2020</ENT>
<ENT>489</ENT>
<ENT>55</ENT>
<ENT>182</ENT>
<ENT>116</ENT>
<ENT>53,615</ENT>
</ROW>
<TNOTE>
* 
<E T="02">Note:</E>
Numbers may not add for Type 1 FFLs due to adjustments to ensure the number of applications in Tables 2 and 3 match total FFLs in this table.
</TNOTE>
</GPOTABLE>
<P>
The second population directly affected by this rule primarily consists of Type 1 and 2 FFLs that sell firearms to the public. These FFLs must acquire secure gun storage or safety devices to be made available to firearm purchasers in their place of business. Based on the year the Act was enacted, ATF assumed that all Type 1 and 2 FFLs in 1999 had to acquire secure gun storage or safety devices to make available to any potential nonlicensee customers. From 2000 onwards, only new FFLs would need to acquire some form of gun storage or safety devices to make available to their customers. Although this rule affects all FFLs that sell firearms to nonlicensed individuals, no cost was attributed to Type 9, 10, and 11 licensees because they primarily deal, manufacture, and import destructive devices used by domestic and foreign governments rather than selling firearms at the retail level to nonlicensed individuals. Similarly, although Type 7 and 8 licensees are manufacturers and importers that may sell firearms to nonlicensed persons, most of these licensees, even prior to enactment of the Act, have voluntarily included secure gun storage or safety devices for their firearms, and hence would not have needed to separately acquire such storage or devices to make them available to nonlicensees.
<SU>5</SU>
<FTREF/>
Of those Type 7 and 8 FFLs that do not provide secure gun storage or safety devices, ATF assumed these licensees primarily sell firearms wholesale to Type 1 FFLs and do not sell to nonlicensed persons.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>5</SU>
 
<E T="03">See Hearing before the Subcomm. on the Constitution of the S. Comm. on the Judiciary,</E>
117th Cong. (2021), 2021 WL 2138600 (discussing the success of Project ChildSafe, through which “manufacturers have voluntarily included a locking device in every box sold since the late 1980's” (testimony of Joseph Bartozzi, President and CEO, National Shooting Sports Foundation)); S. Rep. No. 105-108, at 201-02 (“The arguments raised against safety locks ring hollow, especially in light of the recent announcement by eight[] of the Nation's largest handgun manufacturers that they will voluntarily comply with the heart of Senator Kohl's amendment by packaging a child safety lock with every handgun they sell.”).
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>
Based on congressional testimony and subject matter experts' (“SMEs”) experience, most firearm manufacturers now include locks with new purchases of firearms, and, as noted above, have been doing so since before the enactment of the Act.
<SU>6</SU>
<FTREF/>
ATF, however, is not certain of the exact date when manufacturers and importers began voluntarily providing locks and, in the interest of not underestimating the costs attributable to this rule, ATF assumed that all Type 1 FFLs in 1999 would need to acquire secure gun storage or safety devices to make available to their customers. ATF then estimated that, as manufacturers and importers continued to provide locks with their firearms, and as this practice became more common, a decreasing number of FFLs needed to acquire secure gun storage or safety devices each year until year 2003. After 2003, ATF maintained a constant rate of 20 percent of FFLs that do not receive safety devices with the firearms they sell to account for any manufacturers and importers that, even today, do not provide safety devices with their firearms. In addition, Type 2 FFLs are pawnshops that acquire previously owned firearms. ATF does not know
<PRTPAGE P="189"/>
whether the firearms acquired by Type 2 FFLs have secure locks or not. Therefore, ATF assumed that all new Type 2 FFLs need to acquire secure gun storage or safety devices to satisfy the requirements of the Act.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>6</SU>
 
<E T="03">See supra</E>
note 5.
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>Because Type 2 FFLs primarily deal with secondhand firearms and not new purchases, ATF assumed that, in 1999, all Type 2 FFLs acquired secure gun storage or safety devices and, from 2000 onward, only new Type 2 FFLs needed to acquire a means of securing firearms. Therefore, ATF assumed that pawnbrokers from 2000 to 2020 consisted only of new Type 2 FFLs.</P>
<P>Table 4 provides the estimated number of Type 1 and 2 FFLs that needed to acquire secure gun storage or safety devices and make them available at their place of business for potential nonlicensed customers. For more detailed information on obtaining the population of FFLs needing to acquire secure gun storage or safety devices to make available, please refer to the standalone RA.</P>
<GPOTABLE COLS="5" OPTS="L2,i1" CDEF="s50,15,16,15,15">
<TTITLE>Table 4—FFL Types 1 and 2 That Needed To Purchase Secure Gun Storage or Safety Devices</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">Year</CHED>
<CHED H="1">New type 1 FFL</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
Rate of FFLs that do not receive locks from
<LI>manufacturers</LI>
<LI>(%)</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Type 1 FFL</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
Type 2 FFL
<LI>needing</LI>
</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">1999</ENT>
<ENT>71,290</ENT>
<ENT>100</ENT>
<ENT>71,290</ENT>
<ENT>10,035</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2000</ENT>
<ENT>8,677</ENT>
<ENT>80</ENT>
<ENT>6,942</ENT>
<ENT>1,252</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2001</ENT>
<ENT>8,663</ENT>
<ENT>60</ENT>
<ENT>5,198</ENT>
<ENT>1,248</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2002</ENT>
<ENT>8,618</ENT>
<ENT>40</ENT>
<ENT>3,447</ENT>
<ENT>1,263</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2003</ENT>
<ENT>8,581</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,716</ENT>
<ENT>1,272</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2004</ENT>
<ENT>8,579</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,716</ENT>
<ENT>1,251</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2005</ENT>
<ENT>8,560</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,712</ENT>
<ENT>1,242</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2006</ENT>
<ENT>8,529</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,706</ENT>
<ENT>1,224</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2007</ENT>
<ENT>8,481</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,696</ENT>
<ENT>1,200</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2008</ENT>
<ENT>8,439</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,688</ENT>
<ENT>1,169</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2009</ENT>
<ENT>8,305</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,661</ENT>
<ENT>1,166</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2010</ENT>
<ENT>8,137</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,627</ENT>
<ENT>1,177</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2011</ENT>
<ENT>7,768</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,554</ENT>
<ENT>854</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2012</ENT>
<ENT>9,034</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,807</ENT>
<ENT>971</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2013</ENT>
<ENT>10,177</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>2,035</ENT>
<ENT>1,063</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2014</ENT>
<ENT>7,874</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,575</ENT>
<ENT>823</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2015</ENT>
<ENT>7,088</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,418</ENT>
<ENT>730</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2016</ENT>
<ENT>7,552</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,510</ENT>
<ENT>762</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2017</ENT>
<ENT>6,599</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,320</ENT>
<ENT>645</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2018</ENT>
<ENT>6,314</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,263</ENT>
<ENT>603</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2019</ENT>
<ENT>5,667</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,133</ENT>
<ENT>532</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2020</ENT>
<ENT>
<E T="03">8,442</E>
</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>1,688</ENT>
<ENT>772</ENT>
</ROW>
</GPOTABLE>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">3. Costs</HD>
<P>This analysis considers the rule's direct (or industry) costs, indirect costs, and government costs. Industry costs are the costs to FFLs that need to certify the availability of secure gun storage or safety devices and the costs to FFLs that need to acquire secure gun storage or safety devices to make available to the public. Indirect costs are those costs associated with organizations and manufacturers providing gun locks or safety devices. Government costs are enforcement costs to ensure that the affected FFLs have been and are continuing to comply with the statute.</P>
<P>
In determining direct, industry costs, ATF used the average wage rate associated with certain job titles listed on Form 7/7CR by FFL type. ATF used a loaded wage rate of 1.42 to include fringe benefits such as insurance as part of the overall compensation.
<SU>7</SU>
<FTREF/>
Because FFLs are segmented by industry type, ATF used a sample from each industry type to determine an average wage rate by each FFL type. For FFLs completing Form 7CR, ATF assigned a leisure wage rate of $16.52 because FFLs that complete Form 7CR are Type 3 FFLs—
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
collectors who do not apply for a license as part of an occupation.
<SU>8</SU>
<FTREF/>
Although Type 3 FFL collectors are not required to make available secure gun storage or safety devices, they are still required to answer the question about availability on Form 7CR by marking “N/A.” Therefore, costs for that action were counted as an industry cost of this rule. For more information on the wages used for each sample, please refer the standalone RA. Table 5 provides the average loaded wage rate by FFL type.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>7</SU>
 Bureau of Labor Statistics, Series Report,
<E T="03">https://data.bls.gov/cgi-bin/srgate.</E>
Data was generated for 2020 using series CMU2010000000000D, CMU2010000000000P and CMU2020000000000D, CMU2020000000000P. Average total compensation was $35.87. Average cost per hour worked was $25.18. Loaded wage rate 1.42 = $35.87/$25.18.
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>8</SU>
 As explained more fully in the accompanying RA, the leisure wage rate was estimated using the calculation described in the Department of Transportation's guidance on the valuation of travel time.
<E T="03">See</E>
Dep't of Transportation, Revised Departmental Guidance on Valuation of Travel Time in Economic Analysis 19 (Sept. 27, 2016),
<E T="03">https://www.transportation.gov/sites/dot.gov/files/docs/2016%20Revised%20Value%20of%20Travel%20Time%20Guidance.pdf.</E>
</P>
</FTNT>
<GPOTABLE COLS="2" OPTS="L2,p1,8/9,i1" CDEF="s50,12">
<TTITLE>Table 5—Average Loaded Wage Rate by FFL Type</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1"> </CHED>
<CHED H="1"> </CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Types 1 and 2</ENT>
<ENT>$82.06</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Type 3</ENT>
<ENT>16.52</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Type 6</ENT>
<ENT>58.91</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Type 7</ENT>
<ENT>62.93</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Type 8</ENT>
<ENT>76.13</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Type 9</ENT>
<ENT>103.44</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Type 10</ENT>
<ENT>87.86</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">Type 11</ENT>
<ENT>109.30</ENT>
</ROW>
</GPOTABLE>
<PRTPAGE P="190"/>
<P>The time needed for an FFL to certify on Form 7/7CR that it has secure gun storage or safety devices (or to mark “N/A”) was estimated at 0.1 minute (0.0017 hours). ATF started with the average loaded wage rate by type of license, multiplied the wage rate by the estimated number of new and renewal FFLs per type from Tables 2 and 3, and multiplied that result by the hour burden to determine the annual cost to certify. Tables 6 and 7 provide the annual costs to certify by FFL type from 1999 to the present.</P>
<GPOTABLE COLS="6" OPTS="L2,i1" CDEF="s50,15,15,15,15,15">
<TTITLE>Table 6—Cost To Certify by FFL Types 1, 2, 3, 6, 7, and 8</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">Year</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Types 1 and 2</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Type 3</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Type 6</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Type 7</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Type 8</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">1999</ENT>
<ENT>$3,897</ENT>
<ENT>$548</ENT>
<ENT>$77</ENT>
<ENT>$60</ENT>
<ENT>$34</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2000</ENT>
<ENT>3,886</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>76</ENT>
<ENT>68</ENT>
<ENT>35</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2001</ENT>
<ENT>3,879</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>74</ENT>
<ENT>75</ENT>
<ENT>36</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2002</ENT>
<ENT>3,867</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>71</ENT>
<ENT>84</ENT>
<ENT>38</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2003</ENT>
<ENT>3,856</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>71</ENT>
<ENT>92</ENT>
<ENT>39</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2004</ENT>
<ENT>3,847</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>70</ENT>
<ENT>98</ENT>
<ENT>40</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2005</ENT>
<ENT>3,836</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>67</ENT>
<ENT>108</ENT>
<ENT>40</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2006</ENT>
<ENT>3,817</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>67</ENT>
<ENT>120</ENT>
<ENT>41</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2007</ENT>
<ENT>3,788</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>68</ENT>
<ENT>138</ENT>
<ENT>43</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2008</ENT>
<ENT>3,760</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>70</ENT>
<ENT>155</ENT>
<ENT>44</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2009</ENT>
<ENT>3,706</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>75</ENT>
<ENT>187</ENT>
<ENT>46</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2010</ENT>
<ENT>3,645</ENT>
<ENT>548</ENT>
<ENT>84</ENT>
<ENT>220</ENT>
<ENT>48</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2011</ENT>
<ENT>3,283</ENT>
<ENT>615</ENT>
<ENT>80</ENT>
<ENT>246</ENT>
<ENT>44</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2012</ENT>
<ENT>3,332</ENT>
<ENT>595</ENT>
<ENT>84</ENT>
<ENT>326</ENT>
<ENT>45</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2013</ENT>
<ENT>3,487</ENT>
<ENT>362</ENT>
<ENT>95</ENT>
<ENT>393</ENT>
<ENT>52</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2014</ENT>
<ENT>3,458</ENT>
<ENT>186</ENT>
<ENT>101</ENT>
<ENT>416</ENT>
<ENT>57</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2015</ENT>
<ENT>3,269</ENT>
<ENT>514</ENT>
<ENT>95</ENT>
<ENT>409</ENT>
<ENT>54</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2016</ENT>
<ENT>3,453</ENT>
<ENT>532</ENT>
<ENT>94</ENT>
<ENT>453</ENT>
<ENT>54</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2017</ENT>
<ENT>3,411</ENT>
<ENT>520</ENT>
<ENT>86</ENT>
<ENT>485</ENT>
<ENT>55</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2018</ENT>
<ENT>3,184</ENT>
<ENT>486</ENT>
<ENT>76</ENT>
<ENT>483</ENT>
<ENT>52</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2019</ENT>
<ENT>3,113</ENT>
<ENT>481</ENT>
<ENT>70</ENT>
<ENT>508</ENT>
<ENT>52</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2020</ENT>
<ENT>3,524</ENT>
<ENT>555</ENT>
<ENT>76</ENT>
<ENT>637</ENT>
<ENT>62</ENT>
</ROW>
</GPOTABLE>
<GPOTABLE COLS="5" OPTS="L2,i1" CDEF="s50,15,15,15,15">
<TTITLE>Table 7—Cost To Certify by FFL Types 9, 10, and 11</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">Year</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Type 9</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Type 10</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Type 11</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Total</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">1999</ENT>
<ENT>$1</ENT>
<ENT>$6</ENT>
<ENT>$5</ENT>
<ENT>$4,564</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2000</ENT>
<ENT>1</ENT>
<ENT>7</ENT>
<ENT>5</ENT>
<ENT>4,562</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2001</ENT>
<ENT>1</ENT>
<ENT>7</ENT>
<ENT>5</ENT>
<ENT>4,561</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2002</ENT>
<ENT>1</ENT>
<ENT>8</ENT>
<ENT>6</ENT>
<ENT>4,560</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2003</ENT>
<ENT>1</ENT>
<ENT>8</ENT>
<ENT>6</ENT>
<ENT>4,558</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2004</ENT>
<ENT>1</ENT>
<ENT>9</ENT>
<ENT>7</ENT>
<ENT>4,556</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2005</ENT>
<ENT>1</ENT>
<ENT>10</ENT>
<ENT>7</ENT>
<ENT>4,554</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2006</ENT>
<ENT>1</ENT>
<ENT>12</ENT>
<ENT>9</ENT>
<ENT>4,551</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2007</ENT>
<ENT>2</ENT>
<ENT>13</ENT>
<ENT>9</ENT>
<ENT>4,545</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2008</ENT>
<ENT>3</ENT>
<ENT>14</ENT>
<ENT>10</ENT>
<ENT>4,540</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2009</ENT>
<ENT>3</ENT>
<ENT>16</ENT>
<ENT>12</ENT>
<ENT>4,529</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2010</ENT>
<ENT>3</ENT>
<ENT>17</ENT>
<ENT>13</ENT>
<ENT>4,515</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2011</ENT>
<ENT>3</ENT>
<ENT>16</ENT>
<ENT>13</ENT>
<ENT>4,300</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2012</ENT>
<ENT>4</ENT>
<ENT>16</ENT>
<ENT>13</ENT>
<ENT>4,415</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2013</ENT>
<ENT>4</ENT>
<ENT>17</ENT>
<ENT>14</ENT>
<ENT>4,423</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2014</ENT>
<ENT>4</ENT>
<ENT>17</ENT>
<ENT>15</ENT>
<ENT>4,255</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2015</ENT>
<ENT>4</ENT>
<ENT>17</ENT>
<ENT>15</ENT>
<ENT>4,378</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2016</ENT>
<ENT>5</ENT>
<ENT>19</ENT>
<ENT>16</ENT>
<ENT>4,626</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2017</ENT>
<ENT>5</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>16</ENT>
<ENT>4,597</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2018</ENT>
<ENT>6</ENT>
<ENT>20</ENT>
<ENT>16</ENT>
<ENT>4,323</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2019</ENT>
<ENT>8</ENT>
<ENT>21</ENT>
<ENT>17</ENT>
<ENT>4,271</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2020</ENT>
<ENT>9</ENT>
<ENT>27</ENT>
<ENT>21</ENT>
<ENT>4,912</ENT>
</ROW>
</GPOTABLE>
<P>For purposes of this analysis, ATF estimated that Type 1 and 2 FFLs that must comply with the Act would have purchased at least two safety devices at an average price of $7.39 per safety device and tape ($2.36) to notate the owner of the gun. Combined, the average price to make available secure gun storage or safety devices for customers is $17.14 per store. For sources of costs to make available secure gun storage or safety devices, refer to section 3.1.2 of the standalone RA.</P>
<P>
For an annual direct, industry cost of certifying and making available secure gun storage or safety devices, refer to Table 8. That table provides the annual cost of certifying and making available secure gun storage or safety devices from 1999 to 2020.
<PRTPAGE P="191"/>
</P>
<GPOTABLE COLS="4" OPTS="L2,i1" CDEF="s50,15,15,15">
<TTITLE>Table 8—Year by Year Direct, Industry Cost</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">Year</CHED>
<CHED H="1">
Undiscounted
<LI>industry costs</LI>
</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Discounted cost</CHED>
<CHED H="2">7%</CHED>
<CHED H="2">3%</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">1999</ENT>
<ENT>$1,398,539</ENT>
<ENT>$6,196,088</ENT>
<ENT>$2,679,745</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2000</ENT>
<ENT>147,582</ENT>
<ENT>611,072</ENT>
<ENT>274,546</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2001</ENT>
<ENT>117,089</ENT>
<ENT>453,096</ENT>
<ENT>211,475</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2002</ENT>
<ENT>86,808</ENT>
<ENT>313,942</ENT>
<ENT>152,218</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2003</ENT>
<ENT>56,753</ENT>
<ENT>191,821</ENT>
<ENT>96,618</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2004</ENT>
<ENT>56,368</ENT>
<ENT>178,057</ENT>
<ENT>93,168</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2005</ENT>
<ENT>56,157</ENT>
<ENT>165,784</ENT>
<ENT>90,115</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2006</ENT>
<ENT>55,727</ENT>
<ENT>153,753</ENT>
<ENT>86,821</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2007</ENT>
<ENT>55,132</ENT>
<ENT>142,161</ENT>
<ENT>83,393</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2008</ENT>
<ENT>54,445</ENT>
<ENT>131,204</ENT>
<ENT>79,954</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2009</ENT>
<ENT>53,922</ENT>
<ENT>121,442</ENT>
<ENT>76,879</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2010</ENT>
<ENT>53,517</ENT>
<ENT>112,645</ENT>
<ENT>74,080</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2011</ENT>
<ENT>45,572</ENT>
<ENT>89,646</ENT>
<ENT>61,244</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2012</ENT>
<ENT>52,034</ENT>
<ENT>95,663</ENT>
<ENT>67,893</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2013</ENT>
<ENT>57,778</ENT>
<ENT>99,274</ENT>
<ENT>73,192</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2014</ENT>
<ENT>45,742</ENT>
<ENT>73,451</ENT>
<ENT>56,256</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2015</ENT>
<ENT>41,188</ENT>
<ENT>61,813</ENT>
<ENT>49,181</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2016</ENT>
<ENT>43,561</ENT>
<ENT>61,097</ENT>
<ENT>50,499</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2017</ENT>
<ENT>38,282</ENT>
<ENT>50,179</ENT>
<ENT>43,086</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2018</ENT>
<ENT>36,298</ENT>
<ENT>44,466</ENT>
<ENT>39,664</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2019</ENT>
<ENT>32,817</ENT>
<ENT>37,572</ENT>
<ENT>34,815</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW RUL="n,s">
<ENT I="01">2020</ENT>
<ENT>47,075</ENT>
<ENT>50,370</ENT>
<ENT>48,487</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW RUL="s">
<ENT I="03">Total</ENT>
<ENT>2,632,384</ENT>
<ENT>9,434,596</ENT>
<ENT>4,523,330</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="03">Annualized</ENT>
<ENT/>
<ENT>852,942</ENT>
<ENT>283,827</ENT>
</ROW>
</GPOTABLE>
<P>
In addition to direct, industry costs for Type 1 and 2 FFLs to make available secure gun storage or safety devices, the government incurred costs to enforce secure gun storage and safety device requirements on FFLs. Based on ATF's database, ATF found two violations in 2019 and six violations in 2020, making the average number of violations four. Based on input from SMEs, ATF determined that Industry Operations Investigators (“IOI”) undertaking inspections related to the secure gun storage and safety device requirement range from a GS-9 to GS-13, making the average IOI a GS-10, step 5. The hourly wage rate for a GS-10, step 5 is $27.56.
<SU>9</SU>
<FTREF/>
In order to account for fringe benefits, ATF attributed a load rate of 1.41, making the loaded, hourly wage rate for an IOI $38.86.
<SU>10</SU>
 
<SU>11</SU>
<FTREF/>
The SMEs estimated that it would take an average of 20 minutes (0.33 hours) to have a conversation with the FFL in question and compile a report or warning regarding the violation, making the government cost $26 in 2019 and $78 in 2020. Because ATF does not have any information regarding inspections for previous years, ATF used the average of four violations per year as the government cost for enforcement between the years 1999 and 2018. The average cost of enforcement was estimated to be $52.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>9</SU>
 Office of Personnel Management, SALARY TABLE 2021-GS (Jan. 2021),
<E T="03">https://www.opm.gov/policy-data-oversight/pay-leave/salaries-wages/salary-tables/pdf/2021/GS_h.pdf.</E>
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>10</SU>
 Federal benefits account for 41 percent of total compensation. Congressional Budget Office, Comparing the Compensation of Federal and Private-Sector Employees, 2011 to 2015, at 14 (Apr. 2017),
<E T="03">https://www.cbo.gov/system/files/115th-congress-2017-2018/reports/52637-federalprivatepay.pdf.</E>
</P>
<P>
<SU>11</SU>
 $38.86 loaded wage rate = $27.56 hourly wage rate * 1.41 load rate.
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>
ATF accounts for indirect costs of this rule although they are not considered part of the total cost of the rule. Other organizations, such as Project ChildSafe, provide gun locks free to the public, which ends up being a savings for the populations affected by this rule. Because these costs are voluntarily incurred, they are considered indirect costs. Based on information provided by Project ChildSafe, which primarily obtains its funding through other sources, this organization has provided approximately 38 million gun locks to the public and provides approximately 1.8 million gun lock kits annually.
<SU>12</SU>
<FTREF/>
Furthermore, Project ChildSafe estimates that manufacturers have included approximately 70 million locks with a purchase of a firearm, which they estimate is valued at $140 million.
<SU>13</SU>
<FTREF/>
These are indirect costs that ATF does not consider as part of the total costs of this final rule.
</P>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>12</SU>
 Project ChildSafe, Project ChildSafe by the Numbers,
<E T="03">https://www.projectchildsafe.org/sites/default/files/NSSF_PCS_Infographic_PCSByTheNumbers_Jan2019_0.pdf</E>
(last accessed Dec. 17, 2021).
</P>
</FTNT>
<FTNT>
<P>
<SU>13</SU>
 
<E T="03">Id.</E>
</P>
</FTNT>
<P>Other indirect costs include firearm manufacturers who voluntarily include safety devices with each purchase of a new firearm. While manufacturers are not required to provide gun locks with their firearms due to this rule, it is possible that manufacturers have incorporated the cost of these gun locks into the final purchasing price of the firearm and is therefore already accounted for. It is for these reasons that ATF does not consider these indirect costs as costs attributed to this rule.</P>
<P>
ATF accounted for the direct, industry costs of this rule along with the government enforcement costs attributed to this rule. Table 9 provides the total costs for this rule.
<PRTPAGE P="192"/>
</P>
<GPOTABLE COLS="4" OPTS="L2,i1" CDEF="s50,15,15,15">
<TTITLE>Table 9—Total Direct, Industry and Government Costs of This Rule</TTITLE>
<BOXHD>
<CHED H="1">Year</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Undiscounted total costs</CHED>
<CHED H="1">Discounted cost</CHED>
<CHED H="2">7%</CHED>
<CHED H="2">3%</CHED>
</BOXHD>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">1999</ENT>
<ENT>$1,398,590</ENT>
<ENT>$6,196,318</ENT>
<ENT>$2,679,844</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2000</ENT>
<ENT>147,634</ENT>
<ENT>611,287</ENT>
<ENT>274,642</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2001</ENT>
<ENT>117,140</ENT>
<ENT>453,296</ENT>
<ENT>211,569</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2002</ENT>
<ENT>86,859</ENT>
<ENT>314,130</ENT>
<ENT>152,309</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2003</ENT>
<ENT>56,805</ENT>
<ENT>191,996</ENT>
<ENT>96,706</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2004</ENT>
<ENT>56,420</ENT>
<ENT>178,221</ENT>
<ENT>93,254</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2005</ENT>
<ENT>56,209</ENT>
<ENT>165,937</ENT>
<ENT>90,198</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2006</ENT>
<ENT>55,779</ENT>
<ENT>153,896</ENT>
<ENT>86,902</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2007</ENT>
<ENT>55,184</ENT>
<ENT>142,294</ENT>
<ENT>83,471</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2008</ENT>
<ENT>54,497</ENT>
<ENT>131,329</ENT>
<ENT>80,030</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2009</ENT>
<ENT>53,973</ENT>
<ENT>121,558</ENT>
<ENT>76,953</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2010</ENT>
<ENT>53,569</ENT>
<ENT>112,754</ENT>
<ENT>74,152</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2011</ENT>
<ENT>45,623</ENT>
<ENT>89,748</ENT>
<ENT>61,314</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2012</ENT>
<ENT>52,086</ENT>
<ENT>95,758</ENT>
<ENT>67,960</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2013</ENT>
<ENT>57,830</ENT>
<ENT>99,363</ENT>
<ENT>73,257</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2014</ENT>
<ENT>45,793</ENT>
<ENT>73,534</ENT>
<ENT>56,320</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2015</ENT>
<ENT>41,240</ENT>
<ENT>61,890</ENT>
<ENT>49,243</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2016</ENT>
<ENT>43,613</ENT>
<ENT>61,170</ENT>
<ENT>50,559</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2017</ENT>
<ENT>38,333</ENT>
<ENT>50,247</ENT>
<ENT>43,145</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2018</ENT>
<ENT>36,350</ENT>
<ENT>44,530</ENT>
<ENT>39,720</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="01">2019</ENT>
<ENT>32,843</ENT>
<ENT>37,602</ENT>
<ENT>34,843</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW RUL="n,s">
<ENT I="01">2020</ENT>
<ENT>47,153</ENT>
<ENT>50,454</ENT>
<ENT>48,567</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW RUL="s">
<ENT I="03">Total</ENT>
<ENT>2,633,524</ENT>
<ENT>9,437,311</ENT>
<ENT>4,524,959</ENT>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<ENT I="03">Annualized</ENT>
<ENT/>
<ENT>853,187</ENT>
<ENT>283,929</ENT>
</ROW>
</GPOTABLE>
<P>Overall, ATF estimated that, in accordance with the standards for regulatory analysis described in OMB Circular A-4, the total cost attributable to this rule from 1999 to 2020 was $2.6 million undiscounted, or annualized at $853,187 and $283,929 at 7 percent and 3 percent, respectively.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD3">4. Benefits</HD>
<P>The benefit of this rule is making available secure gun storage or safety devices for owners of firearms who otherwise do not have such storage or safety devices available to them. Making secure gun storage or safety devices available inhibits unauthorized access to privately owned firearms for individuals such as children, who might accidently discharge them, and inhibits access by criminals, who might use them for illicit activities.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">B. Executive Order 13132</HD>
<P>This rule will not have substantial direct effects on the States, on the relationship between the Federal Government and the States, or on the distribution of power and responsibilities among the various levels of government. Therefore, in accordance with section 6 of Executive Order 13132 (Federalism), the Attorney General has determined that this rule does not have sufficient federalism implications to warrant the preparation of a federalism summary impact statement.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">C. Executive Order 12988</HD>
<P>This rule meets the applicable standards set forth in sections 3(a) and 3(b)(2) of Executive Order 12988 (Civil Justice Reform).</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">D. Regulatory Flexibility Act</HD>
<P>Under the Regulatory Flexibility Act, 5 U.S.C. 601-12, the Attorney General certifies that this final rule will not have a significant economic impact on a substantial number of small entities. The Department has considered whether this final rule would have a significant economic impact on a substantial number of small entities. The term “small entities” comprises small businesses, not-for-profit organizations that are independently owned and operated and are not dominant in their fields, and governmental jurisdictions with populations of fewer than 50,000.</P>
<P>ATF has determined that, in order for the costs associated with this rule to impact a small entity's revenue by even one percent, the entity would need to make $1,728 or less in annual revenue. For the costs to have a 10 percent effect on revenue, a small entity would need to make $173 or less in revenue. ATF has determined that it is unlikely that a small entity would make such minimal amounts in revenue and continue to operate. Therefore, the Attorney General certifies under 5 U.S.C. 605(b) that this final rule would not have a significant economic impact on a substantial number of small entities.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">E. Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995</HD>
<P>This rule will not result in the aggregate expenditure by State, local, and Tribal governments, or by the private sector, of $100 million or more in any one year, and it will not significantly or uniquely affect small governments. Therefore, no actions are necessary under the provisions of the Unfunded Mandates Reform Act of 1995.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">F. Paperwork Reduction Act</HD>
<P>Under the Paperwork Reduction Act of 1995 (“PRA”), 44 U.S.C. 3501-21, agencies are required to submit for OMB review and approval any reporting requirements inherent in a rule. The collection of information contained in this final rule is a collection of information that has been reviewed and approved by OMB in accordance with the requirements of the PRA, and it has been assigned an OMB Control Number.</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Title:</E>
Application for Federal Firearms License—ATF Form 7 (5310.12)/7CR (5310.16).
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">OMB Control Number:</E>
1140-0018.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Summary of the Collection of Information:</E>
This collection of information is used by the public when applying for a Federal firearms license
<PRTPAGE P="193"/>
(“FFL”); this form is used to apply for all FFL types.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Need for Information:</E>
The information requested on the form is used to determine the eligibility of the applicant to obtain an FFL, and the identity and eligibility of Responsible Persons.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Proposed Use of Information:</E>
The information contained will be used to determine the applicant's eligibility to receive a license.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Description of the Respondents:</E>
All Federal firearms licensees.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Number of Respondents:</E>
47,088.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Frequency of Response:</E>
Once every 3 years.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Burden of Response:</E>
For this rule, 0.0017 hours. Total 1 hour.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Estimate of Total Annual Burden:</E>
For this rule, 80 hours. Total burden 47,088 hours.
</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD2">G. Congressional Review Act</HD>
<P>Pursuant to the Congressional Review Act, 5 U.S.C. 801-08, OMB's Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs designated this rule as not a “major rule,” as defined by 5 U.S.C. 804(2). This rule will not result in an annual effect on the economy of $100 million or more; a major increase in costs or prices; or a significant adverse effect on competition, employment, investment, productivity, innovation, or on the ability of United States-based enterprises to compete with foreign-based enterprises in domestic and export markets.</P>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">Disclosure</HD>
<P>
Copies of this rule and the comments received in response to the proposed rule will be available for public inspection through the Federal eRulemaking portal,
<E T="03">www.regulations.gov</E>
(search for RIN 1140-AA10), or by appointment during normal business hours at the ATF Reading Room, Room 1E-062, 99 New York Avenue NE, Washington, DC 20226; telephone: (202) 648-8740.
</P>
<LSTSUB>
<HD SOURCE="HED">List of Subjects in 27 CFR Part 478</HD>
<P>Administrative practice and procedure, Arms and munitions, Exports, Freight, Imports, Intergovernmental relations, Law enforcement officers, Military personnel, Penalties, Reporting and recordkeeping requirements, Research, Seizures and forfeitures, Transportation.</P>
</LSTSUB>
<HD SOURCE="HD1">Authority and Issuance</HD>
<P>Accordingly, for the reasons discussed in the preamble, 27 CFR part 478 is amended as follows:</P>
<PART>
<HD SOURCE="HED">PART 478—COMMERCE IN FIREARMS AND AMMUNITION</HD>
</PART>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>1. The authority citation for part 478 is revised to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<AUTH>
<HD SOURCE="HED">Authority: </HD>
<P> 5 U.S.C. 552(a); 18 U.S.C. 847, 921-931; 44 U.S.C. 3504(h).</P>
</AUTH>
</REGTEXT>
<SECTION>
    <SECTNO>§ 478.11 </SECTNO>
    <SUBJECT> [Amended]</SUBJECT>
</SECTION>
<REGTEXT PART="478" TITLE="27">
    <AMDPAR>2. Section 478.11 is revised to read</AMDPAR>
    <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 478.11</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Meaning of terms.</SUBJECT>
        <P>When used in this part and in forms prescribed under this part, where not otherwise distinctly expressed or manifestly incompatible with the intent thereof, terms shall have the meanings ascribed in this section. Words in the plural form shall include the singular, and vice versa, and words importing the masculine gender shall include the feminine. The terms “includes” and “including” do not exclude other things not enumerated which are in the same general class or are otherwise within the scope thereof.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Act.</E> 18 U.S.C. Chapter 44.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Adjudicated as a mental defective.</E> (a) A determination by a court, board, commission, or other lawful authority that a person, as a result of marked subnormal intelligence, or mental illness, incompetency, condition, or disease:</P>
        <P>(1) Is a danger to himself or to others; or</P>
        <P>(2) Lacks the mental capacity to contract or manage his own affairs.</P>
        <P>(b) The term shall include—</P>
        <P>(1) A finding of insanity by a court in a criminal case; and</P>

        <P>(2) Those persons found incompetent to stand trial or found not guilty by reason of lack of mental responsibility pursuant to articles 50a and 72b of the <PRTPAGE P="21"/>Uniform Code of Military Justice, 10 U.S.C. 850a, 876b.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Admitted to the United States for lawful hunting or sporting purposes.</E> (a) Is entering the United States to participate in a competitive target shooting event sponsored by a national, State, or local organization, devoted to the competitive use or other sporting use of firearms; or</P>
        <P>(b) Is entering the United States to display firearms at a sports or hunting trade show sponsored by a national, State, or local firearms trade organization, devoted to the competitive use or other sporting use of firearms.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Alien.</E> Any person not a citizen or national of the United States.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Alien illegally or unlawfully in the United States.</E> Aliens who are unlawfully in the United States are not in valid immigrant, nonimmigrant or parole status. The term includes any alien—</P>
        <P>(a) Who unlawfully entered the United States without inspection and authorization by an immigration officer and who has not been paroled into the United States under section 212(d)(5) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (INA);</P>
        <P>(b) Who is a nonimmigrant and whose authorized period of stay has expired or who has violated the terms of the nonimmigrant category in which he or she was admitted;</P>
        <P>(c) Paroled under INA section 212(d)(5) whose authorized period of parole has expired or whose parole status has been terminated; or</P>
        <P>(d) Under an order of deportation, exclusion, or removal, or under an order to depart the United States voluntarily, whether or not he or she has left the United States.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Ammunition.</E> Ammunition or cartridge cases, primers, bullets, or propellent powder designed for use in any firearm other than an antique firearm. The term shall not include (a) any shotgun shot or pellet not designed for use as the single, complete projectile load for one shotgun hull or casing, nor (b) any unloaded, non-metallic shotgun hull or casing not having a primer.</P>
        <P>
            <E T="03">Antique firearm.</E>
            (1) Any firearm (including any firearm with a matchlock, flintlock, percussion cap, or similar type of ignition system) manufactured in or before 1898;
            </P>
            <P>(2) Any replica of any firearm described in paragraph (a) of this definition if such replica:</P>
            <P>(i) Is not designed or redesigned for using rimfire or conventional centerfire fixed ammunition; or</P>
            <P>(ii) Uses rimfire or conventional centerfire fixed ammunition that is no longer manufactured in the United States and that is not readily available in the ordinary channels of commercial trade; or</P>
            <P>(3) Any muzzle loading rifle, muzzle loading shotgun, or muzzle loading pistol that is designed to use black powder, or a black powder substitute, and that cannot use fixed ammunition. For purposes of this paragraph (3), the term “antique firearm” does not include any weapon that incorporates a firearm frame or receiver, any firearm that is converted into a muzzle loading weapon, or any muzzle loading weapon that can be readily converted to fire fixed ammunition by replacing the barrel, bolt, breechblock, or any combination thereof.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Armor piercing ammunition.</E> Projectiles or projectile cores which may be used in a handgun and which are constructed entirely (excluding the presence of traces of other substances) from one or a combination of tungsten alloys, steel, iron, brass, bronze, beryllium copper, or depleted uranium; or full jacketed projectiles larger than .22 caliber designed and intended for use in a handgun and whose jacket has a weight of more than 25 percent of the total weight of the projectile. The term does not include shotgun shot required by Federal or State environmental or game regulations for hunting purposes, frangible projectiles designed for target shooting, projectiles which the Director finds are primarily intended to be used for sporting purposes, or any other projectiles or projectile cores which the Director finds are intended to be used for industrial purposes, including charges used in oil and gas well perforating devices.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">ATF officer.</E> An officer or employee of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF) authorized to perform any function relating to the administration or enforcement of this part.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Business premises.</E> The property on which the manufacturing or importing of firearms or ammunition or the dealing in firearms is or will be conducted. A private dwelling, no part of which is open to the public, shall not be recognized as coming within the meaning of the term.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Chief, Federal Firearms Licensing Center (FFLC).</E> The ATF official responsible for the issuance and renewal of licenses under this part.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Collector.</E> Any person who acquires, holds, or disposes of firearms as curios or relics.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Collection premises.</E> The premises described on the license of a collector as <PRTPAGE P="22"/>the location at which he maintains his collection of curios and relics.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Commerce.</E> Travel, trade, traffic, commerce, transportation, or communication among the several States, or between the District of Columbia and any State, or between any foreign country or any territory or possession and any State or the District of Columbia, or between points in the same State but through any other State or the District of Columbia or a foreign country.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Committed to a mental institution.</E> A formal commitment of a person to a mental institution by a court, board, commission, or other lawful authority. The term includes a commitment to a mental institution involuntarily. The term includes commitment for mental defectiveness or mental illness. It also includes commitments for other reasons, such as for drug use. The term does not include a person in a mental institution for observation or a voluntary admission to a mental institution.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Controlled substance.</E> A drug or other substance, or immediate precursor, as defined in section 102 of the Controlled Substances Act, 21 U.S.C. 802. The term includes, but is not limited to, marijuana, depressants, stimulants, and narcotic drugs. The term does not include distilled spirits, wine, malt beverages, or tobacco, as those terms are defined or used in Subtitle E of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, as amended.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Crime punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year.</E> Any Federal, State or foreign offense for which the maximum penalty, whether or not imposed, is capital punishment or imprisonment in excess of 1 year. The term shall not include (a) any Federal or State offenses pertaining to antitrust violations, unfair trade practices, restraints of trade, or other similar offenses relating to the regulation of business practices or (b) any State offense classified by the laws of the State as a misdemeanor and punishable by a term of imprisonment of 2 years or less. What constitutes a conviction of such a crime shall be determined in accordance with the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held. Any conviction which has been expunged or set aside or for which a person has been pardoned or has had civil rights restored shall not be considered a conviction for the purposes of the Act or this part, unless such pardon, expunction, or restoration of civil rights expressly provides that the person may not ship, transport, possess, or receive firearms, or unless the person is prohibited by the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held from receiving or possessing any firearms.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Curios or relics.</E> Firearms which are of special interest to collectors by reason of some quality other than is associated with firearms intended for sporting use or as offensive or defensive weapons. To be recognized as curios or relics, firearms must fall within one of the following categories:</P>
        <P>(a) Firearms which were manufactured at least 50 years prior to the current date, but not including replicas thereof;</P>
        <P>(b) Firearms which are certified by the curator of a municipal, State, or Federal museum which exhibits firearms to be curios or relics of museum interest; and</P>
        <P>(c) Any other firearms which derive a substantial part of their monetary value from the fact that they are novel, rare, bizarre, or because of their association with some historical figure, period, or event. Proof of qualification of a particular firearm under this category may be established by evidence of present value and evidence that like firearms are not available except as collector's items, or that the value of like firearms available in ordinary commercial channels is substantially less.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Customs officer.</E> Any officer of U.S. Customs and Border Protection, any commissioned, warrant, or petty officer of the Coast Guard, or any agent or other person authorized by law to perform the duties of a customs officer.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Dealer.</E> Any person engaged in the business of selling firearms at wholesale or retail; any person engaged in the business of repairing firearms or of making or fitting special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms; or any person who is a pawnbroker. The term shall include any person who engages in such business or occupation on a part-time basis.<PRTPAGE P="23"/>
        </P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Destructive device.</E> (a) Any explosive, incendiary, or poison gas (1) bomb, (2) grenade, (3) rocket having a propellant charge of more than 4 ounces, (4) missile having an explosive or incendiary charge of more than one-quarter ounce, (5) mine, or (6) device similar to any of the devices described in the preceding paragraphs of this definition; (b) any type of weapon (other than a shotgun or a shotgun shell which the Director finds is generally recognized as particularly suitable for sporting purposes) by whatever name known which will, or which may be readily converted to, expel a projectile by the action of an explosive or other propellant, and which has any barrel with a bore of more than one-half inch in diameter; and (c) any combination of parts either designed or intended for use in converting any device into any destructive device described in paragraph (a) or (b) of this section and from which a destructive device may be readily assembled. The term shall not include any device which is neither designed nor redesigned for use as a weapon; any device, although originally designed for use as a weapon, which is redesigned for use as a signalling, pyrotechnic, line throwing, safety, or similar device; surplus ordnance sold, loaned, or given by the Secretary of the Army pursuant to the provisions of section 4684(2), 4685, or 4686 of title 10, United States Code; or any other device which the Director finds is not likely to be used as a weapon, is an antique, or is a rifle which the owner intends to use solely for sporting, recreational, or cultural purposes.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Director.</E> The Director, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, the Department of Justice, Washington, DC.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Director of Industry Operations.</E> The principal ATF official in a Field Operations division responsible for administering regulations in this part.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Discharged under dishonorable conditions.</E> Separation from the U.S. Armed Forces resulting from a dishonorable discharge or dismissal adjudged by a general court-martial. The term does not include any separation from the Armed Forces resulting from any other discharge, e.g., a bad conduct discharge.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Division.</E> A Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives Division.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Engaged in the business</E>—(a) <E T="03">Manufacturer of firearms.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to manufacturing firearms as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the firearms manufactured;</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Manufacturer of ammunition.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to manufacturing ammunition as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the ammunition manufactured;</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or a pawnbroker.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to dealing in firearms as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the repetitive purchase and resale of firearms, but such a term shall not include a person who makes occasional sales, exchanges, or purchases of firearms for the enhancement of a personal collection or for a hobby, or who sells all or part of his personal collection of firearms;</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Gunsmith.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to engaging in such activity as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit, but such a term shall not include a person who makes occasional repairs of firearms or who occasionally fits special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms;</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Importer of firearms.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to importing firearms as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the firearms imported; and,</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Importer of ammunition.</E> A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to importing ammunition as a regular course of trade or business with the principal objective of livelihood and profit through the sale or distribution of the ammunition imported.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Executed under penalties of perjury.</E> Signed with the prescribed declaration <PRTPAGE P="24"/>under the penalties of perjury as provided on or with respect to the return form, or other document or, where no form of declaration is prescribed, with the declaration:
        </P>
        <EXTRACT>
          <P>“I declare under the penalties of perjury that this—(insert type of document, such as, statement, application, request, certificate), including the documents submitted in support thereof, has been examined by me and, to the best of my knowledge and belief, is true, correct, and complete.”</P>
        </EXTRACT>
        
        <P>
          <E T="03">Federal Firearms Act.</E> 15 U.S.C. Chapter 18.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Firearm.</E> Any weapon, including a starter gun, which will or is designed to or may readily be converted to expel a projectile by the action of an explosive; the frame or receiver of any such weapon; any firearm muffler or firearm silencer; or any destructive device; but the term shall not include an antique firearm. In the case of a licensed collector, the term shall mean only curios and relics.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Firearm frame or receiver.</E> That part of a firearm which provides housing for the hammer, bolt or breechblock, and firing mechanism, and which is usually threaded at its forward portion to receive the barrel.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Firearm muffler or firearm silencer.</E> Any device for silencing, muffling, or diminishing the report of a portable firearm, including any combination of parts, designed or redesigned, and intended for use in assembling or fabricating a firearm silencer or firearm muffler, and any part intended only for use in such assembly or fabrication.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Friendly foreign government.</E> Any government with whom the United States has diplomatic relations and whom the United States has not identified as a State sponsor of terrorism.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Fugitive from justice.</E> Any person who has fled from any State to avoid prosecution for a felony or a misdemeanor; or any person who leaves the State to avoid giving testimony in any criminal proceeding. The term also includes any person who knows that misdemeanor or felony charges are pending against such person and who leaves the State of prosecution.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Handgun.</E> (a) Any firearm which has a short stock and is designed to be held and fired by the use of a single hand; and</P>
        <P>(b) Any combination of parts from which a firearm described in paragraph (a) can be assembled.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Hunting license or permit lawfully issued in the United States.</E> A license or permit issued by a State for hunting which is valid and unexpired.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Identification document.</E> A document containing the name, residence address, date of birth, and photograph of the holder and which was made or issued by or under the authority of the United States Government, a State, political subdivision of a State, a foreign government, political subdivision of a foreign government, an international governmental or an international quasi- governmental organization which, when completed with information concerning a particular individual, is of a type intended or commonly accepted for the purpose of identification of individuals.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Importation.</E> The bringing of a firearm or ammunition into the United States; except that the bringing of a firearm or ammunition from outside the United States into a foreign-trade zone for storage pending shipment to a foreign country or subsequent importation into this country, pursuant to this part, shall not be deemed importation.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Importer.</E> Any person engaged in the business of importing or bringing firearms or ammunition into the United States. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Indictment.</E> Includes an indictment or information in any court, under which a crime punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year (as defined in this section) may be prosecuted, or in military cases to any offense punishable by imprisonment for a term exceeding 1 year which has been referred to a general court-martial. An information is a formal accusation of a crime, differing from an indictment in that it is made by a prosecuting attorney and not a grand jury.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Interstate or foreign commerce.</E> Includes commerce between any place in a State and any place outside of that State, or within any possession of the United States (not including the Canal Zone) or the District of Columbia. The term shall not include commerce between places within the same State but <PRTPAGE P="25"/>through any place outside of that State.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Intimate partner.</E> With respect to a person, the spouse of the person, a former spouse of the person, an individual who is a parent of a child of the person, and an individual who cohabitates or has cohabitated with the person.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Large capacity ammunition feeding device.</E> A magazine, belt, drum, feed strip, or similar device for a firearm manufactured after September 13, 1994, that has a capacity of, or that can be readily restored or converted to accept, more than 10 rounds of ammunition. The term does not include an attached tubular device designed to accept, and capable of operating only with, .22 caliber rimfire ammunition, or a fixed device for a manually operated firearm, or a fixed device for a firearm listed in 18 U.S.C. 922, appendix A.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Licensed collector.</E> A collector of curios and relics only and licensed under the provisions of this part.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Licensed dealer.</E> A dealer licensed under the provisions of this part.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Licensed importer.</E> An importer licensed under the provisions of this part.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Licensed manufacturer.</E> A manufacturer licensed under the provisions of this part.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Machine gun.</E> Any weapon which shoots, is designed to shoot, or can be readily restored to shoot, automatically more than one shot, without manual reloading, by a single function of the trigger. The term shall also include the frame or receiver of any such weapon, any part designed and intended solely and exclusively, or combination of parts designed and intended, for use in converting a weapon into a machine gun, and any combination of parts from which a machine gun can be assembled if such parts are in the possession or under the control of a person.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Manufacturer.</E> Any person engaged in the business of manufacturing firearms or ammunition. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Mental institution.</E> Includes mental health facilities, mental hospitals, sanitariums, psychiatric facilities, and other facilities that provide diagnoses by licensed professionals of mental retardation or mental illness, including a psychiatric ward in a general hospital.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Misdemeanor crime of domestic violence.</E> (a) Is a Federal, State or local offense that:</P>
        <P>(1) Is a misdemeanor under Federal or State law or, in States which do not classify offenses as misdemeanors, is an offense punishable by imprisonment for a term of one year or less, and includes offenses that are punishable only by a fine. (This is true whether or not the State statute specifically defines the offense as a “misdemeanor” or as a “misdemeanor crime of domestic violence.” The term includes all such misdemeanor convictions in Indian Courts established pursuant to 25 CFR part 11.);</P>
        <P>(2) Has, as an element, the use or attempted use of physical force (e.g., assault and battery), or the threatened use of a deadly weapon; and</P>
        <P>(3) Was committed by a current or former spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim, by a person with whom the victim shares a child in common, by a person who is cohabiting with or has cohabited with the victim as a spouse, parent, or guardian, (e.g., the equivalent of a “common law” marriage even if such relationship is not recognized under the law), or a person similarly situated to a spouse, parent, or guardian of the victim (e.g., two persons who are residing at the same location in an intimate relationship with the intent to make that place their home would be similarly situated to a spouse).</P>
        <P>(b) A person shall not be considered to have been convicted of such an offense for purposes of this part unless:</P>
        <P>(1) The person is considered to have been convicted by the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held.</P>
        <P>(2) The person was represented by counsel in the case, or knowingly and intelligently waived the right to counsel in the case; and</P>
        <P>(3) In the case of a prosecution for which a person was entitled to a jury trial in the jurisdiction in which the case was tried, either</P>
        <P>(i) The case was tried by a jury, or</P>

        <P>(ii) The person knowingly and intelligently waived the right to have the case tried by a jury, by guilty plea or otherwise.<PRTPAGE P="26"/>
        </P>
        <P>(c) A person shall not be considered to have been convicted of such an offense for purposes of this part if the conviction has been expunged or set aside, or is an offense for which the person has been pardoned or has had civil rights restored (if the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held provides for the loss of civil rights upon conviction for such an offense) unless the pardon, expunction, or restoration of civil rights expressly provides that the person may not ship, transport, possess, or receive firearms, and the person is not otherwise prohibited by the law of the jurisdiction in which the proceedings were held from receiving or possessing any firearms.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">National Firearms Act.</E> 26 U.S.C. Chapter 53.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">NICS.</E> The National Instant Criminal Background Check System established by the Attorney General pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 922(t).</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Nonimmigrant alien.</E> An alien in the United States in a nonimmigrant classification as defined by section 101(a)(15) of the Immigration and Nationality Act (8 U.S.C. 1101(a)(15)).</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Nonimmigrant visa.</E> A visa properly issued to an alien as an eligible nonimmigrant by a competent officer as provided in the Immigration and Nationality Act, 8 U.S.C. 1101 <E T="03">et seq.</E>
        </P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Pawnbroker.</E> Any person whose business or occupation includes the taking or receiving, by way of pledge or pawn, of any firearm as security for the payment or repayment of money. The term shall include any person who engages in such business on a part-time basis.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Permanently inoperable.</E> A firearm which is incapable of discharging a shot by means of an explosive and incapable of being readily restored to a firing condition. An acceptable method of rendering most firearms permanently inoperable is to fusion weld the chamber closed and fusion weld the barrel solidly to the frame. Certain unusual firearms require other methods to render the firearm permanently inoperable. Contact ATF for instructions.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Person.</E> Any individual, corporation, company, association, firm, partnership, society, or joint stock company.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Pistol.</E> A weapon originally designed, made, and intended to fire a projectile (bullet) from one or more barrels when held in one hand, and having (a) a chamber(s) as an integral part(s) of, or permanently aligned with, the bore(s); and (b) a short stock designed to be gripped by one hand and at an angle to and extending below the line of the bore(s).</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Principal objective of livelihood and profit.</E> The intent underlying the sale or disposition of firearms is predominantly one of obtaining livelihood and pecuniary gain, as opposed to other intents such as improving or liquidating a personal firearms collection: <E T="03">Provided,</E> That proof of profit shall not be required as to a person who engages in the regular and repetitive purchase and disposition of firearms for criminal purposes or terrorism. For purposes of this part, the term “terrorism” means activity, directed against United States persons, which—</P>
        <P>(a) Is committed by an individual who is not a national or permanent resident alien of the United States;</P>
        <P>(b) Involves violent acts or acts dangerous to human life which would be a criminal violation if committed within the jurisdiction of the United States; and</P>
        <P>(c) Is intended—</P>
        <P>(1) To intimidate or coerce a civilian population;</P>
        <P>(2) To influence the policy of a government by intimidation or coercion; or</P>
        <P>(3) To affect the conduct of a government by assassination or kidnapping.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Published ordinance.</E> A published law of any political subdivision of a State which the Director determines to be relevant to the enforcement of this part and which is contained on a list compiled by the Director, which list is incorporated by reference in the <E T="04">Federal Register,</E> revised annually, and furnished to licensees under this part.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Renounced U.S. citizenship.</E> (a) A person has renounced his U.S. citizenship if the person, having been a citizen of the United States, has renounced citizenship either—</P>
        <P>(1) Before a diplomatic or consular officer of the United States in a foreign state pursuant to 8 U.S.C. 1481(a)(5); or</P>

        <P>(2) Before an officer designated by the Attorney General when the United <PRTPAGE P="27"/>States is in a state of war pursuant to 8 U.S.C. 1481(a)(6).</P>
        <P>(b) The term shall not include any renunciation of citizenship that has been reversed as a result of administrative or judicial appeal.</P>
        
        <P>
          <E T="03">Revolver.</E> A projectile weapon, of the pistol type, having a breechloading chambered cylinder so arranged that the cocking of the hammer or movement of the trigger rotates it and brings the next cartridge in line with the barrel for firing.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Rifle.</E> A weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder, and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of an explosive to fire only a single projectile through a rifled bore for each single pull of the trigger.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Secure gun storage or safety device.</E>
          (1) A device that, when installed on a firearm, is designed to prevent the firearm from being operated without first deactivating the device;
          </P>
          <P>(2) A device incorporated into the design of the firearm that is designed to prevent the operation of the firearm by anyone not having access to the device; or</P>
          <P>(3) A safe, gun safe, gun case, lock box, or other device that is designed to be or can be used to store a firearm and that is designed to be unlocked only by means of a key, a combination, or other similar means.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Semiautomatic assault weapon.</E> (a) Any of the firearms, or copies or duplicates of the firearms in any caliber, known as:</P>
        <P>(1) Norinco, Mitchell, and Poly Technologies Avtomat Kalashnikovs (all models),</P>
        <P>(2) Action Arms Israeli Military Industries UZI and Galil,</P>
        <P>(3) Beretta Ar70 (SC-70),</P>
        <P>(4) Colt AR-15,</P>
        <P>(5) Fabrique National FN/FAL, FN/LAR, and FNC,</P>
        <P>(6) SWD M-10, M-11, M-11/9, and M-12,</P>
        <P>(7) Steyr AUG,</P>
        <P>(8) INTRATEC TEC-9, TEC-DC9 and TEC-22, and</P>
        <P>(9) Revolving cylinder shotguns, such as (or similar to) the Street Sweeper and Striker 12;</P>
        <P>(b) A semiautomatic rifle that has an ability to accept a detachable magazine and has at least 2 of—</P>
        <P>(1) A folding or telescoping stock,</P>
        <P>(2) A pistol grip that protrudes conspicuously beneath the action of the weapon,</P>
        <P>(3) A bayonet mount,</P>
        <P>(4) A flash suppressor or threaded barrel designed to accommodate a flash suppressor, and</P>
        <P>(5) A grenade launcher;</P>
        <P>(c) A semiautomatic pistol that has an ability to accept a detachable magazine and has at least 2 of—</P>
        <P>(1) An ammunition magazine that attaches to the pistol outside of the pistol grip,</P>
        <P>(2) A threaded barrel capable of accepting a barrel extender, flash suppressor, forward handgrip, or silencer,</P>
        <P>(3) A shroud that is attached to, or partially or completely encircles, the barrel and that permits the shooter to hold the firearm with the nontrigger hand without being burned,</P>
        <P>(4) A manufactured weight of 50 ounces or more when the pistol is unloaded, and</P>
        <P>(5) A semiautomatic version of an automatic firearm; and</P>
        <P>(d) A semiautomatic shotgun that has at least 2 of—</P>
        <P>(1) A folding or telescoping stock,</P>
        <P>(2) A pistol grip that protrudes conspicuously beneath the action of the weapon,</P>
        <P>(3) A fixed magazine capacity in excess of 5 rounds, and</P>
        <P>(4) An ability to accept a detachable magazine.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Semiautomatic pistol.</E> Any repeating pistol which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Semiautomatic rifle.</E> Any repeating rifle which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Semiautomatic shotgun.</E> Any repeating shotgun which utilizes a portion of the energy of a firing cartridge to extract the fired cartridge case and chamber the next round, and which requires a separate pull of the trigger to fire each cartridge.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Short-barreled rifle.</E> A rifle having one or more barrels less than 16 inches in length, and any weapon made from a rifle, whether by alteration, modification, or otherwise, if such weapon, as modified, has an overall length of less than 26 inches.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Short-barreled shotgun.</E> A shotgun having one or more barrels less than 18 inches in length, and any weapon made from a shotgun, whether by alteration, modification, or otherwise, if such weapon as modified has an overall length of less than 26 inches.<PRTPAGE P="28"/>
        </P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Shotgun.</E> A weapon designed or redesigned, made or remade, and intended to be fired from the shoulder, and designed or redesigned and made or remade to use the energy of the explosive in a fixed shotgun shell to fire through a smooth bore either a number of ball shot or a single projectile for each single pull of the trigger.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">State.</E> A State of the United States. The term shall include the District of Columbia, the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and the possessions of the United States (not including the Canal Zone).</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">State of residence.</E> The State in which an individual resides. An individual resides in a State if he or she is present in a State with the intention of making a home in that State. If an individual is on active duty as a member of the Armed Forces, the individual's State of residence is the State in which his or her permanent duty station is located, as stated in 18 U.S.C. 921(b). The following are examples that illustrate this definition:
        </P>
        <EXAMPLE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 1.</HD>
          <P>A maintains a home in State X. A travels to State Y on a hunting, fishing, business, or other type of trip. A does not become a resident of State Y by reason of such trip.</P>
        </EXAMPLE>
        <EXAMPLE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 2.</HD>
          <P>A maintains a home in State X and a home in State Y. A resides in State X except for weekends or the summer months of the year and in State Y for the weekends or the summer months of the year. During the time that A actually resides in State X, A is a resident of State X, and during the time that A actually resides in State Y, A is a resident of State Y.</P>
        </EXAMPLE>
        <EXAMPLE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 3.</HD>
          <P>A, an alien, travels to the United States on a three-week vacation to State X. A does not have a state of residence in State X because A does not have the intention of making a home in State X while on vacation. This is true regardless of the length of the vacation.</P>
        </EXAMPLE>
        <EXAMPLE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Example 4.</HD>
          <P>A, an alien, travels to the United States to work for three years in State X. A rents a home in State X, moves his personal possessions into the home, and his family resides with him in the home. A intends to reside in State X during the 3-year period of his employment. A is a resident of State X.</P>
        </EXAMPLE>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Unlawful user of or addicted to any controlled substance.</E> A person who uses a controlled substance and has lost the power of self-control with reference to the use of controlled substance; and any person who is a current user of a controlled substance in a manner other than as prescribed by a licensed physician. Such use is not limited to the use of drugs on a particular day, or within a matter of days or weeks before, but rather that the unlawful use has occurred recently enough to indicate that the individual is actively engaged in such conduct. A person may be an unlawful current user of a controlled substance even though the substance is not being used at the precise time the person seeks to acquire a firearm or receives or possesses a firearm. An inference of current use may be drawn from evidence of a recent use or possession of a controlled substance or a pattern of use or possession that reasonably covers the present time, e.g., a conviction for use or possession of a controlled substance within the past year; multiple arrests for such offenses within the past 5 years if the most recent arrest occurred within the past year; or persons found through a drug test to use a controlled substance unlawfully, provided that the test was administered within the past year. For a current or former member of the Armed Forces, an inference of current use may be drawn from recent disciplinary or other administrative action based on confirmed drug use, e.g., court-martial conviction, nonjudicial punishment, or an administrative discharge based on drug use or drug rehabilitation failure.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">Unserviceable firearm.</E> A firearm which is incapable of discharging a shot by means of an explosive and is incapable of being readily restored to a firing condition.</P>
        <P>
          <E T="03">U.S.C.</E> The United States Code.</P>
        <SECAUTH>(5 U.S.C. 552(a), 80 Stat. 383, as amended; 18 U.S.C. 847 (84 Stat. 959); 18 U.S.C. 926 (82 Stat. 1226))</SECAUTH>
        <CITA>[T.D. ATF-48, 43 FR 13536, Mar. 31, 1978; 44 FR 55842, Sept. 28, 1979]</CITA>
        <EDNOTE>
          <HD SOURCE="HED">Editorial Note:</HD>
          <P>For <E T="04">Federal Register</E> citations affecting § 478.11, see the List of CFR Sections Affected, which appears in the Finding Aids section of the printed volume and at <E T="03">www.fdsys.gov.</E>
          </P>
        </EDNOTE>
    </SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<SECTION>
    <SECTNO>§ 478.73 </SECTNO>
    <SUBJECT> [Amended]</SUBJECT>
</SECTION>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>3. Section 478.73 is revised to read</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
    <SECTNO>§ 478.73</SECTNO>
    <SUBJECT>Notice of revocation, suspension, or imposition of civil fine.</SUBJECT>
    <P>(a) <E T="03">Basis for action.</E> Whenever the Director has reason to believe that a licensee has willfully violated any provision of the Act or this part, a notice of revocation of the license, ATF Form <PRTPAGE P="47"/>4500, may be issued. In addition, a notice of revocation of the license, on ATF Form 4500, may be issued whenever the Director has reason to believe that a licensee fails to have secure gun storage or safety devices available at any place in which firearms are sold under the license to persons who are not licensees (except in any case in which a secure gun storage or safety device is temporarily unavailable because of theft, casualty loss, consumer sales, backorders from a manufacturer, or any other similar reason beyond the control of the licensee). In addition, pursuant to 18 U.S.C. 922(t)(5) and 18 U.S.C. 924(p), a notice of revocation, suspension, or imposition of a civil fine may be issued on ATF Form 4500 whenever the Director has reason to believe that a licensee has knowingly transferred a firearm to an unlicensed person and knowingly failed to comply with the requirements of 18 U.S.C. 922(t)(1) with respect to the transfer and, at the time that the transferee most recently proposed the transfer, the national instant criminal background check system was operating and information was available to the system demonstrating that the transferee's receipt of a firearm would violate 18 U.S.C. 922(g) or 922(n) or State law; or that a licensee has violated 18 U.S.C. 922(z)(1) by selling, delivering, or transferring any handgun to any person other than a licensee, unless the transferee was provided with a secure gun storage or safety device for that handgun.</P>
    <P>(b) <E T="03">Issuance of notice.</E> The notice shall set forth the matters of fact constituting the violations specified, dates, places, and the sections of law and regulations violated. The Director shall afford the licensee 15 days from the date of receipt of the notice in which to request a hearing prior to suspension or revocation of the license, or imposition of a civil fine. If the licensee does not file a timely request for a hearing, the Director shall issue a final notice of suspension or revocation and/or imposition of a civil fine on ATF Form 5300.13, as provided in § 478.74.</P>
    <CITA>[T.D. ATF-415, 63 FR 58278, Oct. 29, 1998, as amended by T.D. ATF-27P, 74 FR 1878, Jan. 14, 2009; T.D. ATF 2013R-9F, 79 FR 46692, Aug. 11, 2014; ATF 2008R-15P; 81 FR 32235, May 23, 2016]</CITA>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>4. Add § 478.104 to subpart F to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§ 478.104</SECTNO>
<SUBJECT>Secure gun storage or safety device.</SUBJECT>
<P>(a) Any person who applies to be a licensed firearms dealer must certify on ATF Form 7 (5310.12), Application for Federal Firearms License, that compatible secure gun storage or safety devices will be available at any place where firearms are sold under the license to nonlicensed individuals (subject to the exception that in any case in which a secure gun storage or safety device is temporarily unavailable because of theft, casualty, loss, consumer sales, backorders from a manufacturer, or any other similar reason beyond the control of the licensee, the dealer shall not be considered in violation of the requirement to make available such a device).</P>
<P>(b) Any person who applies to be a licensed firearms importer or a licensed manufacturer and will be engaged in business on the licensed premises as a dealer in the same type of firearms authorized by the license to be imported or manufactured must make the certification required under paragraph (a) of this section.</P>
<P>
(c) Each licensee described in this section must have compatible secure gun storage or safety devices available at any place in which firearms are sold under the license to persons who are not licensees. However, such licensee shall
<PRTPAGE P="194"/>
not be considered to be in violation of this requirement if a secure gun storage or safety device is temporarily unavailable because of theft, casualty loss, consumer sales, backorders from a manufacturer, or any other similar reason beyond the control of the licensee.
</P>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>5. Add § 478.12 to subpart B to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§ 478.12</SECTNO>
<SUBJECT> Definition of Frame or Receiver.</SUBJECT>
<P>(a) Except as otherwise provided in this section, the term “frame or receiver” means the following—</P>
<P>
(1) The term “frame” means the part of a handgun, or variants thereof, that provides housing or a structure for the primary energized component designed to hold back the hammer, striker, bolt, or similar component prior to initiation of the firing sequence (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
sear or equivalent), even if pins or other attachments are required to connect such component to the housing or structure.
</P>
<P>
(2) The term “receiver” means the part of a rifle, shotgun, or projectile weapon other than a handgun, or variants thereof, that provides housing or a structure for the primary component designed to block or seal the breech prior to initiation of the firing sequence (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
bolt, breechblock, or equivalent), even if pins or other attachments are required to connect such component to the housing or structure.
</P>
<P>(3) The terms “variant” and “variants thereof” mean a weapon utilizing a similar frame or receiver design irrespective of new or different model designations or configurations, characteristics, features, components, accessories, or attachments. For example, an AK-type firearm with a short stock and a pistol grip is a pistol variant of an AK-type rifle, an AR-type firearm with a short stock and a pistol grip is a pistol variant of an AR-type rifle, and a revolving cylinder shotgun is a shotgun variant of a revolver.</P>
<P>(4) The following are nonexclusive examples that illustrate the above definitions:</P>
<P>
(i)
<E T="03">Hinged or single framed revolvers:</E>
The frame is the part of the revolver that provides a structure designed to hold the sear.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="136">
<GID>ER26AP22.001</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(ii)
<E T="03">Colt 1911, Beretta/Browning/FN Herstal/Heckler & Koch/Ruger/Sig Sauer/Smith & Wesson/Taurus hammer-fired semiautomatic pistols:</E>
The frame is the lower portion of the pistol, or grip, that provides housing for the sear.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="136">
<PRTPAGE P="24736"/>
<GID>ER26AP22.002</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(iii)
<E T="03">Glock variant striker-fired semiautomatic pistols:</E>
The frame is the lower portion of the pistol, or grip, that provides housing for the sear.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="134">
<GID>ER26AP22.003</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(iv)
<E T="03">Sig Sauer P250/P320 variant semiautomatic pistols:</E>
The frame is the internal removable chassis of the pistol that provides housing for the energized component (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
sear or equivalent).
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="136">
<GID>ER26AP22.004</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(v)
<E T="03">Bolt action rifles:</E>
The receiver is the part of the rifle that provides a structure for the bolt.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="134">
<PRTPAGE P="24737"/>
<GID>ER26AP22.005</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(vi)
<E T="03">Break action, lever action, or pump action rifles and shotguns:</E>
The receiver is the part of the rifle or shotgun that provides housing for the bolt, breechblock, or equivalent.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="136">
<GID>ER26AP22.006</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(vii)
<E T="03">AK variant firearms:</E>
The receiver is the part of the weapon that provides housing for the bolt.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="134">
<GID>ER26AP22.007</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(viii)
<E T="03">Steyr AUG variant firearms:</E>
The receiver is the central part of the weapon that provides housing for the bolt.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="136">
<PRTPAGE P="24738"/>
<GID>ER26AP22.008</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(ix)
<E T="03">Thompson machineguns and semiautomatic variants, and L1A1, FN FAL, FN FNC, MP38, MP40, and SIG 550 firearms, and HK machineguns and semiautomatic variants:</E>
The receiver is the upper part of the weapon that provides housing for the bolt.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="260">
<GID>ER26AP22.009</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(x)
<E T="03">Sten, Sterling, and Kel-Tec SUB-2000 firearms:</E>
The receiver is the central part of the weapon, or tube, that provides housing for the bolt.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="139">
<GID>ER26AP22.010</GID>
</GPH>
<PRTPAGE P="24739"/>
<P>
(b)
<E T="03">Firearm muffler or silencer frame or receiver.</E>
The terms “frame” and “receiver” shall mean, in the case of a firearm muffler or firearm silencer, the part of the firearm, such as an outer tube or modular piece, that provides housing or a structure for the primary internal component designed to reduce the sound of a projectile (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
baffles, baffling material, expansion chamber, or equivalent). In the case of a modular firearm muffler or firearm silencer device with more than one such part, the terms shall mean the principal housing attached to the weapon that expels a projectile, even if an adapter or other attachments are required to connect the part to the weapon. The terms shall not include a removable end cap of an outer tube or modular piece.
</P>
<P>
(c)
<E T="03">Partially complete, disassembled, or nonfunctional frame or receiver.</E>
The terms “frame” and “receiver” shall include a partially complete, disassembled, or nonfunctional frame or receiver, including a frame or receiver parts kit, that is designed to or may readily be completed, assembled, restored, or otherwise converted to function as a frame or receiver,
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
to house or provide a structure for the primary energized component of a handgun, breech blocking or sealing component of a projectile weapon other than a handgun, or internal sound reduction component of a firearm muffler or firearm silencer, as the case may be. The terms shall not include a forging, casting, printing, extrusion, unmachined body, or similar article that has not yet reached a stage of manufacture where it is clearly identifiable as an unfinished component part of a weapon (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
unformed block of metal, liquid polymer, or other raw material). When issuing a classification, the Director may consider any associated templates, jigs, molds, equipment, tools, instructions, guides, or marketing materials that are sold, distributed, or possessed with the item or kit, or otherwise made available by the seller or distributor of the item or kit to the purchaser or recipient of the item or kit. The following are nonexclusive examples that illustrate the definitions:
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Example 1 to paragraph (c)—Frame or receiver:</E>
A frame or receiver parts kit containing a partially complete or disassembled billet or blank of a frame or receiver that is sold, distributed, or possessed with a compatible jig or template is a frame or receiver, as a person with online instructions and common hand tools may readily complete or assemble the frame or receiver parts to function as a frame or receiver.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Example 2 to paragraph (c)—Frame or receiver:</E>
A partially complete billet or blank of a frame or receiver with one or more template holes drilled or indexed in the correct location is a frame or receiver, as a person with common hand tools may readily complete the billet or blank to function as a frame or receiver.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Example 3 to paragraph (c)—Frame or receiver:</E>
A complete frame or receiver of a weapon that has been disassembled, damaged, split, or cut into pieces, but not destroyed in accordance with paragraph (e), is a frame or receiver.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Example 4 to paragraph (c)—Not a receiver:</E>
A billet or blank of an AR-15 variant receiver without critical interior areas having been indexed, machined, or formed that is not sold, distributed, or possessed with instructions, jigs, templates, equipment, or tools such that it may readily be completed is not a receiver.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Example 5 to paragraph (c)—Not a receiver:</E>
A flat blank of an AK variant receiver without laser cuts or indexing that is not sold, distributed, or possessed with instructions, jigs, templates, equipment, or tools is not a receiver, as a person cannot readily fold the flat to provide housing or a structure for the primary component designed to block or seal the breech prior to initiation of the firing sequence.
</P>
<P>
(d)
<E T="03">Multi-piece frame or receiver.</E>
The term “multi-piece frame or receiver” shall mean a frame or receiver that may be disassembled into multiple modular subparts,
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
standardized units that may be replaced or exchanged. The term shall not include the internal frame of a pistol that is a complete removable chassis that provides housing for the energized component, unless the chassis itself may be disassembled. The modular subpart(s) identified in accordance with § 478.92 with an importer's or manufacturer's serial number shall be presumed, absent an official determination by the Director or other reliable evidence to the contrary, to be part of the frame or receiver of a weapon or device.
</P>
<P>
(e)
<E T="03">Destroyed frame or receiver.</E>
The terms “frame” and “receiver” shall not include a frame or receiver that is destroyed. For purposes of these definitions, the term “destroyed” means that the frame or receiver has been permanently altered such that it may not readily be completed, assembled, restored, or otherwise converted to function as a frame or receiver. Acceptable methods of destruction include completely melting, crushing, or shredding the frame or receiver, or other method approved by the Director.
</P>
<P>
(f)(1)
<E T="03">Frame or receiver classifications based on which part of the weapon was classified as such before</E>
April 26, 2022. Except as provided in paragraph (f)(2) of this section, the terms “frame” and “receiver” shall include the specific part of a complete weapon, including variants thereof, determined (classified) by the Director to be defined as a firearm frame or receiver prior to April 26, 2022. Any such part that is identified with an importer's or manufacturer's serial number shall be presumed, absent an official determination by the Director or other reliable evidence to the contrary, to be the frame or receiver of the weapon. The following is a nonexclusive list of such weapons and the specific part determined by the Director to be the firearm frame or receiver as they existed on that date:
</P>
<P>
(i)
<E T="03">AR-15/M-16 variant firearms:</E>
The receiver is the lower part of the weapon that provides housing for the trigger mechanism and hammer (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
lower receiver).
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="132">
<PRTPAGE P="24740"/>
<GID>ER26AP22.011</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(ii)
<E T="03">Ruger Mark IV pistol:</E>
The frame is the upper part of the weapon that provides housing for the bolt or breechblock.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="136">
<GID>ER26AP22.012</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(iii)
<E T="03">Benelli 121 M1 Shotgun:</E>
The receiver is the lower part of the weapon that provides housing for the trigger mechanism.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="136">
<GID>ER26AP22.013</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(iv)
<E T="03">Vickers/Maxim, Browning 1919, M2, and box-type machineguns and semiautomatic variants:</E>
The receiver is the side plate of the weapon that is designed to hold the charging handle.
</P>
<GPH SPAN="3" DEEP="136">
<PRTPAGE P="24741"/>
<GID>ER26AP22.014</GID>
</GPH>
<P>
(2)
<E T="03">Frame or receiver classifications of partially complete, disassembled, or nonfunctional frames or receivers before</E>
April 26, 2022. Prior determinations by the Director that a partially complete, disassembled, or nonfunctional frame or receiver, including a parts kit, was not, or did not include, a “firearm frame or receiver” under § 478.11, or “frame or receiver” under § 479.11 of this subchapter, as those terms were defined prior to April 26, 2022, shall not continue to be valid or authoritative after that date. Such determinations shall include those in which the Director determined that the item or parts kit had not yet reached a stage of manufacture to be, or include, a “firearm frame or receiver” under § 478.11, or “frame or receiver” under § 479.11 of this subchapter, as those terms were defined prior to [date of publication of the rule].
</P>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<SIG>
<DATED>Dated: December 23, 2021.</DATED>
<NAME>Merrick B. Garland,</NAME>
<TITLE>Attorney General.</TITLE>
</SIG>
</SUPLINF>
<FRDOC>[FR Doc. 2021-28398 Filed 1-3-22; 8:45 am]</FRDOC>
<BILCOD>BILLING CODE 4410-FY-P</BILCOD>
</RULE>