
<RULE>
<PREAMB>
<PRTPAGE P="28968"/>
<AGENCY TYPE="S">DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE</AGENCY>
<SUBAGY>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives</SUBAGY>
<CFR>27 CFR Part 478</CFR>
<DEPDOC>[Docket No. ATF 2022R-17; AG Order No. 5920-2024]</DEPDOC>
<RIN>RIN 1140-AA58</RIN>
<SUBJECT>Definition of “Engaged in the Business” as a Dealer in Firearms</SUBJECT>
<AGY>
<HD SOURCE="HED">AGENCY:</HD>
<P>Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, Department of Justice.</P>
</AGY>
<ACT>
<HD SOURCE="HED">ACTION:</HD>
<P>Final rule.</P>
</ACT>
<SUM>
<HD SOURCE="HED">SUMMARY:</HD>
<P>The Department of Justice (“Department”) is amending Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (“ATF”) regulations to implement the provisions of the Bipartisan Safer Communities Act that broaden the definition of when a person is considered “engaged in the business” (“EIB”) as a dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or pawnbroker. This final rule incorporates the BSCA's definitions of “predominantly earn a profit” (“PEP”) and “terrorism,” and amends the regulatory definitions of “principal objective of livelihood and profit” and “engaged in the business” to ensure each conforms with the BSCA's statutory changes and can be relied upon by the public. The rule also clarifies what it means for a person to be “engaged in the business” of dealing in firearms and to have the intent to “predominantly earn a profit” from the sale or disposition of firearms. In addition, it clarifies the term “dealer” and defines the term “responsible person.” These clarifications and definitions assist persons in understanding when they are required to have a license to deal in firearms. Consistent with the Gun Control Act (“GCA”) and existing regulations, the rule also defines the term “personal collection” to clarify when persons are not “engaged in the business” because they make only occasional sales to enhance a personal collection or for a hobby, or if the firearms they sell are all or part of a personal collection. This rule further addresses the procedures that former licensees, and responsible persons acting on behalf of such licensees, must follow when they liquidate business inventory upon revocation or other termination of their license. Finally, the rule clarifies that a licensee transferring a firearm to another licensee must do so by following the verification and recordkeeping procedures in the regulations, rather than by using a Firearms Transaction Record, ATF Form 4473.</P>
</SUM>
<EFFDATE>
<HD SOURCE="HED">DATES:</HD>
<P>This rule is effective May 20, 2024.</P>
</EFFDATE>
<FURINF>
<HD SOURCE="HED">FOR FURTHER INFORMATION CONTACT:</HD>
<P>Helen Koppe, Office of Regulatory Affairs, Enforcement Programs and Services, Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives, U.S. Department of Justice, 99 New York Ave. NE, Washington DC 20226; telephone: (202) 648-7070 (this is not a toll-free number).</P>
</FURINF>
</PREAMB>
<SUPLINF>
<HD SOURCE="HED">SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION:</HD>
<EXTRACT>
<FP SOURCE="FP-2">I. Executive Summary</FP>
<FP SOURCE="FP-2">II. Background</FP>
<FP SOURCE="FP-2">III. Notice of Proposed Rulemaking</FP>
<FP SOURCE="FP-2">IV. Analysis of Comments and Department Responses</FP>
<FP SOURCE="FP-2">V. Final Rule</FP>
<FP SOURCE="FP-2">VI. Statutory and Executive Order Review</FP>
</EXTRACT>
<PART>
<HD SOURCE="HED">PART 478—COMMERCE IN FIREARMS AND AMMUNITION </HD>
</PART>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>1. The authority citation for 27 CFR part 478 continues to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<AUTH>
<HD SOURCE="HED">Authority: </HD>
<P> 5 U.S.C. 552(a); 18 U.S.C. 847, 921-931; 44 U.S.C. 3504(h).</P>
</AUTH>
</REGTEXT>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>2. Amend § 478.11 by:</AMDPAR>
<AMDPAR>a. Revising the definition of “Dealer”;</AMDPAR>
<AMDPAR>b. In the definition of “Engaged in the business”:</AMDPAR>
<AMDPAR>i. Redesignating paragraphs (a) through (f) as paragraphs (1) through (6);</AMDPAR>
<AMDPAR>
ii. Revising newly redesignated paragraph (3); and
<PRTPAGE P="29090"/>
</AMDPAR>
<AMDPAR>iii. Adding paragraph (7);</AMDPAR>
<AMDPAR>c. Adding definitions of “Former licensee inventory”, “Personal collection (or personal collection of firearms, or personal firearms collection)”, and “Predominantly earn a profit” in alphabetical order;</AMDPAR>
<AMDPAR>d. Revising the definition of “Principal objective of livelihood and profit”; and</AMDPAR>
<AMDPAR>e. Adding definitions of “Responsible person” and “Terrorism” in alphabetical order.</AMDPAR>
<P>The revisions and additions read as follows:</P>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§ 478.11 </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT> Meaning of terms.</SUBJECT>
<STARS/>
<P>
<E T="03">Dealer.</E>
Any person engaged in the business of selling firearms at wholesale or retail; any person engaged in the business of repairing firearms or of making or fitting special barrels, stocks, or trigger mechanisms to firearms; or any person who is a pawnbroker. The term shall include any person who engages in such business or occupation on a part-time basis. The term shall include such activities wherever, or through whatever medium, they are conducted, such as at a gun show or event, flea market, auction house, or gun range or club; at one's home; by mail order; over the internet (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
online broker or auction); through the use of other electronic means (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
text messaging service, social media raffle, or website); or at any other domestic or international public or private marketplace or premises.
</P>
<STARS/>
<P>
<E T="03">Engaged in the business—</E>
* * *
</P>
<P>
(3)
<E T="03">Dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or a pawnbroker.</E>
The term “engaged in the business as a dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or a pawnbroker” shall have the same meaning as in § 478.13.
</P>
<STARS/>
<P>
(7)
<E T="03">Related definitions.</E>
For purposes of this definition—
</P>
<P>(i) The term “purchase” (and derivative terms thereof) means the act of obtaining a firearm in an agreed exchange for something of value;</P>
<P>(ii) The term “sale” (and derivative terms thereof) means the act of disposing of a firearm in an agreed exchange for something of value, and the term “resale” means selling a firearm, including a stolen firearm, after it was previously sold by the original manufacturer or any other person; and</P>
<P>
(iii) The term “something of value” includes money, credit, personal property (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
another firearm or ammunition), a service, a controlled substance, or any other medium of exchange or valuable consideration, legal or illegal.
</P>
<STARS/>
<P>
<E T="03">Former licensee inventory.</E>
Firearms that were in the business inventory of a licensee at the time the license was terminated. Such firearms differ from a personal collection and other personal firearms in that they were purchased repetitively before the license was terminated as part of a licensee's business inventory with the predominant intent to earn a profit.
</P>
<STARS/>
<P>
<E T="03">Personal collection (or personal collection of firearms, or personal firearms collection)</E>
—(1)
<E T="03">General definition.</E>
Personal firearms that a person accumulates for study, comparison, exhibition (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
collecting curios or relics, or collecting unique firearms to exhibit at gun club events), or for a hobby (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
noncommercial, recreational activities for personal enjoyment, such as hunting, skeet, target, or competition shooting, historical re-enactment, or noncommercial firearms safety instruction). The term shall not include any firearm purchased for the purpose of resale with the predominant intent to earn a profit (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
primarily for a commercial purpose or financial gain, as distinguished from personal firearms a person accumulates for study, comparison, exhibition, or for a hobby, but which the person may also intend to increase in value). In addition, the term shall not include firearms accumulated primarily for personal protection:
<E T="03">Provided,</E>
that nothing in this definition shall be construed as precluding a person from lawfully acquiring firearms for self-protection or other lawful personal use.
</P>
<P>
(2)
<E T="03">Personal collection of licensee.</E>
In the case of a firearm imported, manufactured, or otherwise acquired by a licensed manufacturer, licensed importer, or licensed dealer, the term shall include only a firearm described in paragraph (1) of this definition that was—
</P>
<P>(i) Acquired or transferred without the intent to willfully evade the restrictions placed upon licensees under 18 U.S.C. chapter 44;</P>
<P>(ii) Recorded by the licensee as an acquisition in the licensee's acquisition and disposition record in accordance with § 478.122(a), § 478.123(a), or § 478.125(e) (unless acquired prior to licensure and not intended for sale);</P>
<P>(iii) Recorded as a disposition from the licensee's business inventory to the licensee's personal collection or otherwise as a personal firearm in accordance with § 478.122(a), § 478.123(a), or § 478.125(e) (unless acquired prior to licensure and not intended for sale);</P>
<P>(iv) Maintained in such personal collection or otherwise as a personal firearm (whether on or off the business premises) for at least one year from the date the firearm was so transferred, in accordance with 18 U.S.C. 923(c) and 27 CFR 478.125a; and</P>
<P>
(v) Stored separately from, and not commingled with the business inventory. When stored or displayed on the business premises, the personal collection and other personal firearms shall be appropriately identified as “not for sale” (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
by attaching a tag).
</P>
<STARS/>
<P>
<E T="03">Predominantly earn a profit.</E>
The term “predominantly earn a profit” shall have the same meaning as in § 478.13.
</P>
<P>
<E T="03">Principal objective of livelihood and profit.</E>
The intent underlying the sale or disposition of firearms is predominantly one of obtaining livelihood and pecuniary gain, as opposed to other intents such as improving or liquidating a personal firearms collection:
<E T="03">Provided,</E>
That proof of profit shall not be required as to a person who engages in the regular and repetitive purchase and disposition of firearms for criminal purposes or terrorism.
</P>
<STARS/>
<P>
<E T="03">Responsible person.</E>
Any individual possessing, directly or indirectly, the power to direct or cause the direction of the management and policies of a sole proprietorship, corporation, company, partnership, or association, insofar as they pertain to firearms.
</P>
<STARS/>
<P>
<E T="03">Terrorism.</E>
For purposes of the definitions “predominantly earn a profit” and “principal objective of livelihood and profit,” the term “terrorism” means activity, directed against United States persons, which—
</P>
<P>(1) Is committed by an individual who is not a national or permanent resident alien of the United States;</P>
<P>(2) Involves violent acts or acts dangerous to human life which would be a criminal violation if committed within the jurisdiction of the United States; and</P>
<P>(3) Is intended—</P>
<P>(i) To intimidate or coerce a civilian population;</P>
<P>(ii) To influence the policy of a government by intimidation or coercion; or</P>
<P>(iii) To affect the conduct of a government by assassination or kidnapping.</P>
<STARS/>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>3. Add § 478.13 to subpart B to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
<PRTPAGE P="29091"/>
<SECTNO>§478.13 </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT> Definition of “engaged in the business as a dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or a pawnbroker.”</SUBJECT>
<P>
(a)
<E T="03">Definition.</E>
A person who devotes time, attention, and labor to dealing in firearms as a regular course of trade or business to predominantly earn a profit through the repetitive purchase and resale of firearms. The term shall not include a person who makes occasional sales, exchanges, or purchases of firearms for the enhancement of a personal collection or for a hobby, or who sells all or part of the person's personal collection of firearms. In addition, the term shall not include an auctioneer who provides only auction services on commission to assist in liquidating firearms at an estate-type auction;
<E T="03">provided,</E>
that the auctioneer does not purchase the firearms, or take possession of the firearms for sale on consignment.
</P>
<P>
(b)
<E T="03">Fact-specific inquiry.</E>
Whether a person is engaged in the business as a dealer under paragraph (a) of this section is a fact-specific inquiry. Selling large numbers of firearms or engaging or offering to engage in frequent transactions may be highly indicative of business activity. However, there is no minimum threshold number of firearms purchased or sold that triggers the licensing requirement. Similarly, there is no minimum number of transactions that determines whether a person is “engaged in the business” of dealing in firearms. For example, even a single firearm transaction or offer to engage in a transaction, when combined with other evidence (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
where a person represents to others a willingness and ability to purchase more firearms for resale), may require a license; whereas, a single isolated firearm transaction without such evidence would not require a license. At all times, the determination of whether a person is engaged in the business of dealing in firearms is based on the totality of the circumstances.
</P>
<P>
(c)
<E T="03">Presumptions that a person is engaged in the business as a dealer.</E>
In civil and administrative proceedings, a person shall be presumed to be engaged in the business of dealing in firearms as defined in paragraph (a) of this section, absent reliable evidence to the contrary, when it is shown that the person—
</P>
<P>
(1) Resells or offers for resale firearms, and also represents to potential buyers or otherwise demonstrates a willingness and ability to purchase and resell additional firearms (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
to be a source of additional firearms for resale);
</P>
<P>(2) Repetitively purchases for the purpose of resale, or repetitively resells or offers for resale, firearms—</P>
<P>(i) Through straw or sham businesses, or individual straw purchasers or sellers; or</P>
<P>(ii) That cannot lawfully be purchased, received, or possessed under Federal, State, local, or Tribal law, including:</P>
<P>
(A) Stolen firearms (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
18 U.S.C. 922(j));
</P>
<P>
(B) Firearms with the licensee's serial number removed, obliterated, or altered, or not identified as required by law (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
18 U.S.C. 922(k) or 26 U.S.C. 5861(i));
</P>
<P>
(C) Firearms imported in violation of law (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
18 U.S.C. 922(l), 22 U.S.C. 2778, or 26 U.S.C. 5844, 5861(k)); or
</P>
<P>
(D) Machineguns or other weapons defined as firearms under 26 U.S.C. 5845(b) that cannot lawfully be possessed (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
18 U.S.C. 922(o); 26 U.S.C. 5861(d));
</P>
<P>(3) Repetitively resells or offers for resale firearms—</P>
<P>(i) Within 30 days after the person purchased the firearms; or</P>
<P>(ii) Within one year after the person purchased the firearms if they are—</P>
<P>(A) New, or like new in their original packaging; or</P>
<P>(B) The same make and model, or variants thereof;</P>
<P>
(4) As a former licensee (or responsible person acting on behalf of the former licensee), resells or offers for resale to a person (other than a licensee in accordance with § 478.57 or § 478.78) firearms that were in the business inventory of the former licensee at the time the license was terminated (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
license revocation, denial of license renewal, license expiration, or surrender of license), whether or not such firearms were transferred to a responsible person of the former licensee after the license was terminated in accordance with § 478.57(b)(2) or § 478.78(b)(2); or
</P>
<P>(5) As a former licensee (or responsible person acting on behalf of the former licensee), resells or offers for resale firearms that were transferred to the licensee's personal collection or otherwise as personal firearms in accordance with 18 U.S.C. 923(c) and 27 CFR 478.125a(a) prior to the time the license was terminated, unless:</P>
<P>(i) The firearms were received and transferred without any intent to willfully evade the restrictions placed on licensees by 18 U.S.C. chapter 44; and</P>
<P>(ii) One year has passed from the date of transfer to the licensee's personal collection or otherwise as personal firearms.</P>
<P>
(d)
<E T="03">Predominantly earn a profit</E>
—(1)
<E T="03">Definition.</E>
The intent underlying the sale or disposition of firearms is predominantly one of obtaining pecuniary gain, as opposed to other intents, such as improving or liquidating a personal firearms collection:
<E T="03">Provided,</E>
that proof of profit, including the intent to profit, shall not be required as to a person who engages in the regular and repetitive purchase and disposition of firearms for criminal purposes or terrorism. For purposes of this section, a person may have the intent to profit even if the person does not actually obtain the intended pecuniary gain from the sale or disposition of firearms.
</P>
<P>
(2)
<E T="03">Presumptions that a person has intent to predominantly earn a profit.</E>
In civil and administrative proceedings, a person shall be presumed to have the intent to predominantly earn a profit through the repetitive purchase and resale of firearms as defined in paragraph (d)(1) of this section, absent reliable evidence to the contrary, when it is shown that the person—
</P>
<P>
(i) Repetitively or continuously advertises, markets, or otherwise promotes a firearms business (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
advertises or posts firearms for resale, including through the internet or other digital means, establishes a website to offer their firearms for resale, makes available business cards, or tags firearms with sales prices), regardless of whether the person incurs expenses or only promotes the business informally;
</P>
<P>(ii) Repetitively or continuously purchases, rents, or otherwise exchanges (directly or indirectly) something of value to secure permanent or temporary physical space to display firearms they offer for resale, including part or all of a business premises, a table or space at a gun show, or a display case;</P>
<P>(iii) Makes and maintains records to document, track, or calculate profits and losses from firearms repetitively purchased for resale;</P>
<P>
(iv) Purchases or otherwise secures merchant services as a business (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
credit card transaction services, digital wallet for business) through which the person intends to repetitively accept payments for firearms transactions;
</P>
<P>
(v) Formally or informally purchases, hires, or otherwise secures business security services (
<E T="03">e.g.,</E>
a central station-monitored security system registered to a business, or guards for security) to protect firearms assets and repetitive firearms transactions;
</P>
<P>(vi) Formally or informally establishes a business entity, trade name, or online business account, including an account using a business name on a social media or other website, through which the person makes, or offers to make, repetitive firearms transactions; or</P>
<P>
(vii) Secures or applies for a State or local business license to purchase for
<PRTPAGE P="29092"/>
resale or to resell merchandise that includes firearms.
</P>
<P>
(e)
<E T="03">Conduct that does not support a presumption.</E>
A person shall not be presumed to be engaged in the business of dealing in firearms when reliable evidence shows that the person is only reselling or otherwise transferring firearms—
</P>
<P>(1) As bona fide gifts;</P>
<P>(2) Occasionally to obtain more valuable, desirable, or useful firearms for the person's personal collection;</P>
<P>(3) Occasionally to a licensee or to a family member for lawful purposes;</P>
<P>(4) To liquidate (without restocking) all or part of the person's personal collection; or</P>
<P>(5) To liquidate firearms—</P>
<P>(i) That are inherited; or</P>
<P>(ii) Pursuant to a court order; or</P>
<P>(6) To assist in liquidating firearms as an auctioneer when providing auction services on commission at an estate-type auction.</P>
<P>
(f)
<E T="03">Rebuttal evidence.</E>
Reliable evidence of the conduct set forth in paragraph (e) of this section may be used to rebut any presumption in paragraph (c) or (d)(2) of this section that a person is engaged in the business of dealing in firearms, or intends to predominantly earn a profit through the repetitive purchase and resale of firearms.
</P>
<P>
(g)
<E T="03">Presumptions, conduct, and rebuttal evidence not exhaustive.</E>
The activities set forth in the rebuttable presumptions in paragraphs (c) and (d)(2) of this section, and the activities and rebuttal evidence set forth in paragraphs (e) and (f) of this section, are not exhaustive of the conduct or evidence that may be considered in determining whether a person is engaged in the business of dealing in firearms, or has the intent to predominantly earn a profit through the repetitive purchase and resale of firearms.
</P>
<P>
(h)
<E T="03">Criminal proceedings.</E>
The rebuttable presumptions in paragraphs (c) and (d)(2) of this section shall not apply to any criminal case, although they may be useful to courts in criminal cases, for example, when instructing juries regarding permissible inferences.
</P>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>4. Amend § 478.57 by designating the undesignated paragraph as paragraph (a) and adding paragraphs (b) through (d) to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§478.57 </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT> Discontinuance of business.</SUBJECT>
<STARS/>
<P>
(b) Upon termination of a license (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
license revocation, denial of license renewal, license expiration, or surrender of license), the former licensee shall within 30 days, or such additional period approved by the Director for good cause, either:
</P>
<P>(1) Liquidate the former licensee inventory by selling or otherwise disposing of the firearms to a licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer for sale, auction, or pawn redemption in accordance with this part; or</P>
<P>(2) Transfer the former licensee inventory to a responsible person of the former licensee to whom the receipt, possession, sale, or other disposition is not prohibited by law. Any such transfer, however, does not negate the fact that the firearms were repetitively purchased, and were purchased with the predominant intent to earn a profit by repetitive purchase and resale.</P>
<P>(c) Transfers of former licensee inventory to a licensee or responsible person in accordance with paragraph (b)(1) or (2) of this section shall be appropriately recorded as dispositions, in accordance with § 478.122(b), § 478.123(b), or § 478.125(e), prior to delivering the records after discontinuing business consistent with § 478.127. Except for liquidation of former licensee inventory to a licensee within 30 days (or approved period) in accordance with paragraph (b)(1) of this section, or occasional sale of a firearm from such inventory thereafter to a licensee, a former licensee (or responsible person of such licensee) who resells any such inventory, including former licensee inventory transferred in accordance with paragraph (b)(2) of this section, is subject to the presumptions in § 478.13 (definition of “engaged in the business as a dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or pawnbroker”) that apply to a person who repetitively purchased those firearms for the purpose of resale.</P>
<P>
(d) The former licensee shall not continue to engage in the business of importing, manufacturing, or dealing in firearms by importing or manufacturing additional firearms for purposes of sale or distribution, or purchasing additional firearms for resale (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
“restocking”).
</P>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>5. Amend § 478.78 by designating the undesignated paragraph as paragraph (a) and adding paragraphs (b) through (d) to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§478.78 </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT> Operations by licensee after notice.</SUBJECT>
<STARS/>
<P>
(b) Upon final disposition of license proceedings to disapprove or terminate a license (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
by revocation or denial of renewal), the former licensee shall within 30 days, or such additional period approved by the Director for good cause, either:
</P>
<P>(1) Liquidate the former licensee inventory by selling or otherwise disposing of the firearms to a licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer for sale, auction, or pawn redemption in accordance with this part; or</P>
<P>(2) Transfer the former licensee inventory to a responsible person of the former licensee to whom the receipt, possession, sale, or other disposition is not prohibited by law. Any such transfer, however, does not negate the fact that the firearms were repetitively purchased, and were purchased with the predominant intent to earn a profit by repetitive purchase and resale.</P>
<P>(c) Transfers of former licensee inventory to a licensee or responsible person in accordance with paragraph (b)(1) or (2) of this section shall be appropriately recorded as dispositions, in accordance with § 478.122(b), § 478.123(b), or § 478.125(e), prior to delivering the records after discontinuing business consistent with § 478.127. Except for the sale of former licensee inventory to a licensee within 30 days (or approved period) in accordance with paragraph (b)(1) of this section, or occasional sale of a firearm from such inventory thereafter to a licensee, a former licensee (or responsible person of such former licensee) who resells any such inventory, including former licensee inventory transferred in accordance with paragraph (b)(2) of this section, is subject to the presumptions in § 478.13 (definition of “engaged in the business as a dealer in firearms other than a gunsmith or pawnbroker”) that apply to a person who repetitively purchased those firearms for the purpose of resale.</P>
<P>
(d) The former licensee shall not continue to engage in the business of importing, manufacturing, or dealing in firearms by importing or manufacturing additional firearms for purposes of sale or distribution, or purchasing additional firearms for resale (
<E T="03">i.e.,</E>
“restocking”).
</P>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>6. Amend § 478.124 by revising paragraph (a) to read as follows:</AMDPAR>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§478.124 </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT> Firearms transaction record.</SUBJECT>
<P>
(a) A licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer shall not sell or otherwise dispose, temporarily or permanently, of any firearm to any person, other than another licensee, unless the licensee records the transaction on a firearm transaction record, Form 4473:
<E T="03">Provided,</E>
that a firearms transaction record, Form 4473, shall not be required to record the disposition made of a firearm delivered to a licensee for the sole purpose of repair or customizing when such firearm or a replacement
<PRTPAGE P="29093"/>
firearm is returned to the person from whom received;
<E T="03">provided further,</E>
that a firearms transaction record, Form 4473, shall not be used if the sale or other disposition is being made to another licensed importer, licensed manufacturer, or licensed dealer, or a curio or relic to a licensed collector, including a sole proprietor who transfers a firearm to their personal collection or otherwise as a personal firearm in accordance with § 478.125a. When a licensee transfers a firearm to another licensee, the licensee shall comply with the verification and recordkeeping requirements in § 478.94 and this subpart.
</P>
<STARS/>
</SECTION>
</REGTEXT>
<SECTION>
<SECTNO>§ 478.125a </SECTNO>
<SUBJECT>[Amended]</SUBJECT>
</SECTION>
<REGTEXT TITLE="27" PART="478">
<AMDPAR>7. Amend § 478.125a in paragraphs (a)(2) and (3) by removing the citation “§ 478.125(e)” and adding in its place “§ 478.122(a), § 478.123(a), or § 478.125(e)”.</AMDPAR>
</REGTEXT>
<SIG>
<DATED>Dated: April 8, 2024.</DATED>
<NAME>Merrick B. Garland,</NAME>
<TITLE>Attorney General.</TITLE>
</SIG>
</SUPLINF>
<FRDOC>[FR Doc. 2024-07838 Filed 4-18-24; 8:45 am]</FRDOC>
<BILCOD>BILLING CODE 4410-FY-P</BILCOD>
</RULE>